<?xml version="1.0"?>
<county id="anglesey">
    <name lang="en">Anglesey</name>
    <name lang="cy">Ynys Môn</name>
    <population href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Welsh_principal_areas_by_population">69900</population>
    <about lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglesey">Anglesey","extract":"Anglesey (Welsh: Ynys M\u00f4n, [\u02c8\u0259n\u0268s \u02c8mo\u02d0n]) is an island off the north-west coast of Wales. With an area of 714 square kilometres (276 sq mi), Anglesey is the largest island of Wales and the fifth-largest island surrounding Great Britain (and the largest outside of Scotland). Anglesey is also the largest island in the Irish Sea by area, and the second most populous island in the Irish Sea (after the Isle of Man). The actual population taken at the 2011 census was 69,751. Two bridges span the Menai Strait, connecting the island to the mainland: the Menai Suspension Bridge, designed by Thomas Telford in 1826, and the Britannia Bridge.\nFormerly a historic county of Wales and later part of Gwynedd, Anglesey today makes up the Isle of Anglesey County along with Holy Island and other smaller islands. Almost three-quarters of Anglesey's inhabitants are Welsh speakers and Ynys M\u00f4n, the Welsh name for the island, is used for the UK Parliament and National Assembly constituencies.</about>
    <about lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ynys_M%C3%B4n">Sir ac ynys yng ngogledd-orllewin Cymru yw Ynys Môn (Saesneg: Anglesey, Lladin: Mona). Gwahenir yr ynys oddi wrth y tir mawr gan gulfor Afon Menai. Cysylltir y tir mawr â'r ynys gan ddwy bont, y bont wreiddiol Pont Y Borth a godwyd gan Thomas Telford ym 1826 a'r un fwy, Pont Britannia sydd yn cysylltu'r A55 â'r ynys ynghyd â Rheilffordd Arfordir Gogledd Cymru. Ymhlith yr ynysoedd llai o gwmpas arfordir Môn mae Ynys Gybi, Ynys Seiriol, Ynys Llanddwyn ac Ynys Moelfre. Dynodwyd arfordir yr ynys yn Ardal o Harddwch Naturiol Eithriadol, ac mae Llwybr Arfordirol Ynys Môn yn mynd o'i chwmpas. Er i rannau o'r sir gael eu Seisnigeiddio dros y degawdau diweddar wrth i bobl symud yno i fyw o Loegr a llefydd eraill, erys Môn yn un o gadarnleoedd yr iaith Gymraeg a gellir cyfrif rhan sylweddol ohoni yn rhan o'r Fro Gymraeg. Gweinyddir y sir gan Gyngor Sir Ynys Môn sydd â'i bencadlys yn Llangefni.</about>
    <postcodes>
        <postcode>LL58</postcode>
        <postcode>LL59</postcode>
        <postcode>LL60</postcode>
        <postcode>LL61</postcode>
        <postcode>LL62</postcode>
        <postcode>LL64</postcode>
        <postcode>LL65</postcode>
        <postcode>LL66</postcode>
        <postcode>LL67</postcode>
        <postcode>LL68</postcode>
        <postcode>LL69</postcode>
        <postcode>LL70</postcode>
        <postcode>LL71</postcode>
        <postcode>LL72</postcode>
        <postcode>LL73</postcode>
        <postcode>LL74</postcode>
        <postcode>LL75</postcode>
        <postcode>LL76</postcode>
        <postcode>LL77</postcode>
        <postcode>LL78</postcode>
    </postcodes>
    <towns>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#aberffraw">
            <name>Aberffraw</name>
            <lat>53.19196</lat>
            <lon>-4.463753</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberffraw">Aberffraw (Welsh: Aberffro) is a small village and community on the south west coast of the Isle of Anglesey (Welsh: Ynys Môn), in Wales, by the west bank of the River Ffraw. Access by road is by way of the A4080 and the nearest rail station is Bodorgan. In the early Middle Ages Aberffraw was the capital of the Kingdom of Gwynedd from c.860 AD until c.1170. Under the eponymous Aberffraw Dynasty it came to be the most important political centre in medieval Wales. The Llys remained the symbolic throne of the Kings of Gwynedd from the 9th century to the 13th century. The Royal Annals of Edward I of England show the Llys was dismantled in 1315 to provide building materials for nearby Beaumaris Castle.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberffraw">Mae Aberffraw yn bentref ar arfordir gorllewinol Ynys Môn, rhwng Rhosneigr a Llangadwaladr, yng ngogledd Cymru. Mae'n cymryd ei enw o Afon Ffraw. Yn Oes y Tywysogion Aberffraw oedd maenor cwmwd Malltraeth, cantref Aberffraw. Ers cyfnod cynnar iawn roedd yn gartref i brif lys teyrnas Gwynedd, cartref traddodiadol brenhinoedd a thywysogion Gwynedd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#alaw">
            <name>Alaw</name>
            <lat>53.2939122</lat>
            <lon>-4.5013224</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#amlwch">
            <name>Amlwch</name>
            <lat>53.410658</lat>
            <lon>-4.345693</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amlwch">Amlwch (Welsh pronunciation: [ˈamlʊχ]) is a community and the most northerly town in Wales. It is situated on the north coast of the Isle of Anglesey, on the A5025 which connects it to Holyhead and to Menai Bridge. The town has no beach, but it has impressive coastal cliffs. Tourism is an important element of the local economy. At one time it was a busy port, with boats sailing to the Isle of Man and to Liverpool. A number of the houses date from the 19th century and add to the atmosphere of the town.
            The local newspaper for northeastern Anglesey is Yr Arwydd ('The Sign'). Yr Arwydd is the local Welsh name for Mynydd Bodafon, the paper covers the area surrounding the mountain, and has an image of the summit as its logo.
            The name Amlwch – a reference to the site of the town's harbour, Porth Amlwch – derives from Welsh am ("about, on or around") and llwch (an old word meaning "inlet, creek" - similar to the Gaelic word "loch" for a body of water).
            According to legend in the Middle Ages, the town developed on a site that had a harbour but was not visible from the sea, which helped to reduce the chance of Viking attacks.
            It grew rapidly in the 18th century near what was then the world's biggest copper mine at the nearby Parys Mountain. By the late 18th century, Amlwch had a population of around 10,000 and was the second largest town in Wales after Merthyr Tydfil. It was at this time that its harbour was also extended to accommodate the ships needed to transport the ore. At the 2011 census the Community had a population of 3,789.
            When copper mining began to decline in the mid-1850s, shipbuilding became the main industry with many people also becoming involved in the ship repair and other maritime industries. The town was home to a brewing industry and also had tobacco works, producing the famous Amlwch Shag Tobacco - "Baco Shag Amlwch". Even after the decline of the copper mine some chemical industries remained and in 1953 a chemical plant to extract bromine from sea water (for use in petrol engines) was built but this closed in 2004.
            At the peak of the copper mining, it is believed that Amlwch had a record of public house to person ratio, with there being one pub for every four people. Today the ratio is nowhere near that mark but you can find pubs such as the King's Head, the Queen's Head, the Mariner, the Dinorben Arms Hotel and the Market Tavern in the town, and the Liverpool Arms and the Adelphi Vaults down in the port area. It also used to have a station, the northern terminus of the Anglesey Central Railway which was open between 1864 and 1993. There are some that would like to see the line restored, including the County Council's Economic Development Representative and consultants English, Welsh &amp; Scottish Railway, believing that it would be beneficial for the local tourism industry as well as providing further public transport, linking the town with Bangor via rail.
            Attractions in Amlwch include its restored port, the Anglesey Coastal Path which passes through it, its watch tower containing an exhibition by Geo Môn, maritime and copper mining museums, St Eleth's Church (which dates from 1800) and the reinforced concrete Catholic church Our Lady Star of the Sea and St Winefride, built in 1937. The town's leisure centre is one of the few on Anglesey and has a swimming pool, sports centre and squash courts. It is situated on Anglesey's 125-mile stretch of coast that is designated Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty, and the coastal walks and heritage walks provide for unique and spectacular views.
            The town also has two football clubs, Amlwch Town F.C., who play in the Welsh Alliance League, and the Adelphi Vaults F.C., a Sunday League pub team currently playing in the My Scaffolding League Division 1.
            Amlwch has a sea rowing club based in Bull Bay, Trireme Ynys Mon Rowing Club. Training takes place Tuesday and Thursday evenings, and Sunday mornings. The club is the most successful rowing club in North Wales, and competes in the Welsh Sea Rowing Association League.
            It is also home to the local secondary school, Ysgol Syr Thomas Jones which Lemmy attended, and the town also has a primary school. The high street is home to a number of small private businesses, many with a unique and boutique feel.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amlwch">Tref fach yng ngogledd Môn yw Amlwch, ar lôn yr A5025 tua 15 milltir i'r gogledd o Borthaethwy, hanner ffordd rhwng Cemaes a Moelfre. Mae Caerdydd 229.2 km i ffwrdd o Amlwch ac mae Llundain yn 356.8 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 25.5 km i ffwrdd.
            Tref sy'n gorwedd ar lan y môr yw hi, heb draeth ond gyda chlogwynni arfordirol trawiadol. Mae twristiaeth yn elfen bwysig yn yr economi leol. Ar un adeg roedd yn borthladd eithaf prysur gyda llongau yn hwylio oddi yno i Ynys Manaw a Lerpwl. Mae nifer o'r tai yn dyddio o'r 19eg ganrif ac yn ychwanegu at awyrgylch y dref.
            Yr Arwydd yw papur bro Benllech a gweddill cylch Mynydd Bodafon.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#amlwch port">
            <name>Amlwch Port</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amlwch Port">Amlwch Port is a port village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#anglesey">
            <name>Anglesey</name>
            <lat>53.2692804</lat>
            <lon>-4.3212852</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglesey">Anglesey (Welsh: Ynys Môn, [ˈənɨs ˈmoːn]) is an island off the north-west coast of Wales. With an area of 714 square kilometres (276 sq mi), Anglesey is the largest island of Wales and the fifth-largest island surrounding Great Britain (and the largest outside of Scotland). Anglesey is also the largest island in the Irish Sea by area, and the second most populous island in the Irish Sea (after the Isle of Man). The actual population taken at the 2011 census was 69,751. Two bridges span the Menai Strait, connecting the island to the mainland: the Menai Suspension Bridge, designed by Thomas Telford in 1826, and the Britannia Bridge.
            Formerly a historic county of Wales and later part of Gwynedd, Anglesey today makes up the Isle of Anglesey County along with Holy Island and other smaller islands. Almost three-quarters of Anglesey's inhabitants are Welsh speakers and Ynys Môn, the Welsh name for the island, is used for the UK Parliament and National Assembly constituencies.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bachau">
            <name>Bachau</name>
            <lat>53.328379</lat>
            <lon>-4.355078</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachau">Bachau is a small rural hamlet of about a dozen dwellings in Anglesey, north Wales, which is 137 miles (220.5 km) from Cardiff and 218.1 miles (351 km) from London. Bachau is represented in the National Assembly for Wales by Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) and the Member of Parliament is Albert Owen (Labour Party).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachau">Pentrefan tua chilometr o Lannerch-y-medd, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Bachau. Mae 137 milltir (220.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.1 milltir (351 km) o Lundain.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#beaumaris">
            <name>Beaumaris</name>
            <lat>53.265865</lat>
            <lon>-4.09199</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beaumaris">Beaumaris (/bjuːˈmærɨs/; Welsh: Biwmares [bɪuˈmɑːrɛs]) is a former royal borough, a community, and the former county town of Anglesey, Wales. It was located in the commote of Dindaethwy and historic rural deanery of Tindaethwy, and is at the eastern entrance to the Menai Strait, the tidal waterway separating Anglesey from the coast of North Wales. At the 2001 census it had a population of 2,040, reducing to 1,938 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biwmares">Mae Biwmares (Saesneg: Beaumaris) yn dref hanesyddol yn ne-ddwyrain Ynys Môn, ar lan Afon Menai. Enw Ffrangeg Normanaidd sydd i'r dref a'i ystyr yw Morfa Deg.
            Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2011, roedd 1,892 o bobl yn byw yn y gymuned hon a 748 (sef 39.5%) o'r boblogaeth dros dair oed a hŷn yn gallu siarad Cymraeg.[2] Roedd 448 yn ddi-waith, sef 45.7% o'r rhai o fewn yr oedran priodol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#benllech">
            <name>Benllech</name>
            <lat>53.321861</lat>
            <lon>-4.225891</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benllech">Benllech is a small town on the Isle of Anglesey in Wales. It is in the community of Llanfair-Mathafarn-Eithaf, which has a population of 3,382, making it the 5th largest town by population on the island. The name of Benllech village had been removed by the time of the 2011 census with the community being listed under Llanfair-Mathafarn-Eithaf with the electoral ward being listed under Llanddyfnan.
            The name Benllech is perhaps a mutated form of penllech, literally "head slab" or "head rock", i.e. "capstone" or "head of the rock", or possibly meaning 'on slate', shortened from the Welsh term 'ar ben llech'.
            Benllech is a popular beach holiday destination. Winner of the European Blue Flag award since 2004, the beach shelves and has an abundance of clean yellow sand and looks out toward the Great Orme and Penmon Point. The Anglesey Coastal Path and Wales Coast Path pass through Benllech. The village won the 'tidiest village on Anglesey' competition in the years 1973–79 and was also awarded a Civic Trust Award which recognises the very best in architecture, design, planning, landscape and public art. The award was given to projects of the highest quality design, which have made a positive cultural, social and economic contribution to the local community.
            The village has a range of businesses which include public houses and hotels, camping and caravan sites and several bed and breakfasts. The community has a primary school, Ysgol Goronwy Owen; library, doctors' surgery, chemist, several churches, community centre, police and fire station, tennis court and bowling green, and most recently a Tesco Express supermarket. Between 1909 and 1950 there was a railway station close to the village which was the terminus of the Red Wharf Bay branch line. The old station house still exists and several railway bridges can be seen along the road approaching the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benllech">Tref ar arfordir ddwyreiniol Ynys Môn, ym mhwlyf Llanfair Mathafarn Eithaf yw Benllech. Fe'i lleolir 7 milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Borthaethwy ar lôn yr A5025, hanner ffordd rhwng Pentraeth a Moelfre. Mae ar Lwybr Arfordirol Ynys Mon. Mae'n ganolfan gwyliau glan-môr boblogaidd yn yr haf ac mae twristiaeth yn chwarae rhan bwysig yn yr economi leol. Mae nifer o dai newydd a byngalos yn gymysg â thai hŷn yn y dref. Mae Traeth Benllech yn lân a diogel. I'r gorllewin ceir meysydd carafanau ar gyfer ymwelwyr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bethel">
            <name>Bethel</name>
            <lat>53.16313</lat>
            <lon>-4.212325</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethel,_Anglesey">Bethel is a relatively small and quiet village set centrally within the wider community and larger Parish of Bodorgan. The village is located inland (approximately three miles) from the south-western coast on the isle of Anglesey in North Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethel,_Ynys_M%C3%B4n">Pentref bychan ar Ynys Môn yw Bethel. Mae'n un o sawl lle a enwir ar ôl y dref Feiblaidd Bethel (Hebraeg: בֵּית־אֵל Bet El, yn golygy "Tŷ Dduw"). Yn yr achos yma enwir y pentref ar ôl Capel Bethel a godwyd yno.
            Gorwedd Bethel ar ffordd y B4422 tua milltir i'gogledd o bentref Llangadwaladr a thua dwy filltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Falltraeth.
            Tua chwarter milltir i'r de o Fethel ceir Llyn Coron.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bodedern">
            <name>Bodedern</name>
            <lat>53.294814</lat>
            <lon>-4.502152</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodedern">Bodedern is a village and community in the west of Anglesey, Wales. At the 2001 census, it had a population of 1,074, decreasing slightly to 1,051 at the 2011 census. The village has a bilingual primary school, Ysgol Gynradd Bodedern, and secondary school, Ysgol Uwchradd Bodedern. The village's football team, Bodedern Athletic F.C. play in the Welsh Alliance League. Bodedern is the closest village to the island's largest natural lake, Llyn Llywenan, 1 kilometre (0.6 mi) to the north. The parish church (St Edern's Church, Bodedern) dates from the 14th century and is a Grade II* listed building. The Valley Wetlands are the other side of the A55 about 2 miles from Bodedern.
            Presaddfed Hall is a small grade II* listed country house which stands amongst woodlands to the north-east of the village at the southern tip of Llyn Llywenan. The main block was built in 1686 and is joined to an earlier block by a later block built in 1875. A walled garden lies to the east of the house  Once the seat of the Lewis family, several of whom served as High Sheriff of Anglesey, it is now a country hotel.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodedern">Pentref a chymuned yng ngorllewin Ynys Môn yw Bodedern. Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2011, roedd 1,016 o bobl yn byw yn y gymuned hon a 718 (sef 70.7%) o'r boblogaeth dros dair oed a hŷn yn gallu siarad Cymraeg. Roedd 142 yn ddi-waith, sef 32.1% o'r rhai o fewn yr oedran priodol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bodewryd">
            <name>Bodewryd</name>
            <lat>53.387309</lat>
            <lon>-4.405427</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodewryd">Bodewryd is a village in Anglesey, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodewryd">Cymuned wledig ar Ynys Môn yw Bodewryd. Mae'n gorwedd yng ngogledd yr ynys tua dwy filltir i'r dwyrain o Llanfechell a thair milltir a hanner i'r de-orllewin o Amlwch.
            Mae'r enw yn golygu 'Annedd Ewryd', ar ôl y sant cynnar Ewryd/Gerwyd (Lladin: Euridius), sydd fel arall yn anhysbys. Yr unig beth a wyddys amdano yw ei fod, yn ôl traddodiad, yn un o feibion Cynyr Ceinfarfog ac felly'n frawd i'r seintiau Non, Gwen a Banhadlwen.
            Roedd Plas Bodewryd yn adnabyddus fel un o'r tai a noddai beirdd Môn yn yr Oesoedd Canol.
            Brodor o Fodewryd oedd Edward Wyn (m. 1637), gŵr y brydyddes Elen Gwdman.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bodffordd">
            <name>Bodffordd</name>
            <lat>53.265662</lat>
            <lon>-4.359899</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodffordd">Bodffordd is a village and community in central Anglesey, Wales. At the 2011 census, the population of the community was 960.
            Bodffordd is located just under 2 miles (3.2 km) from the county town, Llangefni and is on the south-western edge of the reservoir Llyn Cefni. It is the nearest settlement to RAF Mona and as a community council it includes the village of Trefor. According to the United Kingdom Census 2001, 77.9% of the population in the electoral division can speak the Welsh language. The age group with the highest number is the 15 year olds, where 100% can speak the language.
            The village was originally called Bodffordd Esgob, the Esgob indicating that it belonged to a bishop, the Bishop of Bangor in this case. Village life once revolved around the windmill just north of the village and its related trades. This has now been converted into a private residence. The village was also on a drovers road on the way to Llangefni market and there were two poor houses nearby. Many of these older dwelling have fallen into disrepair but the village church, dedicated to St. Llwydian's, is still in good condition.
            Despite the fact that the village has few facilities (it does have a primary school/village hall, electrical outlet/shop, MOT garage/computer workshop and small shop) it was chosen to host the 2007 Anglesey Eisteddfod, a considerable honour.
            The village is the site of the Mona Industrial Estate, which in 2009 was given planning permission to build a 25,000 tonne animal waste anaerobic digestion plant. Developer Ecoparc Môn, part of Anglesey-based Gray’s Waste Management Systems, has been promised £1.1m in grants from the Welsh Assembly Government through the Waste &amp; Resources Action Programme, towards the developments £3.5m projected cost.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodffordd">Pentref bychan a chymuned yng nghanol Ynys Môn yw Bodffordd (neu Botffordd). Fe'i lleolir ar y lôn gefn B 5109 tua dwy filltir a hanner i'r gorllewin o Langefni, ar ben deheuol Llyn Cefni. Tri chwarter milltir i'r de mae Heneglwys ac mae Bodffordd ei hun yn rhan o'r plwyf honno.
            Fymryn i'r gorllewin o'r pentref ceir Maes Awyr Môn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#braint">
            <name>Braint</name>
            <lat>53.2746792</lat>
            <lon>-4.1955864</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braint">Braint is the name of one of the 40 wards of the Isle of Anglesey County Council, covering part of the area of the community of Llanfairpwllgwyngyll. The ward contained 1,173 electors in 2007, increasing to 1,517 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bryn celyn">
            <name>Bryn Celyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn_Celyn,_Llangoed">Bryn Celyn is an area in the community of Llangoed, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 131.2 miles (211.1 km) from Cardiff and 207.8 miles (334.4 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bryn du">
            <name>Bryn Du</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn Du">Bryn Du is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. Its a cool place, you should go here one day.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn Du">Mae Bryn Du yn gopa mynydd a geir yn Ne-orllewin Cymru; cyfeiriad grid SN845800. Uchder cymharol, neu ”amlygrwydd” y copa, ydy 498 metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
            Dosberthir copaon Cymru, a gweddill gwledydd Prydain, yn rhestri arbennig yn ôl uchder ac yn ôl amlygrwydd y copa; mae'r copa hwn yn cael ei alw'n Dewey. Mae sawl cymdeithas yn mesur, gwiro a chasglu'r rhestri hyn a dônt ynghŷd ar wefan “Database of British and Irish hills”. Uchder y copa o lefel y môr ydy 562 metr (1844 tr). Cafodd yr uchder ei fesur a'i gadarnhau ar 10 Mawrth 2007.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bryngwran">
            <name>Bryngwran</name>
            <lat>53.269233</lat>
            <lon>-4.473994</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryngwran">Bryngwran is a village and community in the Welsh county of Anglesey, located on the A5 London to Holyhead trunk road. It lies 8.1 miles (13.0 km) west of Llangefni, 7.0 miles (11.3 km) south west of Llannerch-y-medd and 7.4 miles (11.9 km) south east of Holyhead, and includes the villages of Bryngwran, Capel Gwyn and Engedi. At the 2001 census the community had a population of 781, increasing to 894 at the 2011 election.
            Saint Peulan's Church stands in an isolated position at Llanbeulan, in the south east of the community. A medieval building, it partly dates from the 12th century, but was extended in the 14th, and restored in the mid-19th century. The gritstone font dates from late 12th century. It is considered an example of a "rural medieval church retaining its simple character" and is Grade II* listed. Pandy Treban, a former fulling mill in the north of the community, and the 18th-century bridge at Pont Factory Cymunod, over the Afon Crigyll on the border with Bodedern, are Grade II listed.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryngwran">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd-orllewin Ynys Môn yw Bryngwran(cyfeiriad grid SH351774). Saif ar y briffordd A5, rhwng Caergeiliog a Gwalchmai. Hyd yn ddiweddar, roedd y drafnidiaeth i Gaergybi yn mynd trwy'r pentref, ond wedi adeiladu'r A55, sy'n mynd ychydig i'r de o'r pentref, mae'n ddistawach. Mae'r rhan fwyaf o'r pentref ym mhlwyf eglwysig Llechylched, gydag ychydig o'r rhan ddwyreiniol ym mhlwyf Llanbeulan.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#brynrefail">
            <name>Brynrefail</name>
            <lat>53.141036</lat>
            <lon>-4.1549319</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynrefail">Brynrefail is a small village in north-east Anglesey, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynrefail,_Ynys_M%C3%B4n">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Brynrefail. Saif ar y briffordd A5025, tua hanner y ffordd rhwng Amlwch a Benllech.
            Saif y pentref yn agos i Draeth Dulas a Thraeth Llugwy, ac mae twristiaeth yn bwysig yn yr ardal, gyda nifer o wersylloedd carafannau. Dyddia'r eglwys i ddiwedd y 19eg ganrif, ac agorwyd neuadd gymumedol yn 1995. Ceir yma hefyd ganolfan arddio a Tyddyn Môn, canolfan ddysgu i rai dan anfantais.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#brynsiencyn">
            <name>Brynsiencyn</name>
            <lat>53.180068</lat>
            <lon>-4.270603</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynsiencyn">Pentref yn ne-orllewin Ynys Môn, ym mhlwyf Llanidan, ar y ffordd A4080 rhwng Llanfairpwllgwyngyll a Niwbwrch, yw Brynsiencyn. O ganol y pentref, mae ffordd arall yn arwain i lawr at Afon Menai, lle mae Sw Môr Môn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#brynteg">
            <name>Brynteg</name>
            <lat>53.065927</lat>
            <lon>-3.039355</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynteg,_Anglesey">Brynteg is a crossroads village and post town on the Isle of Anglesey, North Wales.
            Brynteg is located on the east of the island on the B5108 and B5110 roads due west of the coastal resort of Benllech. It gives its name to an electoral ward of the island's council. The population of this ward taken at the 2011 Census was 1,869.
            During October 2013 the residents of Brynteg were invited to vote for changing the name of the village to Rhosfawr. The results of this vote was 19 for the proposal and 34 against.
            In 2014, Brynteg was rated one of the most attractive postcode areas to live in Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynteg,_Ynys_M%C3%B4n">Pentref bychan yn nwyrain Ynys Môn yw Brynteg (cyfeiriad grid SH496824). Yn gorwedd tua milltir a hanner i'r gorllewin o dref Benllech, ar groesffordd y B5108 a'r B5110. Mae yng nghymuned Llanfair Mathafarn Eithaf.
            Ceir hen felin wynt ar gyrion y pentref a hefyd cwrs golff Brynteg. Mae tafarn y California Arms yng nghanol y pentref.
            Tua chwarter milltir i'r dwyrain o Frynteg ceir hen fryngaer o'r enw Dinas.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#bull bay (porthllechog)">
            <name>Bull Bay (Porthllechog)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#burwen">
            <name>Burwen</name>
            <lat>53.412656</lat>
            <lon>-4.381629</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burwen">Burwen is a village in Anglesey, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burwen">Ardal yng nghymuned Amlwch, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Burwen. Mae 142.7 milltir (229.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 222 milltir (357.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Burwen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#caergeiliog">
            <name>Caergeiliog</name>
            <lat>53.275107</lat>
            <lon>-4.533333</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caergeiliog">Caergeiliog is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caergeiliog">Mae Caergeiliog yn bentref yng ngogledd-orllewin Ynys Môn. Saif ar y briffordd A5, ychydig i'r de-ddwyrain o'r Fali. Mae yng nghymuned Llanfair-yn-Neubwll.
Hyd yn ddiweddar, roedd y drafnidiaeth i Gaergybi yn mynd trwy'r pentref, ond wedi adeiladu'r A55, sy'n mynd ychydig i'r gogledd o'r pentref, mae'n ddistawach. Yn y pentref, gellir gweld un o'r tri tolldy gwreiddiol sydd wedi eu cadw o'r rhai oedd ar yr A5; mae yn awr yn dŷ preifat.
Ychydig i'r de o'r pentref mae Llyn Dinam a gwarchodfa adar RSPB Gwlyptiroedd y Fali.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#caergybi (holyhead)">
            <name>Caergybi (Holyhead)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#caim">
            <name>Caim</name>
            <lat>53.305441</lat>
            <lon>-4.070905</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caim">Caim is a Gaelic rendering of biblical 'Cain', who appears in a variation of the fantastical pedigree of Dardanus of Troy that is spun out in Lebor Bretnach, the Middle Irish language recension of the compilation called Historia Brittonum, known in the 9th century version by Nennius. The Lebor Bretnach, greatly modifies the genealogy given in Nennius, making emendations to earlier sources and tracing the line through Ham rather than Japheth with further spurious names:
Dardain m. Ioib m. Sadoirn m. Peil m. Palloir m. Zorastres m. Mesraim m. Caim.
In the predominantly Welsh-speaking regions of Wales (Gwynedd, Dyfed and Ynys Mon), Cain, Caio, Caim and Cail are commonplace first names for males. These names are derivatives of an ancient Welsh name "Ca" which is recorded in the book of Welsh folklore called the Mabinogion.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#capel coch">
            <name>Capel Coch</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capel Coch">Capel Coch is a small village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. Much of the village over looks Cors Erddreiniog National Nature Reserve.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capel Coch">Pentref bychan yng nghymuned Llanddyfnan yng nghanolbarth Ynys Môn yw Capel Coch. Saif ar ffordd gefn, i'r gogledd o dref Llangefni ac i'r gorllewin o Benllech, ym mhlwyf Llanfihangel Tre'r Beirdd. Mae 135.5 milltir (218.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.1 milltir (347.8 km) o Lundain.
Ceir ysgol gynradd yno, Ysgol Tŷ Mawr, yr ysgol leiaf ym Môn. Fymryn i'r dwyrain o'r pentref mae Cors Erddreiniog, sy'n Warchodfa Natur Genedlaethol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#capel gwyn">
            <name>Capel Gwyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capel Gwyn">Capel Gwyn is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capel Gwyn">Gallai Capel Gwyn gyfeirio at:
Pentrefi
Capel Gwyn, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Capel Gwyn, Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#capel mawr">
            <name>Capel Mawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#capel parc">
            <name>Capel Parc</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#carmel">
            <name>Carmel</name>
            <lat>53.281435</lat>
            <lon>-3.241424</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel">Carmel in the Bible refers to two distinct places:
Mount Carmel, coastal mountain range in Israel overlooking the Mediterranean Sea
Carmel (biblical settlement), an ancient Israelite town in Judea
The word Carmel (Hebrew language: כַּרְמֶל) means "fresh" (planted), or "vineyard" (planted) and Karmiel (Hebrew: כַּרְמִיאֵל) is a portmanteau meaning "God's Vineyard".
In modern times, the name was also given to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel">Gallai Carmel gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#carmel head">
            <name>Carmel Head</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel Head">Carmel Head is a prominent coastal headland on the north-west tip of the island of Anglesey.
It is a designated SSSI because of its geological interest for the Carmel Head Thrust fault where Precambrian rocks have been pushed over younger Ordovician rocks creating the Carmel Head thrust. Rock exposures along the cliffs of Carmel Head include Precambrian gneisses, which are almost certainly the oldest rocks in Wales.
Off-shore from the head lie the islands of the Skerries and to the east of the Skerries three further islands, West Mouse, Middle Mouse and East Mouse. On West Mouse is a large white-painted column which is matched on Carmel Head by two further columns, known locally as the "Three White Ladies". They were constructed in the 1860s as navigation aids: lining up the three columns marks the position of a shallow reef offshore that was a grave danger to shipping.
In the summer months the Anglesey Coastal Path passes over Carmel Head on a permissive path but in winter the path is closed to all for pheasant shooting.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#carreglefn">
            <name>Carreglefn</name>
            <lat>53.37501</lat>
            <lon>-4.430814</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carreglefn">Carreglefn is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carreglefn">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Ynys Môn yw Carreglefn (weithiau Carreg-lefn neu (Y) Garreg(-)lefn). Mae'n bentref anghysbell sy'n gorwedd rhwng Llanfechell i'r gogledd-orllewin a glannau Llyn Alaw i'r de.
Mae'n rhan o blwyf Llanfechell. Milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain ceir cymuned fechan Bodewryd.
Mae llefn yn ffurf fenywaidd ar yr ansoddair llyfn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#cefni">
            <name>Cefni</name>
            <lat>51.662809</lat>
            <lon>-3.9333247</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#cefni reservoir">
            <name>Cefni Reservoir</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#cemaes">
            <name>Cemaes</name>
            <lat>53.412797</lat>
            <lon>-4.451736</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cemaes">Cemaes is a village on the north coast of Anglesey in Wales, sited on Cemaes Bay, an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty which is partly owned by the National Trust. It is the most northerly village in Wales. The name Cemaes was originally spelt Cei Maes meaning Quay Area, but over the years the i has been dropped. In 2011 the population of Cemaes (Llanbadrig ward) was 1,357.
Cemaes is a fishing port and is known for its beach. It has a sheltered natural harbour that looks north to the Irish Sea and is the site of an ancient settlement. Cemaes also has a wind farm and at nearby Wylfa is a nuclear power station. The river in the village is the River Wygyr, which flows from just below Parys Mountain to the sea at Cemaes. It is joined along the way by the Afon Meddanen on Carrog Farm, Carrog. The name Wygyr is Welsh and means 'where two rivers meet'.
Since the Victorian era the picturesque character of Cemaes and the natural beauty of the island have attracted many artists and tourists. Lloyd George used to visit here. Cemaes is located on the Anglesey Coastal Path and is popular with walkers.
The village football team, Cemaes Bay F.C., play in the Welsh Alliance League, but previously have played in the League of Wales, being the first team on Anglesey to do so.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cemaes">Gweler hefyd: Cemmaes (ym Mhowys), Cemais (cantref ym Môn) a Cemais (cantref yn Nyfed).
Mae Cemaes yn bentref gweddol fawr ar arfordir gogleddol Ynys Môn, ger Bae Cemaes lle mae Afon Wygyr yn cyrraedd y môr. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanbadrig. Saif ger y briffordd A5025 rhwng Amlwch a Llanrhuddlad. Mae'n hawlio bod y pentref mwyaf gogleddol yng Nghymru, er y gellid dadlau fod pentref Llanbadrig fwy i'r gogledd.
Pentref gwyliau yw Cemaes yn bennaf erbyn heddiw, er bod pysgota wedi bod yn bwysig yn y gorffennol. Ceir dau draeth, harbwr, amrywiaeth o siopau a nifer o westai. Mae'r ardal o gwmpas y pentref yn Ardal o Harddwch Naturiol Eithriadol ac mae Llwybr Arfordirol Ynys Môn yn mynd heibio'r pentref. Ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r pentref mae gorsaf bŵer niwcliar yr Wylfa.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#cerrig-man">
            <name>Cerrig-man</name>
            <lat>53.3926394</lat>
            <lon>-4.4743512</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#cerrigceinwen">
            <name>Cerrigceinwen</name>
            <lat>53.237108</lat>
            <lon>-4.361644</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerrigceinwen">Cerrigceinwen is a hamlet in the community of Llangristiolus, Ynys Môn, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerrigceinwen">Plwyf a phentref bychan ar wasgar ym Môn yw Cerrigceinwen (neu Cerrig Ceinwen). Fe'i lleolir yn ne-orllewin yr ynys tua 2 filltir a hanner i'r de-orllewin o Langefni.
Enwir Cerrigceinwen ar ôl Ceinwen, santes leol a gysylltir â Llangeinwen ar yr ynys yn ogystal. Mae'n bosibl bod cerrig neu feini goffa yma ar un adeg, ond does dim byd i'w weld erbyn heddiw. Cofnodir ffynnon sanctaidd o'r enw 'Ffynnon Cerrig Ceinwen' yn y plwyf yn 1893.
Rhed Afon Ffraw trwy'r plwyf.
Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd Cerrigceinwen yn rhan o gwmwd Malltraeth, cantref Aberffraw, gyda'i llys yn Bodhenlli.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#city dulas">
            <name>City Dulas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#crigyll">
            <name>Crigyll</name>
            <lat>53.2347534</lat>
            <lon>-4.515959</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crigyll">Traeth yn ymyl Rhosneigr, Ynys Môn yw Crigyll neu Traeth Crigyll. Mae Afon Crigyll yn cyrraedd y môr yno. I'r gogledd ceir maes awyr y Fali.
Byddai lladron Crigyll yn enwog am ysbeilio llongau wrth iddynt daro'r creigiau. Yn 1740 ysbeiliodd nifer o'r trigolion y Loveday &amp; Betty Cawsant eu herlyn yn Llys Biwmaris yn 1741 ond fe'u cafwyd yn ddieuog er eu bod wedi eu dal gyda nwyddau o'r llong. Gweler hefyd hanes trigolion Pen-bre ger Caerfyrddin.
Yn Hydref 1867 cyhoeddwyd erthygl yn The Times, a oedd yn cofnodi llongddrylliad yr Earl of Chester , gan ddweud, “The wreck is now a prey to the notorious wreckers of the coast known to Welsh seafaring men as lladron Crugyll (the Crugyll robbers). Many hundreds of them were there yesterday stealing whatever they could carry away.”
Ysgrifennodd Lewis Morris (1701-1765) gerdd ddychanol adnabyddus yn dymuno gweld crogi "Lladron Crigyll". Dyma'r drydedd bennill:
Os llong a ddaw o draw i drai,
I draethau'r bobl drythyll,
Tosturi'r rhain sydd fel y tân
Neu'r Gwyndraeth a'u gwna'n gandryll;
Gorau gwaith a wnâi wŷr Môn
Oedd grogi lladron Crigyll.
↑ Lewis Morris, 'Lladron Crigyll', yn Blodeugerdd Barddas o Gerddi Rhydd y Ddeunawfed Ganrif, gol. E. G. Millward (Cyhoediadau Barddas, 1991).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#dothan">
            <name>Dothan</name>
            <lat>53.23926</lat>
            <lon>-4.442513</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dothan">Dothan may refer to:
Dothan (ancient city), biblical city
Mevo Dotan, an Israeli settlement on the West Bank near the biblical city
Dothan, Alabama
Dothan (microprocessor), codename for the 2 MB cache 90nm process Pentium M mobile processor
Moshe Dothan (1919–1999), Israeli archaeologist
Trude Dothan (born 1922), Israeli archaeologist
Dani Dothan, Moshe and Trude's son, the lead-singer of HaClique, documentary writer and film-maker</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dothan">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Aberffraw, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Dothan. Mae 132.9 milltir (213.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.8 milltir (350.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Dothan yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#dulas">
            <name>Dulas</name>
            <lat>53.3807504</lat>
            <lon>-4.2911157</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dulas">Dulas may refer to:
Saints in the Eastern Orthodox calendar
Dulas (saint)
Dulas of Cilicia
Places
Dulas, Anglesey, a village in Wales
Dulas Bay, nearby

Dulas, Herefordshire, a civil parish in England</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dulas">Gallai Dulas gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Cymydau canolesol yng nghantref Rhos:
Uwch Dulas
Is Dulas
Afonydd:
Afon Dulas (Rhos), sir Conwy
Afon Dulas (Ceredigion)
Arall:
Traeth Dulas, Môn
Ynys Dulas, oddi ar arfordir Môn
Gweler hefyd:
Llanddulas</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#dwyran">
            <name>Dwyran</name>
            <lat>53.168855</lat>
            <lon>-4.3208529</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwyran">Dwyran is a village on the island of Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwyran">Gall Dwyran gyfeirio at:
Pentref Dwyran yn ne-orllewin Ynys Môn
Castell Dwyran yn Sir Gaerfyrddin.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#dyffryn (valley)">
            <name>Dyffryn (Valley)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#elim">
            <name>Elim</name>
            <lat>53.336697</lat>
            <lon>-4.472152</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elim">Elim may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elim">Pentref yng nghymuned Tref Alaw, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Elim. Mae 139.3 milltir (224.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 222.3 milltir (357.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Elim yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#engedi">
            <name>Engedi</name>
            <lat>53.0773627</lat>
            <lon>-3.0548781</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Engedi">Engedi, Bryngwran is a village 2 miles southeast of Bryngwran, Wales, named after the Biblical place
Engedi and similar can also mean:
Ein Gedi, an oasis in Israel
Ein Gedi (kibbutz), a kibbutz in Israel</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#fedw fawr">
            <name>Fedw Fawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fedw Fawr">Fedw Fawr is an area on the east coast of Anglesey, North Wales, situated just under four miles north of Beaumaris. It is part of the Arfordir Gogleddol Penmon Site of Special Scientific Interest and is managed by the National Trust. The site covers 20 hectares most of which is made up of peaty gley soil.
The cliffs at Fedw Fawr support the only black guillemot colony in Wales.
^ An "Anglesey Nature" site providing information on the flora and fauna of Arfordir Gogleddol Penmon
^ Evans, Lee G. R. (1996). The Ultimate Site Guide to Scarcer British Birds. Little Chalfont: LGRE. ISBN 1-898918-15-5</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#four mile bridge">
            <name>Four Mile Bridge</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four Mile Bridge">Four Mile Bridge (Welsh: Pontrhydybont / Pont-rhydbont / Pontrhypont) is the name given to a bridge and the village surrounding it in Anglesey, Wales. They are so named because the bridge is around four miles by the old road (3 miles "as the crow flies") from Holyhead, the largest town in Anglesey and its surrounding islands. The bridge is one of three connecting the Anglesey mainland to the smaller Holy Island, where Holyhead is located. A bridge at this location was in existence by 1530, and was the only land route to Holyhead until the construction of the Stanley Embankment in 1823. It is 120 metres long and carries the B4545 road over the Cymyran strait.
The village itself is quite small and is split between the two islands, the larger portion being on Holy Island. It is hard to get information on the population of the village as it is split between two communities. It is safe to say, however, that it must be around 500 as the largest part of the village is in the community of Rhoscolyn which has a population of 484, and there is no other settlement of any real size.
The village is about one mile from Valley railway station, and is on the Isle of Anglesey Coastal Path. The village has one cafe, Y Gegin Fach, meaning 'the little kitchen', a hairdressers and a pub, The Anchorage.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#gadfa">
            <name>Gadfa</name>
            <lat>53.382279</lat>
            <lon>-4.319193</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gadfa">Gadfa is a hamlet in the community of Llaneilian, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 140 miles (225.3 km) from Cardiff and 218.8 miles (352.1 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gadfa">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llaneilian, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Gadfa. Mae 140 milltir (225.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.8 milltir (352.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Gadfa yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#gaerwen">
            <name>Gaerwen</name>
            <lat>53.22199</lat>
            <lon>-4.281381</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaerwen">Gaerwen is a village on the island of Anglesey, Wales. It is located in the south of the island 4 miles (6.4 km) west of Llanfairpwllgwyngyll and 4 miles (6.4 km) southeast of Llangefni . The A5 runs through the village, and the A55 runs just a few hundred metres north. According to the 2011 Census Gaerwen is now listed by the Office for National Statistics as Llanfihangel Ysgeifiog. The population of this community was 1,551.
^ "Community Population 2011". Retrieved 19 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaerwen">Pentref gweddol fawr yn ne-orllewin Ynys Môn yw'r Gaerwen. Saif ar ffordd yr A5 rhyw bedair milltir i'r gorllewin o bentref Llanfairpwllgwyngyll ac i'r dwyrain o Bentre Berw. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanfihangel Ysgeifiog.
Hyd yn ddiweddar roedd yr holl drafnidiaeth i Gaergybi yn mynd trwy'r pentref, ond ar ôl i ffordd newydd yr A55, sy'n osgoi'r p[entref, gael ei hagor mae pethau'n ddistawach.
Mae Stâd Ddiwydiannol y Gaerwen ar ochr orllewinol y pentref, ac mae dwy hen felin wynt i'r gogledd. Ar un adeg roedd Rheilffordd Canol Môn yn gadael y prif reilffordd i Gaergybi yng ngorsaf Gaerwen ac yn arwain tua'r gogledd-ddwyrain i Amlwch.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#glan-yr-afon">
            <name>Glan-yr-afon</name>
            <lat>52.971617</lat>
            <lon>-3.4577463</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glan-yr-afon">Gallai Glan-yr-afon neu Glanrafon gyfeirio at:
Glan-yr-afon, Bodffordd, Ynys Môn
Glan-yr-afon, Mariandyrys, Ynys Môn
Glan'rafon, Caerdydd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#goferydd">
            <name>Goferydd</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goferydd">Goferydd is an area in the community of Trearddur, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 141.4 miles (227.5 km) from Cardiff and 228.9 miles (368.4 km) from London.
"Goferydd" is a Welsh word meaning "overflowing."</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#gwalchmai">
            <name>Gwalchmai</name>
            <lat>53.259346</lat>
            <lon>-4.417015</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwalchmai">Am enghreifftiau eraill o'r enw gweler Gwalchmai (gwahaniaethu).
Pentref yng nghanol Ynys Môn yw Gwalchmai, a leolir ar hyd yr A5, tua 5 milltir i'r gorllewin o dref Llangefni (cyfeiriad grid SH399761).
Yn agos iddo mae Llyn Hendref a Chors Bodwrog. Gwalchmai yw'r pentref sydd agosaf i 'gae Primin' (Sioe Amaethyddol Môn). I'r dwyrain o'r pentref i gyfeiriad Bodffordd ceir llain lanio sy'n perthyn i RAF Valley.
C.P.D Gwalchmai yw'r tîm pêl-droed lleol, ac maent yn chwarae eu gemau cartref yn y stadiwm 'Burn-a-Ball' ym Maes Meurig.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#gwalchmai uchaf">
            <name>Gwalchmai Uchaf</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#gwredog">
            <name>Gwredog</name>
            <lat>53.3483572</lat>
            <lon>-4.3986508</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwredog">Gwredog is a village in the community of Llannerch-y-medd, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 138.9 miles (223.6 km) from Cardiff and 220.2 miles (354.4 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#hebron">
            <name>Hebron</name>
            <lat>51.917985</lat>
            <lon>-4.646032</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebron">Hebron (Arabic:  الخليل  al-Khalīl; Hebrew:  חֶבְרוֹן , Standard Hebrew: Ḥevron; ISO 259-3: Ḥebron) is a Palestinian city located in the southern West Bank, 30 km (19 mi) south of Jerusalem. Nestled in the Judaean Mountains, it lies 930 meters (3,050 ft) above sea level. It is the largest city in the West Bank, and the second largest in the Palestinian territories after Gaza, and home to around 175,000 to 250,000 Palestinians, and between 500 and 850 Jewish settlers concentrated in Otniel settlement and around the old quarter. The city is divided into two sectors: H1, controlled by the Palestinian Authority and H2, roughly 20% of the city, administered by Israel. The settlers are governed by their own municipal body, the Committee of the Jewish Community of Hebron. The city is most notable for containing the traditional burial site of the biblical Patriarchs and Matriarchs, within the Cave of the Patriarchs. It is therefore considered the second-holiest city in Judaism after Jerusalem. The city is venerated by Jews, Christians, and Muslims for its association with Abraham. It is viewed as a holy city in Islam and Judaism.
Hebron is a busy hub of West Bank trade, responsible for roughly a third of the area's gross domestic product, largely due to the sale of marble from quarries. It is locally well known for its grapes, figs, limestone, pottery workshops and glassblowing factories, and is the location of the major dairy product manufacturer, al-Junaidi. The old city of Hebron is characterized by narrow, winding streets, flat-roofed stone houses, and old bazaars. The city is home to Hebron University and the Palestine Polytechnic University.
Hebron is detached to cities of ad-Dhahiriya, Dura, Yatta, the surrounding villages with no borders. Hebron Governorate is the largest Palestinian governorate with its population of 600,364 (2010).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebron">Gweler hefyd Hebron (gwahaniaethu).
Dinas ar y Lan Orllewinol yw Hebron (Hebraeg: חברון Chevron; Arabeg: الخليل Al Khalil). Ers dechrau 1997, mae 80% o'r ddinas dan reolaeth Awdurdod Cenedlaethol Palesteina a'r gweddill yn cael ei rheoli gan Israel. Roedd y boblogaeth yn 2006 tua 167,000, bron i gyd yn Balestiniaid, ac eithio tua 600 o Iddewon.
Mae Hebron yn un o ddinasoedd hynaf y Dwyrain Canol. Gerllaw Hebron mae Ogof y Patriarchiaid, lle dywedir bod Abraham, Sara, Isaac a Rebecca wedi eu claddu. Mae'n fangre sanctaidd mewn Iddewiaeth, Cristnogaeth ac Islam. Yn Hebron y cyhoeddwyd Dafydd yn frenin teyrnas Israel ac oddi yno y bu'n teyrnasu hed nes iddo goncro Jeriwsalem.
Yn 1929, lladdwyd 69 o Iddewon gan y Palestiniaid, a gorfodwyd y gweddill o'r boblogaeth Iddewig i ffoi. Yn 1994 lladdwyd 29 o bobl oedd yn gweddio ym Mosg Ibrahimi gan Baruch Goldstein, meddyg Americanaidd-Israelaidd, ac anafwyd 125 arall.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#hen bentref llandegfan">
            <name>Hen Bentref Llandegfan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hen Bentref Llandegfan">Hen Bentref Llandegfan is a village in the community of Cwm Cadnant, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 128.9 miles (207.5km) from Cardiff and 207.8 miles (334.3km) from London.
"Hen Bentref" in Welsh means "the old village".

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hen Bentref Llandegfan">Pentref yng nghymuned Cwm Cadnant, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Hen Bentref Llandegfan. Mae 128.9 milltir (207.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.8 milltir (334.3 km) o Lundain. Saif ychydig i'r gogledd o Landegfan.
Cynrychiolir Hen Bentref Llandegfan yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#heneglwys">
            <name>Heneglwys</name>
            <lat>53.0922252</lat>
            <lon>-3.7996326</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heneglwys">Heneglwys is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heneglwys">Pentrefan a phlwyf eglwysig ar Ynys Môn yw Heneglwys (cyfeiriad grid SH424762). Fe'i lleolir milltir i'r de o bentref Bodffordd yn y gymuned o'r un enw, tua hanner ffordd rhwng Gwalchmai i'r gorllewin a Llangefni i'r dwyrain. Mae 132.7 milltir (213.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 215.8 milltir (347.2 km) o Lundain.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#hermon">
            <name>Hermon</name>
            <lat>51.956106</lat>
            <lon>-4.612589</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermon">Ceir sawl lle o'r enw Hermon, a enwir ar ôl mynydd sanctaidd yn y Beibl, Mynydd Hermon, gan gynnwys:
Hermon (Sir Gaerfyrddin)
Hermon (Sir Benfro)
Hermon (Ynys Môn)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#holy island">
            <name>Holy Island</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy Island">Holy Island or Holy Isle may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy Island">Gallai Holy Island gyfeirio at un o nifer o ynysoedd:
Enw Saesneg ar Ynys Gybi, ger Ynys Môn
Enw arall ar Lindisfarne
Enw Saesneg ar Eilean MoLaise, ger ynys Arran ar arfordir gorllewinol yr Alban</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#holyhead (caergybi)">
            <name>Holyhead (Caergybi)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#isallt bach">
            <name>Isallt Bach</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isallt Bach">Isallt Bach is a hamlet in the community of Trearddur, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 138.7 miles (223.3km) from Cardiff and 225.8 miles (363.4km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isallt Bach">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Trearddur, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Isallt Bach. Mae 138.7 milltir (223.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 225.8 milltir (363.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Isallt Bach yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#kingsland">
            <name>Kingsland</name>
            <lat>53.3028989</lat>
            <lon>-4.633721</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingsland">Kingsland may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingsland">Ardal yn nhref Caergybi, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw '. Mae 140 milltir (225.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 226.6 milltir (364.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llaingoch">
            <name>Llaingoch</name>
            <lat>53.310911</lat>
            <lon>-4.657376</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaingoch">Llaingoch is an area of Holyhead in North Wales that lies between the town centre and Holyhead Mountain. The name comes from the Welsh llain, plot or patch of land, and goch, red.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaingoch">Ardal yn nhref Caergybi, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Llaingoch. Mae 141 milltir (226.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 227.8 milltir (366.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llaingoch yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanallgo">
            <name>Llanallgo</name>
            <lat>53.341036</lat>
            <lon>-4.255672</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanallgo">Llanallgo is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanallgo">Mae Llanallgo yn bentref bychan yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn gerllaw Moelfre, ar lôn yr A5025.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanbabo">
            <name>Llanbabo</name>
            <lat>53.352329</lat>
            <lon>-4.4394</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbabo">Llanbabo (Welsh: Church of Pabo) is a small village two miles north west of Llannerch-y-medd in Anglesey, Wales. It lies within the community of Tref Alaw.
The ancient church of St Pabo, Llanbabo is dedicated to Saint Pabo: possibly Pabo Post Prydain, one of the leaders among the Britons of the Hen Ogledd following the withdrawal of the Roman legions. He is said to have founded a church here in 460, upon the site of which the present one is built, and to have been buried here along with his daughters. A 14th-century effigy of Pabo, along with the words HIC JACET PABO POST PRUD CORPORS ... TE ... PRIMA, is found on a stone in the church.
Llyn Alaw lies nearby.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbabo">Mae Llanbabo yn bentref bychan 4 milltir i'r de o Fae Cemaes ar ymyl Cors y Bol ger Llyn Alaw, yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd yn rhan o gwmwd Talybolion. Ceir tystiolaeth sy'n awgrymu'n gryf fod Sefnyn, un o Feirdd yr Uchelwyr a ganai yn ail hanner y 14eg ganrif, yn frodor o blwyf Llanbabo.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanbadrig">
            <name>Llanbadrig</name>
            <lat>53.4247768</lat>
            <lon>-4.4298199</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbadrig">Llanbadrig is a village community and electoral ward in the Welsh county of Anglesey. The parish includes the township of Clygyrog, Tregynrig and the port of Cemaes (pronounced "Kem-ice"), and was formerly in the cwmwd of Talybolion. The area has extensive quarries of limestone and marble. At the 2001 census it had a population of 1,392, reducing slightly to 1,357 at the 2011 census.
The Welsh name Llanbadrig means "Church of Saint Patrick" and there is indeed a Church of St. Patrick on the coast near Cemaes. It is said to have been founded in 440CE by St Patrick himself. Local legend states that Patrick was shipwrecked on the small nearby island of Ynys Badrig (Patrick's Isle, also known as Middle Mouse), which can be seen from the stile in the churchyard wall. The nearby cove is known as Porth Padrig.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbadrig">Plwyf eglwysig a chymuned ar arfordir gogledd Môn yw Llanbadrig. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd yn rhan o gwmwd Talybolion, cantref Cemais.
Mae'r gymuned hon yn cynnwys treflan Clygyrog a phorthladd bychan Cemaes (Porth Wygyr), lleoliad tybiedig maenor cantref Cemais yn yr Oesoedd Canol. Ceir nifer o hen chwareli calchfaen yn yr ardal. Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2011, roedd 1,316 o bobl yn byw yn y gymuned hon a 690 (sef 52.4%) o'r boblogaeth dros dair oed a hŷn Cymuned Llanbadrig yn gallu siarad Cymraeg. Roedd 302 yn ddi-waith, sef 46.7% o'r rhai o fewn yr oedran priodol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanbedrgoch">
            <name>Llanbedrgoch</name>
            <lat>53.300353</lat>
            <lon>-4.236241</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedrgoch">Llanbedrgoch is a hamlet and post town, a mile south of the town of Benllech and west of Red Wharf Bay, on the island of Anglesey (Welsh: Ynys Môn), north Wales. The parish church is St Peter's Church, Llanbedrgoch, a Grade II* listed building that dates back to the 15th century.
The historical settlements in the area have been subject of archaeological exploration.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedrgoch">Mae Llanbedrgoch (hefyd Llanbedr-goch) yn bentref a phlwyf eglwysig yn ne-ddwyrain Ynys Môn. Saif ar ffordd gefn ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r briffordd A5025 rhwng Pentraeth a Benllech.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanddaniel fab">
            <name>Llanddaniel Fab</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddaniel Fab">Llanddaniel Fab is a village and community in the Welsh county of Isle of Anglesey. At the 2001 census it had a population of 699, increasing to 776 at the 2011 census.
It is near the prehistoric monument of Bryn Celli Ddu which was constructed in the late neolithic period. In the east of the community, by the Menai Strait, stands the country seat of the Marquess of Anglesey, Plas Newydd, parts of which date from the 14th century. The house has been owned by the National Trust since 1976.
During the 2001 United Kingdom foot-and-mouth crisis, many sheep and cattle were slaughtered in the area.
The village has its own community council and its county council representative is Hywel Eifion Jones, who has held the post since May 1999. Amenities include a post office, primary school (Ysgol Parc y Bont), and a 12-hole golf course.
Probably the village's most famous son is Tecwyn Roberts (1925-1988), who became NASA’s first Flight Dynamics Officer with Project Mercury that put the first American into space. Roberts was born at Trefnant Bach cottage in Llanddaniel Fab and was a former pupil of Ysgol Parc y Bont. After serving as a member of the Avro Arrow project team and the Space Task Group, Roberts transferred to NASA where he eventually became chief of the Manned Flight Support Division, chief of the Network Engineering Division during the Apollo Program and later Director of Networks at Goddard Space Flight Center.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddaniel Fab">Pentref bychan, cymuned a phlwyf eglwsyig yw Llanddaniel Fab (gynt Llanddeiniol Fab), sy'n gorwedd yn ne-orllewin Ynys Môn, ar ffordd gefn rhwng Y Gaerwen ar ffordd yr A5 a Llanedwen ar yr A4080. Mae'n rhan o ward Llanidan.
Yn yr Oesoedd Canol bu'n rhan o gwmwd Menai, cantref Aberffraw. Mae'r eglwys wedi ei chysegru i Ddaniel Fab (Deiniol Fab; hefyd Deiniolen).
Mae claddfa gynhanesyddol enwog Bryn Celli Ddu ychydig i'r de o'r pentref. Yma hefyd y saif Plas Llwyn-onn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanddeusant">
            <name>Llanddeusant</name>
            <lat>51.905686</lat>
            <lon>-3.779008</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddeusant">Llanddeusant may refer to:
Llanddeusant, Anglesey, North Wales
Llanddeusant, Carmarthenshire, West Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddeusant">Ceir dau bentref o'r enw Llanddeusant yng Nghymru:
Llanddeusant, Ynys Môn
Llanddeusant, Sir Gaerfyrddin</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanddona">
            <name>Llanddona</name>
            <lat>53.292295</lat>
            <lon>-4.139824</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddona">Llanddona is a village and community noted for its beach in the Welsh county of Anglesey. Located between Benllech and Beaumaris, it is popular as a holiday destination, particularly for families. The beach is a good size without being bleakly huge, shelves at a decent but not alarming rate and has an abundance of clean yellow sand. Llanddona has no shops, however it has a riding school and a public house. At the 2001 census it had a population of 639, increasing to 691 at the 2011 census.
Llanddona transmitting station is located approximately one mile to the north east of the village. The station is the main broadcasting site for television and radio in north Wales.
St Dona's Church, Llanddona, dates from 610, although the present building was erected in 1873.
Llanddona is said to have once been home to a family of witches, whose powers descended from mother to daughter.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddona">Mae Llanddona yn bentref a chymuned yn ne-ddwyrain Ynys Môn, rhyw dair milltir i’r gogledd o dref Biwmares ar ffordd fechan sy’n troi tua’r gogledd o’r B5109 rhwng Biwmares a Llansadwrn (cyfeiriad grid SH575796). Mae ar ochr ddwyreiniol Traeth Coch. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd yn rhan o gwmwd Dindaethwy, cantref Menai.

Mae’r eglwys wedi ei chysegru i Sant Dona, mab Selyf ap Cynan o deulu brenhinol Teyrnas Powys. Dywedir fod yr eglwys wreiddiol yma yn dyddio o tua 610. Ail-adeiladwyd yr eglwys bresennol yn 1873. Yn yr eglwys mae cloch yn dyddio o 1647 a chwpan cymun arian yn dyddio o 1769, ond gyda chaead o 1574.
Nodwedd amlycaf yr ardal yw’r mast radio ar fryn uwchben y pentref, sydd i’w weld am filltiroedd. Ychydig i’r gogledd o’r pentref mae bryngaer o’r enw Bwrdd Arthur, neu "Din Sylwy". Mae maen hir cynhanesyddol i’r gorllewin o’r pentref.
Ceir stori adnabyddus am Wrachod Llanddona. Yn ôl y chwedl daeth cwch heb hwyl na rhwyfau i’r lan yn Nhraeth Coch yn llawn o ddynion a merched. Daethant yn enwog am eu gallu i reibio, yn enwedig gwraig o’r enw Bella Fawr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llandegfan">
            <name>Llandegfan</name>
            <lat>53.244101</lat>
            <lon>-4.15277</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandegfan">Llandegfan (The Church of St. Tegfan) is a village on the south of Anglesey, North Wales. It is part of the community of Cwm Cadnant.
The original village Hen Llandegfan was on the ancient way from the crossing of the Menai Strait at Porthaethwy via Pentraeth to Beaumaris. St Tegfan's Church, the mother church of Beaumaris, has been highly restored.
Llandegfan has expanded greatly in recent decades and is continuing to expand in the 21st century notably in the extension to the Mill Lodge estate and along Lon Ganol. Almost all of this expansion is centred on the modern village centre to the south and east of the old windmill. The expansion of the village is due to a number of factors including the proximity to Bangor where many of the residents of Llandegfan work, its proximity to the A55 and the views from the village over to the mountains of Snowdonia.
To the outskirts of the village is Bryn Mel Manor, built in 1899 and standing in approx 10 acres (40,000 m2) of wood and parkland as a summer house for the owners of the White Star Line. Since the death of the last family owner, the building was derelict for many years, before being converted into a nursing home. Financial constraints meant much of the original land was sold, and in the latter years the home struggled to stay open. In July 2011 it was announced that the home was to close and the building redeveloped into luxury flats and apartments. Despite its modern history, the external features of the building have changed little but many of the internal features have been lost.
Notable past residents include singer and television presenter Aled Jones and harpist Robert ap Huw.
Llandegfan has a senior football team playing in the Anglesey League called Llandegfan Antelope FC, who play their home matches at Cae Llandegfan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandegfan">Pentref yn ne-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Llandegfan. Saif ar ffordd gefn ychydig i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o dref Porthaethwy ac i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A545 rhwng Porthaethwy a Biwmares. Mae yng nghymuned Cwm Cadnant.
Mae'r pentref mewn dwy ran; y pentref gwreiddiol yw'r hyn a elwir yn awr yn Hen Landegfan, o gwmpas yr eglwys, sydd wedi ei chysegru i Sant Tegfan. Tyfodd y rhan arall, sydd gryn dipyn yn fwy, i'r de o'r hen bentref ac yn nes at yr A545.
Gweithio yn ninas Bangor y mae'r mwyafrif o'r trigolion.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llandyfrydog">
            <name>Llandyfrydog</name>
            <lat>53.339128</lat>
            <lon>-4.339601</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandyfrydog">Llandyfrydog is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandyfrydog">Plwyf a phentre bychan yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Llandyfrydog. Gorwedd tua 5 milltir i'r gorllewin o Foelfre a thua 2 filltir i'r dwyrain o Lannerch-y-medd. Mae'r pentref yn rhan o gymuned Rhosybol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llaneilian">
            <name>Llaneilian</name>
            <lat>53.4090739</lat>
            <lon>-4.3018029</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaneilian">Llaneilian is a village and community in the Welsh county of Anglesey. It is located in the north east of the island, 2.2 miles (3.5 km) east of Amlwch, 16.5 miles (26.6 km) north west of Menai Bridge and 12.5 miles (20.1 km) north of Llangefni. The community includes the villages of Dulas, Llaneilian, Pengorffwysfa and Penysarn, and at the 2001 census had a population of 1,192, decreasing slightly to 1,186 at the 2011 Census. The parish is crowned by its hill, Mynydd Eilian (177 metres), a HuMP, popular with walkers and ramblers (the Anglesey Coastal Path navigates most of the parish's coastline - all of which is classed as an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty), and its beach, Traeth Eilian, which is popular with holidaymakers and for watersport activities. At the north easternmost point is Point Lynas,(on a clear day from the north coast of Anglesey the Isle of Man is visible with the streetlights of Douglas, Isle of Man visible on the Horizon), while Ynys Dulas lies off the North East coast of the island, east of Dulas Bay.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaneilian">Am y pentref yn sir Conwy, gweler Llaneilian-yn-Rhos.

Pentref, plwyf a chymuned ar yr arfordir yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Llaneilian. Cysegrwyd Eglwys Llaneilian i Sant Eilian; mae'n un o'r eglwysi hynaf ar yr ynys. Gerllaw mae Trwyn Eilian (Saesneg: Point Lynas) gyda'i oleudy a bae Porth Eilian. Arferai fod melin wynt gerllaw a elwid yn Felin Eilian.
Mae cymuned Llaneilian yn cynnwys pentref Penysarn yn ogystal a Llaneilian ei hun, ac Ynys Dulas. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 1,192.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanerchymedd">
            <name>Llanerchymedd</name>
            <lat>53.33105</lat>
            <lon>-4.376968</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llaneuddog">
            <name>Llaneuddog</name>
            <lat>53.367814</lat>
            <lon>-4.3062037</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaneuddog">Llaneuddog is a village in the community of Llaneilian, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 138.8 miles (223.4km) from Cardiff and 217.8 miles (350.6km) from London.
^ Google Maps (Map). Google.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaneuddog">Pentref yng nghymuned Llaneilian, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Llaneuddog. Mae 138.8 milltir (223.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.8 milltir (350.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llaneuddog yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfachraeth">
            <name>Llanfachraeth</name>
            <lat>53.312401</lat>
            <lon>-4.531226</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfachraeth">Llanfachraeth is a village and community in the Welsh county of Anglesey. It is located on the west coast of the island, at the head of the Alaw estuary, 6.2 miles (10.0 km) east of Holyhead, 11.7 miles (18.8 km) south west of Amlwch and 11.3 miles (18.2 km) north west of Llangefni. At the 2001 census the community had a population of 566, increasing slightly at the 2011 census to 589.
In the extreme north of the community, on the border with Llanfaethlu, stands Gronant, a Grade II* listed sub-medieval house dating from around 1540. A second house was built around 1618. In the 19th century the two houses were joined and a bell turret, used to call servants for meals, was added. The former servants' loft contains fragments of an original wallpainting.
The Alaw estuary forms part of the Beddmanarch–Cymyran site of special scientific interest, which also extends across the mudflats between Holy Island and mainland Anglesey. The area contains large areas of seagrass and salt marsh, and is an important wintering area for ringed plovers, greenshanks, red-breasted mergansers and goldeneyes.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfaelog">
            <name>Llanfaelog</name>
            <lat>53.228442</lat>
            <lon>-4.492722</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaelog">Llanfaelog is a village in western Anglesey, Wales. It is situated some 13 kilometres south-east of Holyhead and 22 kilometres west of the city of Bangor. At the 2001 census, it had a population of 1,679, increasing to 1,758 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaelog">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd-orllewin Ynys Môn yw Llanfaelog. Saif ar y briffordd A4080, ychydig i'r dwyrain o bentref Rhosneigr a gerllaw Llyn Maelog. Mae gorsaf rheilffordd Tŷ Croes gerllaw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfaes">
            <name>Llanfaes</name>
            <lat>53.279625</lat>
            <lon>-4.096544</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaes">Llanfaes (formerly also known as Llanmaes) is a small village on the island of Anglesey, Wales, located on the shore of the eastern entrance to the Menai Strait, the tidal waterway separating Anglesey from the north Wales coast. Its natural harbour made it an important medieval port and it was briefly the capital of the kingdom of Gwynedd. Following Prince Madoc's Rebellion, Edward I removed the Welsh population from the town and rebuilt the port a mile to the south at Beaumaris.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfaethlu">
            <name>Llanfaethlu</name>
            <lat>53.352632</lat>
            <lon>-4.536465</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaethlu">Llanfaethlu is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. The community population taken at the 2011 Census was 553.
It is home to Condessa, a small liquor company.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaethlu">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd-orllewin Ynys Môn yw Llanfaethlu. Saif ar y briffordd A5025 rhwng Y Fali a Chemaes. Daw enw'r pentref o enw sant Maethlu, a elwir hefyd yn "Maethlu Gyffeswr".
Nid yw'r pentref ei hun ar lan y môr, ond mae traeth Porth Swtan gerllaw, tua milltir a hanner i'r gogledd-orllewin. Mae bwthyn yma o'r enw Swtan sy'n awr yn amgueddfa werin; dywedir mai hwn yw'r bwthyn to gwellt olaf ar yr ynys. Mae plasty Garreglwyd gerllaw yn dyddio o'r 17eg ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfair pwllgwyngyll">
            <name>Llanfair Pwllgwyngyll</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfair Pwllgwyngyll">Pentref a chymuned ar Ynys Môn yw Llanfair Pwllgwyngyll (neu Llanfairpwllgwyngyll; Llanfairpwll ar lafar yn lleol). Fe'i lleolir ar ffordd yr A5 tua 3 milltir i'r gorllewin o Borthaethwy.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfairyneubwll">
            <name>Llanfairyneubwll</name>
            <lat>53.258867</lat>
            <lon>-4.548478</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfairynghornwy">
            <name>Llanfairynghornwy</name>
            <lat>53.388619</lat>
            <lon>-4.523669</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfairynghornwy">This is a redirect from a title with a different spelling. Pages that link to this redirect may be updated to link directly to the target page if that results in an improvement of the text. Do not "fix" such links if they are not broken. Also, these links should not be replaced with piped links. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfechell">
            <name>Llanfechell</name>
            <lat>53.392837</lat>
            <lon>-4.453698</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfechell">Llanfechell (Welsh: Llanfechell llan church + Saint Mechell) is a village in Anglesey, North Wales, UK. It is the largest of several small villages and dispersed settlements that make up Mechell Community Council area. It is 11 miles (18 km) east of Holyhead, and 5.6 miles (9.0 km) west of Amlwch, on the north of the island.
The Community (which also includes Mynydd Mechell and Carreglefn) has a 2001 population of 1,532. Village services include a church, a primary school, a pub and two chapels. It is an agricultural area, and has been a local centre for markets, livestock fairs, and had both a watermill and windmill. The area round about has many prehistoric monuments.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfechell">Pentref ar Ynys Môn yw Llanfechell (cyfeiriad grid SH369912). Saif yng ngogledd yr ynys tua 2 filltir i'r de o bentref Cemaes, ar yr arfordir i'r gogledd, a milltir i'r de o bentref Tregele, lle mae lôn yn rhedeg o'r pentref hwnnw i Llanfechell. Mae'r pentref yn perthyn i gymuned Mechell.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfflewyn">
            <name>Llanfflewyn</name>
            <lat>53.3727003</lat>
            <lon>-4.4820668</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfflewyn">Llanfflewyn is a village in the community of Mechell, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 141.9 miles (228.3 km) from Cardiff and 224.1 miles (360.6 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfflewyn">Pentref yng nghymuned Mechell, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Llanfflewyn. Mae 141.9 milltir (228.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 224.1 milltir (360.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanfflewyn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfigael">
            <name>Llanfigael</name>
            <lat>53.3179329</lat>
            <lon>-4.511548</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfihangel yn nhowyn">
            <name>Llanfihangel yn Nhowyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfihangel yn Nhowyn">Llanfihangel yn Nhowyn is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. The church in the village, St Mihangel's, is a Grade II listed building and is the chapel for the nearby airbase, RAF Valley.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanfwrog">
            <name>Llanfwrog</name>
            <lat>53.111044</lat>
            <lon>-3.329039</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfwrog">Llanfwrog may refer to:
Llanfwrog, Anglesey
Llanfwrog, Denbighshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfwrog">Gallai Llanfwrog gyfeirio at un o ddau bentref yng Nghymru:
Llanfwrog, pentref ger Rhuthun yn Sir Ddinbych
Llanfwrog, pentref ar Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangadwaladr">
            <name>Llangadwaladr</name>
            <lat>53.196286</lat>
            <lon>-4.422357</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangadwaladr">Llangadwaladr is a small village in south-west Anglesey, Wales, located around 2 miles east of Aberffraw and 3 miles south of Gwalchmai. It is part of the community of Bodorgan.
The village's church (St Cadwaladr) is believed to have been a royal burial ground, and one of its windows dates from the 12th Century.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangadwaladr">Gall Llangadwaladr gyfeirio at un o ddau le yng Nghymru:
Llangadwaladr, pentref ar Ynys Môn.
Llangadwaladr, pentref ym Mhowys.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangaffo">
            <name>Llangaffo</name>
            <lat>53.188918</lat>
            <lon>-4.3301</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangaffo">Llangaffo is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. It lies along the B4419 and B4421 roads, north of Dwyran, south of Gaerwen and northwest of Llanidan. It is named after Caffo, a 6th-century saint. A church, St Caffo's Church, is named after him. A war memorial, a village hall and a primary school are also located in the village. The 1851 census recorded 138 people in the village, 75 males, 63 females and a parish area of 1,590 acres (640 ha).

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangaffo">Pentref yn ne-orllewin Ynys Môn yw Llangaffo, ar y ffordd rhwng Pentre Berw a Niwbwrch, lle mae'r ffyrdd B4419 a B4421 yn cyfarfod. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol bu'n rhan o gwmwd Menai, cantref Aberffraw. Mae yng nghymuned Rhosyr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangefni">
            <name>Llangefni</name>
            <lat>53.255785</lat>
            <lon>-4.311402</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangefni">Llangefni (Welsh pronunciation: [ɬanˈɡɛvni]) is the county town of Anglesey in Wales and contains the principal offices of the Isle of Anglesey County Council. The United Kingdom Census 2011 recorded Llangefni's population as 5,116 people, making it the second largest settlement on the island. The Census also recorded that 83.8% of the population state that they can speak Welsh, with the highest percentage of speakers being in the 10-14 age group where 95.2% are able to speak Welsh.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangefni">Tref yng nghanol Ynys Môn yw Llangefni, sydd wedi bod yn dref farchnad bwysig i'r ynys. Llangefni yw tref sirol Môn a lleolir pencadlys Cyngor Sir Ynys Môn yma. Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2001, mae gan Llangefni boblogaeth o 4,499 o bobl. Mae 83.8% o'r boblogaeth honno'n rhugl yn y Gymraeg gyda'r canran uchaf yn yr oedran 10-14 mlwydd gyda 95.2% yn medru'r Gymraeg. O'i tharddle ger Llyn Cefni rhed Afon Cefni trwy'r dref, sy'n cymryd ei enw o'r afon. Mae Caerdydd 211.6 km i ffwrdd o Llangefni ac mae Llundain yn 344.7 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 11.7 km i ffwrdd.
Yn y dref ceir Oriel Ynys Môn, gydag amgueddfa sy'n olrhain hanes yr ynys ac oriel i ddangos gwaith yr arlunydd bywyd gwyllt Charles Tunnicliffe.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangoed">
            <name>Llangoed</name>
            <lat>53.295301</lat>
            <lon>-4.087893</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangoed">Llangoed is a small village, community and electoral ward just north of Beaumaris, on the Isle of Anglesey or Ynys Môn, at grid reference SH609793. The Royal Mail postcode begins LL58. Llangoed ward has a population of 1,275 (2001), falling at the 2011 census to 1,229.
The village's placename means the 'religious enclosure in the wood' in the Welsh language.
Llangoed is on the banks of a brook called the Afon Lleiniog, which flows from the hamlet of Glanrafon to the sea, beneath the ruins of an 11th-century motte-and-bailey castle, Castell Aberlleiniog.
The 17th-century parish church of St Cawrdaf, restored in the 19th century, is in the north of the village, near a Victorian school and chapel.
The modern centre of the village is a steep hill lined by cottages, a Post Office, grocery store and chapel. To the south of the village is a primary school, Ysgol Gynradd Llangoed, and small housing estates. Sports fields are the location of an annual Rugby sevens competition. Undulating green farmland surrounds the village, with fine views to the Menai Strait, the Irish Sea and the mountains of Snowdonia (in Welsh, Eryri).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangoed">Am y pentrefan ym Mhowys gweler Llangoed, Powys.
Pentref ger Biwmares yn ne-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Llangoed. Y mae ganddi ysgol, neuadd bentref, tŷ tafarn a siop. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd yn rhan o gwmwd Dindaethwy, cantref Menai. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llangoed a Phenmon.
Mae Afon Lleiniog, sy'n llifo trwy'r pentref o dreflan Glanrafon i'r môr, yn llifo heibio i adfeilion Castell Aberlleiniog, castell mwnt a beili sy'n dyddio o'r 11eg ganrif.
Mae'r pentref yn cynnal twrnament Rygbi 7 bob ochr bob blwyddyn. Dechreuir ei gôd post gyda LL58 8.
Ceir clystyrau cytiau hynafol gerllaw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangristiolus">
            <name>Llangristiolus</name>
            <lat>53.235693</lat>
            <lon>-4.345801</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangristiolus">Llangristiolus is a village in the middle of Anglesey, Wales, southwest of Llangefni, and is named after Saint Cristiolus. The River Cefni flows through the village. The village is within a mile of the A5 and A55 roads.
The church of St Cristiolus, Llangristiolus, dates from the 12th century.
The village was also home to Meinir Gwilym who was born in Wales in 1983, and educated at Ysgol Henblas in Llangristiolus, and also to Elin Fflur, a Welsh singer.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangristiolus">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf eglwysig yng nghanol Ynys Môn, ger Llangefni, yw Llangristiolus. Enwir y pentref ar ôl eglwys y plwyf, a gysegrir i Sant Cristiolus.
Yn Oes y Tywysogion roedd yn rhan o gwmwd Malltraeth, cantref Aberffraw. Ceir clwstwr cytiau Tyddyn Sadler gerllaw.
I'r gogledd o'r pentref ceir Rhostrehwfa.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llangwyllog">
            <name>Llangwyllog</name>
            <lat>53.29105</lat>
            <lon>-4.343293</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwyllog">Llangwyllog is a small village and ancient parish in the centre of Anglesey, Wales.
It is found three miles to the north of the island's capital, Llangefni, and two miles north of Llyn Cefni, the island's second largest body of water. The settlement was once far more important than it is today reaching a population of 277 in 1821, whereas the 1971 census showed only 75 people living there.
The Anglesey Central Railway used to operate a station in the village until its closure in 1993. The tracks however still run through the village and there is a significant railway cutting in the village.
The parish church is St Cwyllog's Church, Llangwyllog; the first church here was founded by St Cwyllog in the 6th century.
One historic event said to have taken place here in 1134 was a battle between Owain Gwynedd, the first king of Wales and the armies of the Erse, Manx, and Norsemen, who had invaded the island. In the end the Welsh leader was triumphant.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwyllog">Pentref bychan gwledig a phlwyf yng nghanol Ynys Môn yw Llangwyllog.
Fe'i lleolir tair milltir i'r gogledd o dref Llangefni a dwy filltir o Lyn Cefni. Cofnodir poblogaeth o 277 yn 1821, ond erbyn 1971 dim ond 75 o bobl oedd yn byw yno.
Mae'r eglwys yn weddol hen gyda rhannau yn dyddio o'r 15fed ganrif efallai. Yn ôl traddodiad cafodd ei sefydlu gan y Santes Cwyllog (Cywyllog) yn y 6ed ganrif ar dir a roddwyd iddi gan y brenin Maelgwn Gwynedd.
Yn yr Oesoedd Canol gorweddai'r plwyf yng nghwmwd Menai. Bu brwydr yn y cyffiniau yn y flwyddyn 1134 rhwng byddin Owain Gwynedd, brenin Teyrnas Gwynedd, a llu o Northmyn a Manawyr a geisiodd oresgyn yr ynys. Enillodd gwŷr Gwynedd y dydd.
Rhoddodd y Tywysog Llywelyn ab Iorwerth Eglwys Gwyllog a'i degwm i Briordy Penmon.
Roedd gan Lein Amlwch (Rheilffordd Canolbarth Môn) orsaf yn Llangwyllog nes i'r lein gau yn 1993. Mae'n dŷ preifat heddiw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanrhyddlad">
            <name>Llanrhyddlad</name>
            <lat>53.371745</lat>
            <lon>-4.509927</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrhyddlad">Llanrhyddlad (Welsh: Llan-Rhûddlad) is a parish in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llansadwrn">
            <name>Llansadwrn</name>
            <lat>51.966113</lat>
            <lon>-3.901252</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llansadwrn">Llansadwrn is a small village in Carmarthenshire, Wales.
It is located in the countryside of the River Tywi river valley, about half way between Llanymddyfri to the north-east, and Llandeilo to the south-west, just off the A40 road.
According to tradition, it was founded by an early Christian saint, Sadwrn (fl. around 460 AD).
Four miles to the west of the village are the ruins of Talley Abbey (Welsh: Abaty Talyllychau).
Three miles to the west is the hamlet of Waunclunda and a fort above, little information is available about this fort.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llansadwrn">Gall Llansadwrn gyfeirio at un o ddau bentref yng Nghymru:
Llansadwrn yn Sir Gaerfyrddin
Llansadwrn ar Ynys Môn
Gweler hefyd
Sadwrn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llantrisant">
            <name>Llantrisant</name>
            <lat>51.5429188</lat>
            <lon>-3.3749525</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llantrisant">Llantrisant ("Parish of the Three Saints") is a town in the county borough of Rhondda Cynon Taf in Wales, within the historic county boundaries of Glamorgan, Wales, lying on the River Ely and the Afon Clun. The three saints of the city's name are SS. Illtyd, Gwynno, and Dyfodwg. Llantrisant is a hilltop settlement, at an altitude of 174 m (565 ft) above sea level. The town is home to the Royal Mint.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llantrisant">Ceir mwy nag un lle o'r enw Llantrisant:
Llantrisant, Rhondda Cynon Taf
Llantrisant, Sir Fynwy
Llantrisant, Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llanynghenedl">
            <name>Llanynghenedl</name>
            <lat>53.29896</lat>
            <lon>-4.526728</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanynghenedl">Llanynghenedl is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanynghenedl">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd-orllewin Ynys Môn yw Llanynghenedl. Saif ar y briffordd A5025 gerllaw ei chyffordd gyda'r B5109, ychydig i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o'r Fali ac i'r de o Lanfachraeth.
Dywedir fod yr eglwys, a gysegrwyd i Sant Enghenedl (amrywiad: Ynghenedl), ar safle eglwys hŷn yn dyddio i'r 7fed ganrif.
Ceir maen hir mewn cae ger y pentref a adnabyddir fel 'Maen hir Llanynghenedl'.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llechcynfarwy">
            <name>Llechcynfarwy</name>
            <lat>53.3022028</lat>
            <lon>-4.4308726</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llechcynfarwy">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tref Alaw, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Llechcynfarwy. Mae 136.5 milltir (219.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.7 milltir (353.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llechcynfarwy yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#llynfaes">
            <name>Llynfaes</name>
            <lat>53.2789699</lat>
            <lon>-4.3864772</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llynfaes">Llynfaes is a hamlet in the community of Bodffordd, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 134.3 miles (216.1 km) from Cardiff and 217.2 miles (349.5 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llynfaes">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Bodffordd, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Llynfaes. Mae 134.3 milltir (216.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.2 milltir (349.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llynfaes yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#maenaddwyn">
            <name>Maenaddwyn</name>
            <lat>53.331394</lat>
            <lon>-4.31477</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maenaddwyn">This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target article. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maenaddwyn">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanddyfnan, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Maen-Addwyn. Mae 136.6 milltir (219.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.7 milltir (348.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Maen-Addwyn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#malltraeth">
            <name>Malltraeth</name>
            <lat>53.192112</lat>
            <lon>-4.384489</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malltraeth">Malltraeth (origin: Mall (corrupt, blasted, desolate, + Traeth (beach)) is a small village in the southwest of Anglesey, in the area of Bodorgan. It is now at the end of a large bay, which used to extend much further inland, almost creating a second sea strait in the area (the Menai Strait broke through following the end of the ice age).
After several abortive attempts, a 1 kilometre (0.62 mi) long 'cob' or dyke was completed across it during the 19th century, allowing land reclamation behind it. Despite this, the land remains very wet and prone to flooding, much of it of great natural and scientific importance as a result. The former salt marsh creeks are still visible on aerial photography and evident as shallow depressions in the fields. Coal mining occurred for a time in the underlying Carboniferous rock strata and the subsidence of these workings resulted in the lakes "Llynnau Gwaith-glo".
The village has two pubs: The Royal Oak and The Joiners. It also had a village Post Office shop, but this closed as a victim of the Royal Mail's making deep cuts in local post offices. A mainline railway runs just a few hundred metres north of the town, but there is no station. The nearest stations are Bodorgan, a request stop, which offers limited local journeys, along with Bangor and Holyhead, which offer more frequent access to longer distance travel to most parts of Wales, England, and Scotland
The long-established Meyrick landowning family of Bodorgan are located within the area, and are the owners of the Anglesey Racing Circuit near Aberffraw. Older still is the ancient standing stone found on the northern edge of the village.
For live weather and webcam view from Malltraeth, and links to aerial and ground photographs of the area and surroundings, please visit fotonix.co.uk</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malltraeth">Ardal ym Môn yw Malltraeth. Gallai'r enw gyfeirio at:
Cwmwd Malltraeth, cwmwd canoloesol
Malltraeth (pentref)
Cors Ddyga ("Malltraeth Marsh" yn Saesneg)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#marian-glas">
            <name>Marian-glas</name>
            <lat>53.335896</lat>
            <lon>-4.246625</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marian-glas">Marian-glas or Marianglas is a small village and post town in Anglesey, in north-west Wales. It is situated between the larger villages of Moelfre and Benllech and just off the A5025. There is a large caravan park on the edge of the village and several camp sites. However there is no church, pub or shop. It has a memorial to those killed in the two world wars, including a list of 17 seamen from the Merchant Navy.
Marian-glas Hut Group is an unenclosed hut circle (53.3379°N 4.2516°W﻿ / 53.3379; -4.2516﻿ (Marian-glas Hut Group), SH501846). This Scheduled Ancient Monument (Cadw SAM No. AN093) is a roundhouse settlement dating at least back to Roman times. It is also called Cae Marh Hut Group. There are several huts with thick walls, some standing up to 1.4m high. Some of the huts walls are now obscured by a thicket, while others are visible as wall lines in the lawns of Marianglas caravan park. The location is indicated on the ground through a signboard by the Ministry of Public Building and Works (which dates the sign to 1962-70).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#mariandyrys">
            <name>Mariandyrys</name>
            <lat>53.3092689</lat>
            <lon>-4.0996354</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariandyrys">Mariandyrys is a village in the community of Llangoed, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 132.2 miles (212.7km) from Cardiff and 208.5 miles (335.4km) from London.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariandyrys">Pentrefan yn Ynys Môn yw Mariandyrys. Fe'i lleolir tua milltir i'r gogledd o bentref Llangoed yng nghymuned Llangoed ar ben de-ddwyreiniol yr ynys tua hanner milltir o'r môr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#menai bridge (porthaethwy)">
            <name>Menai Bridge (Porthaethwy)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#moelfre">
            <name>Moelfre</name>
            <lat>53.352276</lat>
            <lon>-4.237343</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moelfre">Moelfre may refer to:
Moelfre, Anglesey - a village and community on the Isle of Anglesey, Wales, United Kingdom
Moelfre, Conwy - a place in the county borough of Conwy, Wales, United Kingdom
Moelfre, Gwynedd - a hill in the Snowdonia range, in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, United Kingdom
Moelfre, Powys - a hamlet in the community of Llansilin in the county of Powys, Wales, United Kingdom</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moelfre">Gallai Moelfre gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#morawelon">
            <name>Morawelon</name>
            <lat>53.2721464</lat>
            <lon>-4.5855074</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morawelon">Morawelon is an area in the community of Caergybi, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 140.2 miles (225.6 km) from Cardiff and 226.6 miles (364.6 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morawelon">Ardal (neu faestref) o fewn i Gaergybi, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Morawelon. Mae 140.2 milltir (225.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 226.6 milltir (364.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Morawelon yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#mountain">
            <name>Mountain</name>
            <lat>53.312436</lat>
            <lon>-4.6629722</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mountain">A mountain is a large landform that stretches above the surrounding land in a limited area, usually in the form of a peak. A mountain is generally steeper than a hill. Mountains are formed through tectonic forces or volcanism. These forces can locally raise the surface of the earth. Mountains erode slowly through the action of rivers, weather conditions, and glaciers. A few mountains are isolated summits, but most occur in huge mountain ranges.
High elevations on mountains produce colder climates than at sea level. These colder climates strongly affect the ecosystems of mountains: different elevations have different plants and animals. Because of the less hospitable terrain and climate, mountains tend to be used less for agriculture and more for resource extraction and recreation, such as mountain climbing.
The highest mountain on Earth is Mount Everest in the Himalayas of Asia, whose summit is 8,850 m (29,035 ft) above mean sea level. The highest known mountain on any planet in the Solar System is Olympus Mons on Mars at 21,171 m (69,459 ft).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#mynydd bodafon">
            <name>Mynydd Bodafon</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynydd Bodafon">Mynydd Bodafon is the highest point on the island of Anglesey (although not in the county of Anglesey — see Holyhead Mountain). Its summit is also known as Yr Arwydd ("the signal"). It lies about 2½ miles west of the coastal town of Moelfre and ⅔ of a mile south-west of the hamlet of Brynrefail. The meaning of Bodafon is obscure. Bod is a common placename element meaning 'dwelling' and afon here is possibly a corruption of the personal name A(e)ddan (afon is Welsh for 'river' but topography rules that out).
The terrain of Mynydd Bodafon varies greatly, from pine forest to heathland. In 2006 during an arson attack, much of this land was burnt. The walk to the top of Yr Arwydd is not a particularly difficult one and can be done by anyone with a reasonable level of fitness. There is a small lake which contains various varieties of fish, a reservoir and three springs coming from the hill. To the east of the hill is found an iron age earthwork.
Mynydd Bodafon's wildlife is typical for Anglesey. There are a growing number of rabbits which spread past the base of the hill. At one time, deer were present but were hunted and no longer exist there. Also due to hunting the number of foxes in the area has decreased. Mynydd Bodafon boasts a large number of wild birds. Various birds of prey include buzzards and a small number of peregrine falcons. The region is also a popular point of migration for swallows, who inhabit the area between mid-April to October. Recently there have been sightings of the lesser spotted woodpecker, which shows promising growth in the area. The cuckoo is regularly seen on the mountain (there is an old local song about the cuckoo on Bodafon Mountain).
Although the name Mynydd Bodafon may refer to the hill itself, it is also the name for the wider geographical area, which is part of the Penrhoslligwy area. Traditionally a Welsh area, many English people have moved there over the last few decades. The area is very popular with tourists, who use it for walking and sometimes fishing. Agriculture is the economy of the area - mainly cattle and sheep.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynydd Bodafon">Bryn ar Ynys Môn yw Mynydd Bodafon. Ei bwynt uchaf yw copa Yr Arwydd (178 m / 585'). Hwn yw'r bryn uchaf ar yr ynys. Mynydd Eilian yw'r ail uchaf, (177 m / 581'.) Pwynt uchaf y sir ydy Mynydd Tŵr 220m, 720' sydd yn ddaearyddol ar Ynys Gybi nid Ynys Môn.
Lleolir Mynydd Bodafon yng ngogledd-ddwyrain yr ynys, tua hanner ffordd rhwng Llannerch-y-medd i'r gorllewin a Moelfre i'r dwyrain. Mae ar y ffin rhwng plwyfi Penrhosllugwy a Llanfihangel Tre'r Beirdd; cyfeiriad grid SH472854. Uchder cymharol, neu ”amlygrwydd” y copa, ydy 0metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
Mae union ystyr yr enw Bodafon yn ansicr. Mae bod (trigfan) yn elfen gyffredin mewn enwau lleoedd, ond does dim afon yn y cylch i esbonio'r enw. Fodd bynnag, ceir Llyn Archaddon fel hen enw ar y llyn bychan ar lethr y mynydd a elwir yn Llyn Bodafon heddiw. Gall Bodafon fod yn amrywiad ar Bodaddon (gyda -dd yn newid i -f, fel sy'n digwydd weithiau). Felly bod (trigfan) + aeddon ('arglwydd') neu A(e)ddon (enw personol), efallai.
Ceir olion Cytiau'r Gwyddelod, sy'n perthyn i Oes yr Haearn yn ôl pob tebyg, ar lethrau'r mynydd.
Mae'r bryn yn boblogaidd gan bobl leol i fynd am dro neu i bysgota. Ceir golygfa dros Fôn o'r copa.
Enwir Yr Arwydd, papur bro cylch Mynydd Bodafon, ar ôl enw copa'r bryn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#mynydd mechell">
            <name>Mynydd Mechell</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynydd Mechell">Mynydd Mechell is an area in the community of Mechell, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 141.9 miles (228.4 km) from Cardiff and 223.8 miles (360.2 km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#nebo">
            <name>Nebo</name>
            <lat>53.0300719</lat>
            <lon>-4.269537</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebo">Nebo may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebo">Ceir mwy nag un enghraifft o'r enw Nebo:
Nebo - Duw Babilonaidd
Y Dwyrain Canol
Nebo - dinas Feiblaidd, yn Iwda
Nebo - dinas Feiblaidd, ym Moab
Cymru
Nebo - pentref yn Nyffryn Aeron, Ceredigion
Nebo - pentref yn Sir Conwy
Nebo - pentref yng Ngwynedd
Nebo - pentref ar Ynys Môn
Awstralia
Nebo - tref yn Queensland
Swydd Nebo
Yr Unol Daleithiau
Nebo, Illinois
Nebo, Kentucky
Nebo, Gogledd Carolina
Nebo Center, Califfornia
Ardal Ysgol Nebo, ardal ysgol yn Swydd Utah, Utah
Mynyddoedd
Enwir sawl mynydd gyda'r enw hwn, gweler dudalen gwahaniaethu Mynydd Nebo</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#newborough (niwbwrch)">
            <name>Newborough (Niwbwrch)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#newlands park">
            <name>Newlands Park</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#niwbwrch (newborough)">
            <name>Niwbwrch (Newborough)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#nodwydd">
            <name>Nodwydd</name>
            <lat>53.2822354</lat>
            <lon>-4.2189242</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nodwydd">Gall nodwydd, neu nodwyddau gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#parciau">
            <name>Parciau</name>
            <lat>52.8462026</lat>
            <lon>-4.5241479</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pen-llyn">
            <name>Pen-llyn</name>
            <lat>53.313298</lat>
            <lon>-4.474438</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-llyn">Pentrefan ar lan gogleddol Llyn Llywenan yng nghymuned Bodedern, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Pen-llyn. Mae 137.9 milltir (221.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 221.6 milltir (356.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pen-llyn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pen-lon">
            <name>Pen-lon</name>
            <lat>53.158848</lat>
            <lon>-4.350763</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pen-y-garnedd">
            <name>Pen-y-garnedd</name>
            <lat>53.215844</lat>
            <lon>-4.1467356</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-garnedd">Pen-y-garnedd is a village in the community of Pentraeth, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 130.6 miles (210.2km) from Cardiff and 210.1 miles (338.2km) from London.
^ Google Maps (Map). Google.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-garnedd">Pentref yng nghymuned Pentraeth, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Pen-y-garnedd. Mae 130.6 milltir (210.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.1 milltir (338.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pen-y-garnedd yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pencarnisiog">
            <name>Pencarnisiog</name>
            <lat>53.233332</lat>
            <lon>-4.470307</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pencarnisiog">Pencarnisiog is a village in the community of Llanfaelog, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 132.9 miles (213.8km) from Cardiff and 218.5 miles (351.6km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pencarnisiog">Pentref bychan ar Ynys Môn yw Pencarnisiog (hefyd: Pencaernisiog). Fe'i lleolir yng ngogledd-orllewin yr ynys ar yr A4080 tua milltir i'r dwyrain o bentref Llanfaelog a thua 8 filltir i'r gorllewin o dref Llangefni.
Ceir dwy ffordd o sillafu enw'r pentref. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd treflan o'r enw Conysiog yno ('Tir Conws'). Tyfodd pentref bychan a galwyd y lle yn 'Penconisiog'. Tybid fod yr enw yn cynnwys y gair caer ac felly cafwyd yr enw 'Pencaernisiog'.
Yn ymyl y pentref ceir siambr gladdu neolithig Tŷ Newydd.
Lleolir Ysgol Pencarnisiog yn y pentref, ysgol gynradd sydd yn nhalgylch Ysgol Uwchradd Bodedern.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pencraig">
            <name>Pencraig</name>
            <lat>52.225627</lat>
            <lon>-3.099451</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pencraig">Pentref a chymuned ym Mhowys, yw Pencraig (Saesneg: Old Radnor). Saif rhwng Maesyfed a Llanandras, ychydig i'r de o'r briffordd A44 ac ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r ffîn a Lloegr.
Mae eglwys plwyf Pencraig yn dyddio o'r 15fed ganrif ac yn cynnwys y cas organ hynaf ym Mhrydain.
Heblaw pentref Pencraig, mae'r gymuned yn cynnwys pentrefi Evenjobb a Walton. Cafwyd hyd i balisâd mawr o goed o'r cyfnod Neolithig yn Walton yn ddiweddar. Codwyd y castell mwnt a beili yn Womaston cyn 1066, a chredir mai hwn oedd yn cynharaf yng Nghymru. Bu George Cornewall Lewis yn byw yn Harpton Court. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 741.
Ceir Allt Pencraig (Old Radnor Hill) yn y gymuned.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pengorffwysfa">
            <name>Pengorffwysfa</name>
            <lat>53.40254</lat>
            <lon>-4.307989</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pengorffwysfa">Pengorffwysfa is a village in Anglesey, in north-west Wales.
The village lies on the crossroad between Penysarn and Porth Eilian and Point Lynas Lighthouse, with turnings down towards Amlwch Port and Amlwch town, and the ascent for Llaneilian Mountain and heading towards Dulas Bay. This road forms part of the National Cycle Network Route 566, known as the Copper Trail, taking in the north coast of Anglesey that is designated an Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty, and the nearby remains of the historical copper mines at Parys Mountain.
The village has a Calvinist chapel, Capel Seilo, built in 1835 to replace a smaller chapel built in 1826.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pengorffwysfa">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llaneilian, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Pengorffwysfa. Mae 141.1 milltir (227.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.3 milltir (352.9 km) o Lundain. Saif Mynydd Eilian fymryn i'r dwyrain o'r pentref. Mae'n gorwedd i'r de o bentref Llaneilian ac i'r gogledd o bentref Penysarn.
Cynrychiolir Pen-Gorphwysfa yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penmon">
            <name>Penmon</name>
            <lat>53.304152</lat>
            <lon>-4.058777</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmon">Penmon is a promontory, village and ecclesiastical parish on the south-east tip of the Isle of Anglesey in Wales, about 3 miles (4.8 km) east of the town of Beaumaris. It is in the community of Llangoed. The name comes from Welsh: pen (which can mean "head", "end" or "promontory") and Môn, which is the Welsh word for Anglesey. It is the site of an historic monastery and associated 12th-century church. Walls near the well next to the church may be part of the oldest remaining Christian building in Wales. Penmon also has an award-winning beach and the Anglesey Coastal Path follows its shores. Quarries in Penmon have provided stone for many important buildings and structures, including Birmingham Town Hall and the two bridges that cross the Menai Strait. The area is popular with locals and visitors alike for its monuments, tranquillity, bracing air and fine views of Snowdonia to the south across the Menai Strait.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmon">Llecyn a phlwyf eglwysig ar gongl de-ddwyreiniol Ynys Môn yw Penmon (Pen 'terfyn, diwedd' + Môn). Mae'n gorwedd i'r gogledd o Fiwmaris ac i'r dwyrain o blwyf Llangoed. Mae ei arfordir dwyreiniol yn gorwedd ar Afon Menai. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd yn rhan o cwmwd Dindaethwy, cantref Menai. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llangoed a Phenmon.
Mae'r ardal yn cynnwys Priordy Penmon, Castell Aberlleiniog, a chymunedau bychain Trecastell ac Aberlleiniog. Trwyn Du yw enw'r penrhyn ar bwynt eithaf Penmon. Ceir goleudy, maes parcio a chaffi yno a chyferbyn mae Ynys Seiriol, gynt yn eiddo i briordy Penmon.
Mae yma fynachdy o'r 6ed ganrif (Priordy Penmon) a gafodd ei ail-adeiladu wedyn yn y 12fed ganrif. Mae dwy groes Geltaidd yn dyddio o tua'r 10fed ganrif, oedd yn arfer sefyll y tu allan i'r mynachdy, yn awr i mewn yn yr eglwys.
Yn Oes y Tywysogion gorweddai Penmon yng nghwmwd Dindaethwy, cantref Rhosyr.
Ger priordy Penmon ceir colomendy i ddal bron i fil o nythod a deiladwyd yn 1600.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penmynydd">
            <name>Penmynydd</name>
            <lat>53.245435</lat>
            <lon>-4.233734</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmynydd">Penmynydd, meaning top of the mountain in Welsh, is a village on Anglesey island, off the north west coast of Wales, situated on a slight hill on the B5420 road between Menai Bridge and Llangefni, at grid reference SH510743. The Royal Mail postcode begins LL61 with a community population taken at the 2011 cenus of 465. When Welsh nobleman Rhys ap Tudur was executed in 1412, lands of the Penmynydd family were forfeited. The village includes the Neuadd Lwyd, a former Victorian rectory that was converted into a country-house hotel. The village is notable for its almshouses. A radio communication transmission mast was installed in 2002 a few yards north of the village at the top of the hill.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmynydd">Mae Penmynydd yn bentref a chymuned ar Ynys Môn, ar y ffordd gefn B5420 rhwng Porthaethwy a Llangefni. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Penmynydd a Star.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penrhos">
            <name>Penrhos</name>
            <lat>53.300496</lat>
            <lon>-4.600263</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhos">Penrhos may refer to:
Penrhos, Anglesey, Wales
home of Penrhos Country Park

Penrhos, Gwynedd, Wales
RAF Penrhos, Gwynedd, Wales

Penrhos, Herefordshire, England
Penrhos, Monmouthshire, Wales
Penrhos, Powys, Wales
Penrhos College, Perth, an independent school for girls in Western Australia</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhos">Gallai Penrhos neu Pen-rhos gyfeirio at un o sawl lle yng Nghymru:
Penrhos, Gwynedd
Penrhos, Powys
Penrhos, Sir Fynwy
Gweler hefyd
Penrhosgarnedd, Gwynedd
Penrhosllugwy, Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penrhosfeilw">
            <name>Penrhosfeilw</name>
            <lat>53.294305</lat>
            <lon>-4.66491</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhosfeilw">Penrhosfeilw is a village in the community of Trearddur, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 140.1 miles (225.4km) from Cardiff and 227.5 miles (366.1km) from London.
^ Google Maps (Map). Google.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhosfeilw">Pentref yng nghymuned Trearddur, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Penrhosfeilw. Mae 140.1 milltir (225.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 227.5 milltir (366.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Penrhosfeilw yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penrhyd lastra">
            <name>Penrhyd Lastra</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhyd Lastra">Penrhyd Lastra is a hamlet in the community of Amlwch, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 141.9 miles (228.3km) from Cardiff and 221.2 miles (355.9km) from London.
^ Google Maps (Map). Google.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhyd Lastra">Pentrefan tua cilometr i'r de o Amlwch, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Penrhyd Lastra. Mae 141.9 milltir (228.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 221.2 milltir (355.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Penrhyd Lastra yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).
↑ Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
↑ Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penrhyn mawr">
            <name>Penrhyn Mawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pentraeth">
            <name>Pentraeth</name>
            <lat>53.281821</lat>
            <lon>-4.2162879</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentraeth">Pentraeth is a village on the island of Anglesey (Ynys Môn), North Wales, at grid reference SH523786. The Royal Mail postcode begins LL75. The community population taken at the 2011 census was 1,178.
Its Welsh name means at the end of (or head of) a beach, and it is located near Traeth Coch (Red Wharf Bay). There is a small river, Afon Nodwydd which runs through it. The village's ancient name was Llanfair Betws Geraint. In 1170 it was the site of a battle when Hywel ab Owain Gwynedd landed with an army raised in Ireland in an attempt to claim a share of the kingdom of Gwynedd following the death of his father Owain Gwynedd. He was defeated and killed here by the forces of his half-brothers Dafydd ab Owain Gwynedd and Rhodri.
In 1859, Charles Dickens stayed in the village on his trip, as a journalist for The Times, to visit the wreck of the Royal Charter in Moelfre. Between 1908 and 1950 it was served by Pentraeth railway station, on the Red Wharf Bay branch line.
The village has a football side, Pentraeth F.C., who play in the Gwynedd League, the fourth tier of Welsh football.
The centre of the village is The Square. It is bounded by St. Mary's Church and the Panton Arms public house as well as a row of shops called Cloth Hall. This was founded in the 19th century by Benjamin Thomas as a general store. It continued as a grocery store into the 1990s, and is now occupied by a carpet shop as well as a bakery and party-ware hire shop.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 20 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentraeth">Pentref a chymuned yn ne-ddwyrain Môn, Cymru, yw Pentraeth, ar lôn yr A5025. Ceir Gwarchodfa Natur Cenedlaethol Cors Bodeilio gerllaw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pentre berw">
            <name>Pentre Berw</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentre Berw">Pentre Berw is a small village located on the island of Anglesey in north Wales. It lies about 2 miles (3.2 km) south of the county town of Llangefni.
A major road, the A5, runs through the village as does the disused Anglesey Central Railway. Indeed the village's most famous hotel The Holland Arms even had a station named after it. The village is located at the top of a gentle slope on the eastern edge of the Malltraeth Marshes. Therefore a good view of the marshes and also of the Afon Cefni can be taken in from parts of the village.

Plas Berw, a country house which dates back from the early 17th century, is near the village. It also has formal gardens and a deer park. The grounds cover some 8.5 acres (34,000 m2) and it is a Grade II listed building. Llanfihangel Ysceifiog (St Michael's church), although ruined, is a good example of a traditional Welsh church. It is situated just north of the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentre Berw">Pentref yn rhan ddeheuol Ynys Môn yw Pentre Berw. Saif ar y briffordd A5, ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r Gaerwen a gerllaw Afon Cefni, ar ymylon Cors Ddyga.
Mae 'berw' yn ffurf ar y gair 'berwr' (cress). Berw oedd enw'r dref ganoloesol (cymuned o ffermydd a thai ar wasgar); tyfodd pentref ar y groesffordd a gafodd yr enw 'Pentre Berw'.
Yn y pentref mae gwesty yr Holland Arms a chanolfan garddio fawr o'r un enw. Roedd Rheilffordd Canol Môn yn gadael y prif reilffordd i Gaergybi gerllaw'r pentref. Ar un adeg yr oedd diwydiant glo bychan yn yr ardal, a gellir gweld rhai o'r hen adeiladau o hyd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pentrefelin">
            <name>Pentrefelin</name>
            <lat>52.934281</lat>
            <lon>-4.193056</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentrefelin">Mae Pentrefelin yn enw ar sawl lle yng Nghymru:
Pentrefelin, Ceredigion
Pentrefelin, Conwy
Pentrefelin, Gwynedd
Pentrefelin, Powys
Pentrefelin, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Pentrefelin, Ynys Môn, ar gyrion Amlwch
Gweler hefyd:
Pentre'r Felin (gwahaniaethu)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penygraigwen">
            <name>Penygraigwen</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygraigwen">Penygraigwen is a village in the community of Rhosybol, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 138.9 miles (223.6km) from Cardiff and 218.5 miles (351.6km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygraigwen">Pentref yng nghymuned Rhosybol, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Penygraigwen. Mae 138.9 milltir (223.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.5 milltir (351.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Penygraigwen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#penysarn">
            <name>Penysarn</name>
            <lat>53.3893402</lat>
            <lon>-4.3169297</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penysarn">Penysarn (/pɛnˈsɑrn/; Welsh pronunciation: [pɛnˈsarn]) is a small village located in the north-eastern corner of Anglesey, Wales, and on the north-eastern side of Parys Mountain, at approximately 140–150 feet above sea level.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penysarn">Am y pentref ger Abergele, Sir Conwy, gweler Pensarn.

Pentref yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn yw Penysarn. Saif ychydig i'r dwyrain o Fynydd Parys, a gerllaw'r briffordd A5025 rhwng Amlwch a Llanallgo. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llaneilian.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#point lynas">
            <name>Point Lynas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Point Lynas">This is a redirect from a title that potentially could be expanded into a new article or other type of associated Wikipedia page. The topic described by this title is more detailed than what is currently provided on the target page, or section of that page. For more information follow the category link.
When the target page becomes too large, this redirect may be replaced with a page carved out of the target page. See also {{R to section}}, and when appropriate, use both together.
If the topic is not susceptible to a major expansion, then instead of this rcat, tag this redirect with {{R to section}} or {{R to list entry}} as applicable.
Do not replace links to this redirect with a link directly to the target page.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#pont hwfa">
            <name>Pont Hwfa</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#porth-y-felin">
            <name>Porth-y-felin</name>
            <lat>53.314817</lat>
            <lon>-4.642079</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#porthaethwy (menai bridge)">
            <name>Porthaethwy (Menai Bridge)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#porthllechog (bull bay)">
            <name>Porthllechog (Bull Bay)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#puffin island">
            <name>Puffin Island</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puffin Island">Puffin Island is the name of several islands in a number of countries. In most cases the island has been so named because it has – or used to have – a colony of puffins.
Puffin Islands include:
Canada
Puffin Island (Baccalieu Tickle), Newfoundland and Labrador
Puffin Island (Greenspond), Newfoundland and Labrador
Iceland
Puffin Island, Reykjavík
Ireland
Puffin Island (County Kerry)
United Kingdom
Puffin Island (Anglesey), Wales
Lundy in the Bristol Channel may also be included, as its name means "Puffin Island" in Norse
United States
Puffin Island (Alaska)
Puffin Island (Maine)
Puffin Island (Washington)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#red wharf bay">
            <name>Red Wharf Bay</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhos lligwy">
            <name>Rhos Lligwy</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhos Lligwy">Pentref yng nghymuned Moelfre, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Rhos Lligwy. Mae 137.5 milltir (221.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.3 milltir (348 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rhos Lligwy yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhoscefnhir">
            <name>Rhoscefnhir</name>
            <lat>53.2666251</lat>
            <lon>-4.2161009</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhoscolyn">
            <name>Rhoscolyn</name>
            <lat>53.250164</lat>
            <lon>-4.59686</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoscolyn">Rhoscolyn is a village located on Holy Island, Anglesey, Wales. It is just over five miles south of Holyhead and is the most southerly settlement on the island. The name Rhoscolyn is said to mean "The Moor" (Rhos) of The Column (colyn), referring to a pillar which the Romans put up to mark the edge of their territories. The community population taken from the 2011 census was 542.
A little to the west of the village is a mediaeval well dedicated to St Gwenfaen beside which are the remains of a drystone well house measuring 4.5 m east-west by 5.5 m. The local church in the village itself is dedicated to the same saint and was first built in the 6th century.
Rhoscolyn is bordered to the south by a small enclosed bay called Borthwen which is bordered by a public beach. There was once a lifeboat station on Borthwen which was open between 1830 and 1929 which has been replaced by a navigational beacon on Ynysoedd Gwylanod (Gulls' Island). Around these waters at the end of the 18th century was a thriving oyster catching industry, but this declined once the beds had been depleted. Existing buildings include the local pub, The White Eagle, reportedly a favourite of Prince William of Wales, and the primary school which is found just over a mile north of the village.
Probably the most significant lifeboat incident here was the launch to the Timbo. On December 1 1920 the small coaster, was en route to Ireland from Holyhead when she was overcome by a storm off South Stack and began to drift down the coast. The lifeboat was launched, with great difficulty in the heavy seas, and made a number of attempts to get a line aboard her, without success, until the cox decided no more could be done and the lifeboat started its return journey, from a point close to Llanddwyn Island. The lifeboat capsized and 5 of the 13 man crew were lost, and, a little later, 4 men from the Timbo as well. The ship eventually became stranded at Dinas Dinlle, was eventually refloated with the use of tugs until she struck the Carreg y Trai (Ebb Rocks) reef off Abersoch and was lost.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoscolyn">Cymuned a phentref bychan ar Ynys Gybi, Ynys Môn yw Rhoscolyn. Ffurfia ran ddeheuol Ynys Gybi.
Mae'r gymuned hon yn cynnwys pentref Pontrhydybont yn ogystal a Rhoscolyn ei hun. Sefydlwyd un o fadau achub cyntaf Ynys Môn yma tua 1830. Roedd y boblogaeth yn 2001 yn 484.
Ceir Eglwys y Santes Gwenfaen yn Rhoscolyn. Gwenfaen yw nawddsant y plwyf a dywedir mai 'Llanwenfaen' oedd yr hen enw am Roscolyn ei hun. Enwir yr ysgol gynradd leol yn Ysgol Gwenfaen ar ei hôl.
Ganwyd y paffiwr Atholl Oakeley yn Rhoscolyn yn 1900.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhosgoch">
            <name>Rhosgoch</name>
            <lat>53.377121</lat>
            <lon>-4.390969</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosgoch">Rhosgoch (Red Moor) is a small village in the north of the island of Anglesey, Wales about 3.5 miles (5.6 km) to the south-west of Amlwch.
A short distance to the west of the village is the small lake Llyn Hafodol and a mile to the south is Anglesey's largest body of water the reservoir Llyn Alaw (Water Lily Lake).
The village once was home to one of the stations on the Anglesey Central Railway. Although the tracks still exist no train has run on them since 1993.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosgoch">Pentref yng nghymuned Rhosybol, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Rhosgoch. Mae 140.7 milltir (226.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 221.1 milltir (355.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rhosgoch yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhosmeirch">
            <name>Rhosmeirch</name>
            <lat>53.27417</lat>
            <lon>-4.310534</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosmeirch">Rhosmeirch is a small village in Anglesey, Wales.
It is located 1 1⁄2 miles (2.4 km) north of the county town, Llangefni, and half a mile west of the reservoir Llyn Cefni.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosmeirch">Pentref bychan ar Ynys Môn yw Rhosmeirch (cyfeiriad grid SH461776). Mae'n gorwedd yng nghanol yr ynys tua milltir a hanner i'r gogledd o dref Llangefni ac mae'n rhan o gymuned Llangefni.
Rhed yr hen ffordd o Langefni i Amlwch (y B5111) trwy'r pentref. Tua chwarter milltir i'r gorllewin ceir Llyn Cefni, cronfa ddŵr Llangefni.
Mae Rhosmeirch yn adnabyddus am ei le yn hanes yr Annibynwyr a chyfrifir Capel Ebenezer, ar gwr y pentref, yn un o gapeli pwysicaf yr enwad hwnnw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhosneigr">
            <name>Rhosneigr</name>
            <lat>53.228996</lat>
            <lon>-4.519761</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosneigr">Rhosneigr is a village in the south-west of Anglesey, North Wales. It is situated on the A4080 road some 10 km south-east of Holyhead, and is on the Anglesey Coastal Path. From the clock at the centre of the village can be seen RAF Valley and Holyhead Mountain. The major towns of Holyhead and Llangefni and the city of Bangor are all within easy travelling distance. It is the most expensive place to live in Anglesey in terms of house prices.
The village contains four caravan sites, three camp sites, holiday homes and bungalows, pubs, hotels, cafes, a new village hall, a chapel, residential homes, a school, a fire station, a convenience store and Post Office, a pharmacy and a fish and chip shop. It is served by Rhosneigr railway station.
Recreational activities include: swimming, surfing, wind surfing, kite surfing, wakeboarding, shore and boat fishing, water skiing, golf, tennis and underwater diving. The village is home to Anglesey Golf Club.
It has three main beaches:
'Traeth Cymyran' that stretches from Afon Crigyll estuary to the Cymyran Strait.
'Pwll Cwch' and the 'Town Beach' – a small, rocky beach where boats and yachts stay overnight, running into a sandy beach interspersed by rocks and views of Snowdonia. It is popular with watersports enthusiasts, notably windsurfers and sailors.
'Traeth Llydan' which runs from the Barclodiad y Gawres ancient monument to Rhosneigr, ranging from pebble shores to pristine sandy shores. It is perfect for canoeing, walking and surfing. Broad Beach is a regular Green Coast Award Winner and is backed by sand dunes.
Llyn Maelog or Maelog lake is around 65 acres in total with varying depth up to seven feet. It is a designated Site of Special Scientific Interest. There is a good stock of fish in the lake including perch, bream, roach and pike. A large variety of birdlife inhabits the reedbeds. grey heron, snipe, reed warblers, coots, mallard, shelducks etc.. Black headed gulls nest on the small island. The lake is circled by public footpath and is popular with walkers. In 2011 it became the first lake in Wales to be classified as a village green.
Maelog Lake Golf Club (now defunct) appeared prior to WW1. The club and course disappeared at the onset of WW2.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosneigr">Pentref ar arfordir gorllewinol Ynys Môn yw Rhosneigr. Saif ar y briffordd A4080. Erbyn hyn mae'n bentref gwyliau yn bennaf.
Mae traeth bychan gerllaw'r pentref ei hun, a dau draeth mwy, Traeth Cymyran a Thraeth Llydan, gerllaw. Ceir gorsaf reilffordd yno, yn ogystal a nifer o westai a thai bwyta. Twristiaeth yw'r prif ddiwydiant, er fod rhai o'r trigolion yn gweithio ym maes awyr Y Fali gerllaw. Mae Llyn Maelog gerllaw a Llwybr Arfordirol Ynys Môn yn rhedeg heibio'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhostrehwfa">
            <name>Rhostrehwfa</name>
            <lat>53.247556</lat>
            <lon>-4.337973</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhostrehwfa">Rhostrehwfa is a village in southern-central Anglesey, located southwest of Llangefni. To the southeast is the Malltraeth Marsh. It is "situated at a prominent point on the crest of a ridge overlooking the River Cefni valley to the south."It contains the Capel Pisgah and several holiday cottages.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhostrehwfa">Pentref bychan ar Ynys Môn yw Rhostrehwfa (cyfeiriad grid SH440746). Fe'i lleolir tua 2 filltir i'r de-orllewin o dref Llangefni a milltir i'r gogledd o Langristiolus.
Gorwedd Rhostrehwfa ar hyd lôn y B4422 o'i chyffordd â'r A55.
Mae'r enw yn hen ac yn tarddu o enw'r dreflan ganoloesol, Tre Hwfa. Roedd Hwfa yn bennaeth lleol yn yr Oesoedd Canol ac roedd nifer o deuluoedd mawr Môn yn ddisgynyddion iddo.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhosybol">
            <name>Rhosybol</name>
            <lat>53.3683369</lat>
            <lon>-4.368121</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosybol">Rhosybol (English: Moor in the Hollow) is a village in Anglesey, Wales. The community population at the 2011 census was 1,078. Located four kilometres south of the town of Amlwch, the village is close to both Llyn Alaw, the largest body of water on the island, and Parys Mountain, the historic copper mines. It is to the mines that the village owes its existence as it was one of several built to house the miners. During the 1960s noted painter Kyffin Williams produced an oil painting of the village.
Rhosybol has a Post Office which is incorporated within its small corner shop. There is also a primary school for boys and girls between the ages of 4 and 11, in the playground of which is the village's war memorial clock tower. The memorial is unusual in that it only shows the names of those who fell in the First World War and not those in the Second. The village church is named Christ Church and is disused but there is a chapel named Capel Gorslwyd where services are still held.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 19 May 2015. 
^ Rhosybol on allaboutanglesey.co.uk
^ Williams' picture on bbc.co.uk
^ Post Office location and opening times
^ The Estyn (inspection board) report on the school
^ The war memorial on Anglesey.info
^ Coflein page on the church</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosybol">Pentref bychan a chymuned ar Ynys Môn yw Rhosybol (neu Rhos-y-bol). Saif yng ngogledd yr ynys ar y B5111, hanner ffordd rhwng Amlwch i'r gogledd a Llannerch-y-medd i'r de.
Pentref estynedig sy'n gorwedd o neilldu'r lôn ydyw. Mae'r pentref yn rhan o blwyf eglwysig Amlwch. Tri chwarter milltir i'r gorllewin ceir pen dwyreiniol Llyn Alaw, ond does dim mynediad hawdd iddo o Rosybol. Milltir a hanner i'r gogledd o Rosybol ceir Mynydd Parys sy'n enwog am ei hen gloddfeydd copr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#rhydwyn">
            <name>Rhydwyn</name>
            <lat>53.370848</lat>
            <lon>-4.534573</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhydwyn">Rhydwyn (Rhyd-Wyn) is a village located at the north west of Anglesey, Wales
Rhydwyn is named after a little stream crossing the centre of the village; "Rhyd" means ford and "Wyn" white.
There are roughly fifty people living in the village as of 2010.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhydwyn">Pentrefan gwledig yng nghymuned Cylch y Garn ar Ynys Môn yw Rhydwyn (weithiau Rhyd-wyn). Saif yng ngogledd yr ynys ym mhlwyf Llanrhuddlad, tua milltir i'r gorllewin o'r pentref hwnnw a milltir o fae Porth Swtan ar yr arfordir i'r gorllewin. Milltir a hanner i'r de ceir pentref Llanfaethlu. Mae 142.5 milltir (229.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 225.7 milltir (363.3 km) o Lundain.
Ystyr yr enw yw 'rhyd Gwyn' (enw personol). Gellir cyrraedd y pentref trwy troi oddi ar yr A5025 ger Llanrhuddlad neu Lanfaethlu.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#soar">
            <name>Soar</name>
            <lat>51.537778</lat>
            <lon>-3.302269</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soar">Soar may refer to:
160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (Airborne), a US Army regiment
The Special Operations Assault Rifle, primary assault rifle for the special forces unit of the Philippine National Police
Soar (cognitive architecture), a symbolic cognitive architecture
"Soar", a song by Christina Aguilera from the album Stripped (2002)
Soar (album), the second album (released 1991) by the American band Samiam
Hank Soar (1914–2001), American football player, baseball umpire and basketball coach
Safe operating area, typically used to describe power limitations of electronic components
Southern Astrophysical Research Telescope, a modern 4.1-meter-aperture optical and near-infrared telescope located on Cerro Pachón, Chile
SOAR Student Orientation And Registration
Surgical Outcomes Analysis and Research, a research collaborative in the department of surgery the Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center
An increased growth in the height of a mountain
Soaring, a mode of flight
Soar, a fictional airline in Flight Simulator X
Situation, Obstacles, Actions, Results
Any of several places in England:
The River Soar, a river in the East Midlands
Soar, Nottinghamshire
Soar, Devon
Old Soar Manor, an English Heritage property

Any of several places in Wales:
Soar, Anglesey
Soar, Gwynedd
Soar, Powys</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soar">Gallai Soar gyfeirio at:
Soar, dinas y cyfeirir ati yn llyfr Genesis yn yr Hen Destament
neu un o sawl lle yng Nghymru;
Soar, Ynys Môn
Soar, Gwynedd
Soar, Powys
Soar, Sir Gaerfyrddin
neu Loegr;
Afon Soar
Soar, Dyfnaint
Soar, Swydd Nottingham</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#stryd">
            <name>Stryd</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stryd">Ffordd mewn tref neu ddinas yw stryd fel arfer, gyda siopau neu tai (a.y.y.b.) bob ochr iddi.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#stryd y facsen">
            <name>Stryd y Facsen</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#talwrn">
            <name>Talwrn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talwrn">Talwrn is a small hamlet on the Isle of Anglesey, an island off the coast of north Wales. Talwrn is most notable for the Grade II-listed 16th-century manor house of Plas Llanddyfnan, which lies just to the north of the hamlet. Plas Llanddyfnan is a Queen Anne manor house from the early 1700s. Plas Llanddyfnan was owned by seven generations of the Griffiths family.

To the west and south of Talwrn are a number of unimproved fields which have been designated as a site of special scientific interest because of the botanical assemblage supported on the neutral grassland and mire.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talwrn">Gallai talwrn gyfeirio at:
Pentrefi
Talwrn, Ynys Môn
Talwrn Green, Sir Wrecsam
Ysgol
Ysgol Talwrn, Ynys Môn
Rhaglen radio
Talwrn y Beirdd (neu "Y Talwrn")</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#the skerries">
            <name>The Skerries</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The Skerries">This is a redirect from an ambiguous page name to a disambiguation page. These redirects are pointed to by links that should always be disambiguated. Therefore, this template should never appear on a page that has "(disambiguation)" in its title. Use {{R to disambiguation page}} instead. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#trearddur">
            <name>Trearddur</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trearddur">Trearddur Bay is a village south of Holyhead on the west coast of Holy Island off the north-west coast of Anglesey in Wales. At the 2001 census, it had a population of 1,858, reducing to 1,686 at the 2011 census.
The historical name for Trearddur Bay is Towyn Capel or Tywyn y Capel, and at the centre of the beach lies an ancient burial ground known by the old names and which was excavated in 2003.
There are two general shops in the centre of the village, along with a garage, two golf courses (one 18-hole, and one small 9-hole), and two hotels including a large hotel, Trearddur Bay Hotel, which overlooks the beach. There is also a number of self-catering holiday cottages, many with views of the sea and easy access to the beaches.
On the two beaches — Porth Diana and the main beach — there are some shallow scuba diving sites, and the main beach is one of the tourist hotspots of Anglesey. There is excellent sea fishing in the area. Boat trips and fishing trips are available from the beach. Horse riding is available, as well as a range of watersports. Visitors can walk along the Anglesey Coastal Footpath towards neighbouring Rhoscolyn or in the other direction towards Porth Dafarch and on to South Stack and the RSPB Reserve and lighthouse.
Near the beach is a play area and a football pitch where Trearddur Bay United F.C. play.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trearddur">Mae Trearddur, weithiau Bae Trearddur (Saesneg: Trearddur Bay), yn bentref a chymuned ar arfordir gorllewinol Ynys Cybi ger Ynys Môn, ar y ffordd B4545 rhwng Y Fali a Chaergybi. Mae na ddwy siop yma yng nghalon y pentref a modurdy, dau glwb golff (un 18 twll ac un 9 twll) a sawl gwesty gan gynnwys Gwesty Bae Trearddur, yng ngolwg y môr.
Pentref gwyliau yw Trearddur yn bennaf erbyn hyn, fel mae ffigurau'r Cyfrifiad (isod) yn dangos; mae ganddo draeth tywodlyd a nifer o westai, tafarnau, bwytai a siopau. Mae Clwb Golff Caergybi gerllaw, a gellir dilyn Llwybr yr Arfordir i'r de i Roscolyn ac i'r gogledd i Ynys Lawd. Mae yna ddau draeth mewn gwirionedd: Bae Trearddur ei hun a Phorth Dafarch, a rhyngddyn nhw mae yna le sy'n cael ei ddefnyddio ar gyfer plymio sgwba. Mae yna farchogaeth ceffylau gerllaw a thripiau neu wibdeithiau a physgota môr.
Ar fin y traeth ceir llecyn chwarae pêl-droed ble mae'r tim lleol yn chwarae.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#trefdraeth">
            <name>Trefdraeth</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefdraeth">Trefdraeth is a hamlet in the Bodorgan Community of Anglesey, Wales, about 5 miles (8 km) southwest of the county town of Llangefni.
Trefdraeth's Church in Wales parish church of St Beuno dates from the 13th century.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefdraeth">Ceir mwy nag un lle o'r enw Trefdraeth yng Nghymru:
Trefdraeth - plwyf eglwysig hanesyddol ar Ynys Môn
Trefdraeth - tref yn Sir Benfro
Trefdraeth - pentrefan ym Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#trefor">
            <name>Trefor</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefor">Trefor is a village on the north coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in Gwynedd, Wales. Its population, with nearby Llanaelhaearn is 1,560.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefor">Erthygl am y pentref yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Gweler hefyd Trefor (gwahaniaethu).

.
Pentref gerllaw Yr Eifl ar arfordir gogleddol Llŷn yng Ngwynedd yw Trefor. Saif ychydig oddi ar y briffordd A499 o Gaernarfon i Bwllheli, rhwng Clynnog Fawr a Llanaelhaearn, lle maer'r briffordd yn gadael yr arfordir ac yn troi tua'r de. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanaelhaearn. Mae yno harbwr bychan, pier a thraeth. Llifa Afon Tal i'r môr yn y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#tregaian">
            <name>Tregaian</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tregaian">This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target article. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tregaian">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanddyfnan, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Tregaian. Mae 134.2 milltir (215.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 215.6 milltir (346.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Tregaian yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#tregele">
            <name>Tregele</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tregele">Tregele is a small village located in north Anglesey, Wales. Located about a mile south-west of the larger coastal village of Cemaes, it is also close to the Wylfa Nuclear Power Station on Wylfa Head. Despite its small size Tregele has a petrol station and a pub. One kilometre south of the village is a cromlech (ancient burial chamber) named Llanfechell Cromlech.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tregele">Pentref bychan ar Ynys Môn yw Tregele. Gorwedd yng ngogledd yr ynys ar lôn yr A5025, tua thri chwarter milltir i'r de-orllewin o bentref Cemaes.
Ceir lôn yn rhedeg i lawr i Fae Cemlyn ar yr arfordir i'r gogledd-orllewin. Hanner milltir i'r de o'r pentref ceir cromlech ar Foel Fawr, ar y ffordd i Llanfechell.
Mae atomfa'r Wylfa yn gorwedd cwta hanner milltir i'r gogledd o'r pentref, gyda gwarchodfa natur Cemlyn gerllaw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#tryfil">
            <name>Tryfil</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tryfil">Tryfil is a hamlet in the community of Bodffordd, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 135.9 miles (218.7km) from Cardiff and 218.3 miles (351.3km) from London.
^ Google Maps (Map). Google.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tryfil">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Bodffordd, Ynys Môn, Cymru yw Tryfil. Mae 135.9 milltir (218.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.3 milltir (351.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Tryfil yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Rhun ap Iorwerth (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Albert Owen (Y Blaid Lafur).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#twr">
            <name>Twr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#ty croes">
            <name>Ty Croes</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ty Croes">This is a redirect from a page name that does not have diacritical marks (accents, umlauts, etc.) to essentially the same page name with diacritical marks. For more information follow the category link.
Apply this redirect (without piping) when the subject page concerns language translation or foreign language equivalents. Other pages that use this redirect should be updated with a direct link to the redirect target (again, without piping).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#tyddyn dai">
            <name>Tyddyn Dai</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyddyn Dai">Tyddyn Dai is a hamlet in the community of Amlwch, Ynys Môn, Wales, which is 141.4 miles (227.6km) from Cardiff and 220.7 miles (355.1km) from London.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#tynygongl">
            <name>Tynygongl</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tynygongl">This is a redirect from a title with a different spelling. Pages that link to this redirect may be updated to link directly to the target page. It is not necessary to replace these redirected links with piped links. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="anglesey/sir fon#valley (dyffryn)">
            <name>Valley (Dyffryn)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
    </towns>
</county>