<?xml version="1.0"?>
<county id="Glamorgan">
    <postcodes>
        <postcode>CF32</postcode>
        <postcode>CF35</postcode>
        <postcode>CF5</postcode>
        <postcode>CF61</postcode>
        <postcode>CF62</postcode>
        <postcode>CF63</postcode>
        <postcode>CF64</postcode>
        <postcode>CF71</postcode>
    </postcodes>
    <towns>
        <town id="glamorgan#abergarw">
            <name>Abergarw</name>
            <lat>51.5509371</lat>
            <lon>-3.5746963</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergarw">Pentref ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yw Abergarw. Saif wrth gymer Afon Garw ac Afon Ogwr yn y Cymoedd tua 4 milltir i'r gogledd o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ei hun, a rhwng pentrefi Brynmenyn a Bryncethin.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#aberkenfig">
            <name>Aberkenfig</name>
            <lat>51.540786</lat>
            <lon>-3.597806</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberkenfig">Aberkenfig (Welsh: Abercynffig, meaning "mouth of the Kenfig (stream)) is a village of around 2,000 people located in the County Borough of Bridgend, Wales to the north of Bridgend town.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#aberthin">
            <name>Aberthin</name>
            <lat>51.4672657</lat>
            <lon>-3.4273121</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberthin">Aberthin is a small village, just outside Cowbridge in the Vale of Glamorgan, South Wales, on the north side of a shallow valley, less than a mile northeast of Cowbridge across the A48 road. Cowbridge Comprehensive School lies just to the southwest of the village. About 250 metres to the south is an old quarry, with a "faulted strip of grey oolite". Aberthin is also the name of a brook, the River Aberthin. The village was served by the Aberthin Platform railway station between 1905 and 1920, now a field to the west of Aberthin.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberthin">Pentref bychan ym Mro Morgannwg, de Cymru, sy'n gorwedd tua milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o'r Bont-faen yw Aberthin. Mae'n gorwedd ar yr A4222 rhwng y Bont-faen a Llantrisant ac mae'n rhan o blwyf Llanfleiddan.
Ymddengys fod yr enw yn dod o enw'r ffrwd Nant y Berthin sy'n rhedeg heibio i'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#barri (barry)">
            <name>Barri (Barry)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#barry (barri)">
            <name>Barry (Barri)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#barry dock">
            <name>Barry Dock</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#barry island">
            <name>Barry Island</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barry Island">Barry Island (Welsh: Ynys y Barri) is a district, peninsula and seaside resort, forming part of the town of Barry in the Vale of Glamorgan, South Wales. It is named after the 6th century Saint Baruc. Barry's stretch of coast, on the Bristol Channel, has the world's second highest tidal range of 15 metres (49 ft), second only to Bay of Fundy in Eastern Canada.

The peninsula was an island until the 1880s when it was linked to the mainland as the town of Barry expanded. This was partly due to the opening of Barry Docks by the Barry Railway Company. Established by David Davies, the docks now link up the gap which used to form Barry Island.
Although Barry Island used to be home to a Butlins Holiday Camp, it is now known more for its beach and Barry Island Pleasure Park.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#beggars pound">
            <name>Beggars Pound</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#betws">
            <name>Betws</name>
            <lat>51.788921</lat>
            <lon>-3.983382</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betws">Am enghreifftiau eraill o enwau lleol sy'n cynnwys y gair Betws, gweler Betws (gwahaniaethu).
Pentref bychan a chymuned yn Sir Gaerfyrddin yw'r Betws.
↑ Defnyddir sillafiad safonol Cymdeithas Enwau Lleoedd Cymru a Gwyddoniadur Cymru; Gwasg Prifysgol Cymru; cyhoeddwyd 2008; tud 75</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#blackmill">
            <name>Blackmill</name>
            <lat>51.569768</lat>
            <lon>-3.539452</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackmill">Blackmill is a small village within Bridgend County Borough Council, in south Wales. It is located at the confluence of the Ogwr Fach and Ogmore rivers, around 8 km north-east of Bridgend town and 5 km west of Gilfach Goch.
It is sited within the community (parish) of Ogmore Valley. The ward population taken at the 2011 census was 2,493.
The settlement was the site of a Wesleyan Methodist chapel which was built in 1885, although as of 2005 the building was no longer in use as a church and was due to be converted to housing. In 1915 a new church (All Saints) was opened in the community.
^ "Blackmill: Bridgend". Explore Britain. Retrieved 19 July 2012. 
^ "Ward population 2011". Retrieved 10 April 2015. 
^ Gareth Hicks (10 July 2008). "Llandyfodwg: Chapels database". genuki.org.uk. Retrieved 29 July 2010. 
^ "Timeline:Before 1920...". Ogmore Valley Local History &amp; Heritage Society. Retrieved 17 December 2010.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#blaencaerau">
            <name>Blaencaerau</name>
            <lat>51.6389062</lat>
            <lon>-3.6460999</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#blaengarw">
            <name>Blaengarw</name>
            <lat>51.624105</lat>
            <lon>-3.587432</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaengarw">Blaengarw is the uppermost village in the river valley (Cwm Garw) of the River Garw, in the county borough of Bridgend, Wales.
In the English language Blaengarw means the rugged 'front' or head of the valley. The population of Blaengarw according to the 2001 census was 1,895, reducing to 1,789 at the 2011 census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaengarw">Blaengarw yw'r pentref uchaf yng Nghwm Garw, yng ngogledd bwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr. Fe'i lleolir ym mhen uchaf Cwm Garw, ar ôl Pont-y-cymer, tua deg milltir i'r gogledd o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr.
Saif Mynydd Llangeinwyr i'r dwyrain o'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bonvilston">
            <name>Bonvilston</name>
            <lat>51.4576903</lat>
            <lon>-3.344802</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonvilston">Bonvilston (Welsh: Tresimwn) is a village in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. The village is situated on the A48 about four miles east of Cowbridge and near the Welsh capital city of Cardiff.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#boverton">
            <name>Boverton</name>
            <lat>51.407749</lat>
            <lon>-3.466309</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boverton">Boverton (Welsh: Trebefered) is a village located to the east of Llantwit Major in the Vale of Glamorgan in South Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#boys village">
            <name>Boys Village</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boys Village">St Athan Boys' Village was a village-style holiday camp located in West Aberthaw, Vale of Glamorgan, Wales.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#brackla (bragle)">
            <name>Brackla (Bragle)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bragle (brackla)">
            <name>Bragle (Brackla)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#breaksea point">
            <name>Breaksea Point</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breaksea Point">Breaksea Point is the southernmost point of mainland Wales, at the edge of Gileston's Limpert Bay. The island of Flat Holm, part of Cardiff, is about 1 km further south).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bridgend (pen-y-bont ar ogwr)">
            <name>Bridgend (Pen-y-bont Ar Ogwr)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#broughton">
            <name>Broughton</name>
            <lat>53.163494</lat>
            <lon>-2.997219</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broughton">Broughton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bryncethin">
            <name>Bryncethin</name>
            <lat>51.5477892</lat>
            <lon>-3.564131</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncethin">Bryncethin (which means dark hill or dun hill) is a small village in the County Borough of Bridgend, South Wales, located just north of Junction 36 of the M4 Motorway and approximately 3 miles north of the county town of Bridgend. The population of the ward taken from the United Kingdom Census 2011 was 1,319. The area was mainly farmland until its ample quantities of high quality clay and workable seams of steam coal led to the construction of a brickworks and the sinking of the Bryncethin Colliery by The Barrow-in Furness Iron and Coal Company. This led to an increase in the population of the village and to the construction of housing for the workforce. Both industries are now long gone and much effort is being made to provide recreational facilities on the site of the former colliery and clay pits. Bryncethin is surrounded by the villages of Aberkenfig, Brynmenyn, Sarn, Tondu, Ynysawdre, and Abergarw, the last of which stands at the confluence of the River Garw (Afon Garw) with the larger River Ogmore (Ogmore River).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncethin">Pentref bach ym mwrdeisdref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, i'r gogledd o draffordd yr M4 ar cyffordd 36, yw Bryncethin. Mae'n gorwedd rhwng pentrefi Sarn, Abercynffig, Abergarw, Tondu ac Ynysawdre.
Mae Ysgol Gynradd Bryncethin yno ac mae Ysgol Gyfun ger llaw.
Mae Bryncethin yn tyfu'n gyflym, ond mae dan fygythiad, gyda'r pentrefi cyfagos, o ddod yn ran o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ei hun. Ceir un o lochesi 'Cats Protection' ym Mryncethin.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bryncoch">
            <name>Bryncoch</name>
            <lat>51.6831569</lat>
            <lon>-3.8175666</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncoch">Bryncoch is a suburb of the town of Neath in Neath Port Talbot County Borough, Wales. The name derives from the Welsh 'red hill' (bryn coch), originally the name of a nearby farm.
Bryncoch is divided into two wards: Bryncoch North and Bryncoch South. The area is one of the most affluent parts of the county borough, with 29% and 35% of households in the Bryncoch North and Bryncoch South respectively earning more than £40,000 per year.
Historically the village of Bryncoch was centred on Main Road and a few adjacent streets, but the village expanded considerably in the 1960s with the building of the Furzeland Drive and Elias Drive developments. This area makes up the council ward of Bryncoch North, which has only one small street of social housing at Heol Pant Glas, named after a nearby farm located at the furthest northern corner of the ward. The council ward of Bryncoch South includes the distinct areas of the Rhyddings, Gilfach, Penywern, Leiros Parc, and the large social housing estate of Caewern.
There are two village primary schools: Blaenhonddan and the Bryncoch Church in Wales school. There is also a special school, Ysgol Hendre. The nearest secondary school is Dwr Y Felin Comprehensive. Many village children also attend the Welsh-language secondary Ysgol Gyfun at Ystalyfera and the Welsh-language primary school Ysgol Gymraeg Castell Nedd.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncoch">Pentref sy'n awr yn rhan o dref Castell-nedd ym mwrdeisdref sirol Castell-nedd Port Talbot yw Bryncoch.
Ar un adeg, yma yr oedd pencadlys y Main Colliery Company, oedd yn gyflogwr pwysig yn yr ardal hyd 1928. Roedd y cymwynaswr Howel Gwyn AS, a adeiladodd Neuadd Gwyn, yn byw ym mhlasdy Dyffryn, sydd yn awr wedi ei ddymchwel. Adeiladodd eglwys Sant Matthew ar ei stad yn 1871.
Mae Bryncoch wedi cynyddu'n sylweddol wrth i stadau tai newydd gael eu hadeiladu.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#brynheulog">
            <name>Brynheulog</name>
            <lat>51.6930898</lat>
            <lon>-4.1420418</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#brynmenyn">
            <name>Brynmenyn</name>
            <lat>51.552236</lat>
            <lon>-3.575482</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynmenyn">Brynmenyn is a small village located at the confluence of the Garw and Ogmore rivers in south Wales, around 4 miles north of Bridgend, and it also in the Bridgend County Borough council area. The village has its own primary school.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynmenyn">Pentref ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yw Brynmenyn. Saif wrth gymer Afon Garw ac Afon Ogwr yn y Cymoedd tua 4 milltir i'r gogledd o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ei hun.
Rhed ffordd yr A4065 trwy'r pentref; i'r gorllewin mae'n arwain i gyfeiriad Tondu, ac i'r dwyrain i gyfeiriad Abergarw a Bryncethin. Mae'r A4064 yn cychwyn o'r pentref ac yn dringo dros y mynydd i Llangeinor.
Ceir Ysgol Gynradd Brymenyn i wasanaeth'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#brynnau gwynion">
            <name>Brynnau Gwynion</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#bryntirion">
            <name>Bryntirion</name>
            <lat>51.5938311</lat>
            <lon>-3.1967189</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryntirion">Bryntirion is a heritage-listed detached house at 287 Wickham Terrace, Spring Hill, City of Brisbane, Queensland, Australia. It was designed by James Furnival for Edward Barton Southerden and built in 1861 with subsequent extensions. It was added to the Queensland Heritage Register on 17 December 1993.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#burdonshill">
            <name>Burdonshill</name>
            <lat>51.4402052</lat>
            <lon>-3.2691673</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#burton">
            <name>Burton</name>
            <lat>51.710955</lat>
            <lon>-4.919328</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton">Burton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton">Gall Burton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#byeastwood">
            <name>Byeastwood</name>
            <lat>51.524743</lat>
            <lon>-3.545063</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cadoxton">
            <name>Cadoxton</name>
            <lat>51.673094</lat>
            <lon>-3.799281</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadoxton">Cadoxton may refer to:
Cadoxton-juxta-Neath, Wales
Cadoxton, Vale of Glamorgan, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadoxton">Mae Cadoxton yn enw Saesneg ar ddau bentref yng Nghymru:
Llangatwg, Castell-nedd Port Talbot
Tregatwg, Bro Morgannwg</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#caerau">
            <name>Caerau</name>
            <lat>51.638377</lat>
            <lon>-3.653423</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerau">Caerau may refer to:
Caerau, Bridgend, near Maesteg in the River Llynfi valley, south Wales
Caerau, Cardiff, a district of the city of Cardiff, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerau">Gallai Caerau gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#caermead">
            <name>Caermead</name>
            <lat>51.6198593</lat>
            <lon>-3.9423498</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#caerphilly">
            <name>Caerphilly</name>
            <lat>51.578829</lat>
            <lon>-3.218134</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerphilly">Caerphilly (/kɛərˈfɪli/; Welsh: Caerffili, Welsh pronunciation: [ˌkɑːɨrˈfɪlɪ]) is a town in the county borough of Caerphilly, South Wales, located at the southern end of the Rhymney Valley. At the time of the 2001 Census the town had a population of 30,388. It is a commuter town of Cardiff and Newport, which are located some 7.5 miles (12 km) and 12 miles (19 km) away, respectively. It is separated from the Cardiff suburbs of Lisvane and Rhiwbina by Caerphilly mountain. It is traditionally within the county of Glamorgan, on the border with Monmouthshire and it is the largest town in the county borough of Caerphilly, which since 2003 has formed part of the lieutenancy area of Gwent. The town gives its name to Caerphilly cheese, which originated in the area.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#capel llanilterne">
            <name>Capel Llanilterne</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cardiff">
            <name>Cardiff</name>
            <lat>51.481581</lat>
            <lon>-3.17909</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardiff">Cardiff (/ˈkɑrdɪf/; Welsh: Caerdydd  [kairˈdiːð, kaˑɨrˈdɨːð]) is the capital and largest city in Wales and the tenth largest city in the United Kingdom. The city is the country's chief commercial centre, the base for most national cultural and sporting institutions, the Welsh national media, and the seat of the National Assembly for Wales. The unitary authority area's mid-2011 population was estimated to be 346,100, while the population of the Larger Urban Zone was estimated at 861,400 in 2009. Cardiff is part of the Cardiff and south Wales valleys metropolitan area of about 1,100,000 people. Cardiff is a significant tourist centre and the most popular visitor destination in Wales with 18.3 million visitors in 2010. In 2011, Cardiff was ranked sixth in the world in National Geographic's alternative tourist destinations.
The city of Cardiff is the county town of the historic county of Glamorgan (and later South Glamorgan). Cardiff is part of the Eurocities network of the largest European cities. The Cardiff Urban Area covers a slightly larger area outside the county boundary, and includes the towns of Dinas Powys and Penarth. A small town until the early 19th century, its prominence as a major port for the transport of coal following the arrival of industry in the region contributed to its rise as a major city.
Cardiff was made a city in 1905, and proclaimed the capital of Wales in 1955. Since the 1990s, Cardiff has seen significant development. A new waterfront area at Cardiff Bay contains the Senedd building, home to the Welsh Assembly and the Wales Millennium Centre arts complex. Current developments include the continuation of the redevelopment of the Cardiff Bay and city centre areas with projects such as the Cardiff International Sports Village, a BBC drama village, and a new business district in the city centre.
Sporting venues in the city include the Millennium Stadium (the national stadium for the Wales national rugby union team), SWALEC Stadium (the home of Glamorgan County Cricket Club), Cardiff City Stadium (the home of Cardiff City football team), Cardiff International Sports Stadium (the home of Cardiff Amateur Athletic Club) and Cardiff Arms Park (the home of Cardiff Blues and Cardiff RFC rugby union teams). The city was awarded with the European City of Sport in 2009 due to its role in hosting major international sporting events. Again Cardiff was the European City of Sport in 2014. The Millennium Stadium hosted 11 football matches as part of the 2012 Summer Olympics, including the games' opening event and the men's bronze medal match.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardiff">Cardiff yw'r ffurf Saesneg ar enw Caerdydd, prifddinas Cymru. Gall hefyd gyfeirio at:
Cardiff (Alabama), tref yn Alabama
Cardiff (Efrog Newydd), dinas yn Efrog Newydd
Cardiff-by-the-Sea, cymuned a dinas yn Encinitas, Califfornia
Cardiff (De Cymru Newydd), bwrdeistref yn Lake Macquarie, Awstralia
Cardiff (Ontario), yng Nghanada
Cardiff, Pennsylvania, pentref ym Maryland</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#castle-upon-alun">
            <name>Castle-upon-Alun</name>
            <lat>51.4608167</lat>
            <lon>-3.565725</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cefn cribwr">
            <name>Cefn Cribwr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cefn Cribwr">Cefn Cribwr is a village and community in Bridgend County Borough in south Wales. The village is located about 5 miles (8 km) from the centre of Bridgend town. Cefn Cribwr, as a community, recorded a population of 1,546 in the 2001 Census, reducing to 1,481 at the 2011 Census.
The community centre (opened 1924), locally known as the 'Green Hall' was originally conceived as a Miners' Welfare Hall and was supported by colliery owners and colliers. Many political meetings were held there. Labour politician and former Prime Minister Ramsay Macdonald spoke there in the closing weeks of the General Strike of 1926. The Wesley Dramatic Society entertained, as did the members of Siloam Chapel who performed many dramas and concerts. The community centre today, is mainly used as the venue for the meetings of Cefn Cribwr Labour Party.
Bedford Park, found in Cefn Cribwr is now an area of 40 acres (160,000 m2) of ancient woodland and meadows, glades and open spaces. It was once an area of intense industrial activity following the building of a blast furnace here in 1780 by the Birmingham Industrialist John Bedford. He also sank pits to mine the raw materials of ironstone and coal as well as founding a forge and brickworks. The ironworks were never as successful as Bedford had hoped and began to decline after his death in 1791. Coal mining and brick making, however, continued throughout the 19th Century and industrial activity at Bedford Park ceased after World War I.
Cefn Cribwr Ironworks in Bedford Park is now protected as a Scheduled Ancient Monument and is one of the most complete of its kind in Britain. Many parts of the ironworks and related buildings can still be seen.
The community has several public footpaths and cycling routes which pass through the park following the line of the old Dyffryn, Llynfi and Porthcawl railway which linked the ironworks to the coast.
^ National Statistics, Census 2001
^ "Ward population 2011". Retrieved 11 April 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cefn Cribwr">Pentref ym mwrdesitref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yw Cefn Cribwr. Lleolir tua 5 milltir o ganol tref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr. Roedd poblogaeth o 1546 yn y pentref yn ystod cyfrifiad 2001.
Lleolir Ysgol Gynradd Cefn Cribwr yn y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cefn cross">
            <name>Cefn Cross</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cefn glas">
            <name>Cefn Glas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cefn Glas">Cefn Glas is an area of the town of Bridgend, Wales.
In the 2001 Census, Cefn Glas had a population of 1,742 people, making up 1.35% of Bridgend's total population. This population reduced to 1,437 at the 2011 Census.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#city">
            <name>City</name>
            <lat>51.49542</lat>
            <lon>-3.455298</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City">A city is a large and permanent human settlement. Although there is no agreement on how a city is distinguished from a town in general English language meanings, many cities have a particular administrative, legal, or historical status based on local law.
Cities generally have complex systems for sanitation, utilities, land usage, housing, and transportation. The concentration of development greatly facilitates interaction between people and businesses, benefiting both parties in the process, but it also presents challenges to managing urban growth. A big city or metropolis usually has associated suburbs and exurbs. Such cities are usually associated with metropolitan areas and urban areas, creating numerous business commuters traveling to urban centers for employment. Once a city expands far enough to reach another city, this region can be deemed a conurbation or megalopolis. In terms of population, the largest city proper is Shanghai, while the fastest growing is Dubai.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/City">Gweler hefyd Dinas (gwahaniaethu).
Pentref bychan tua 3 milltir i'r gogledd o'r Bont-faen ym Mro Morgannwg, de Cymru, yw City (ni cheir ffurf Gymraeg ar yr enw).
Mae tarddiad ac ystyr yr enw lle "City" yn ansicr. Yn amlwg nid yw'n air Cymraeg yn y ffurf honno ond fe allai fod yn ffurf Seisnig ar enw Cymraeg sydd bellach yn anhysbys. Yn ôl rhai trigolion lleol mae'n llygriad o "Saith tŷ" ond ymddengys hynny'n anhebygol. Ond ceir yr hen air Cymraeg cyty, sy'n golygu "cydbreswylio, cymdeithas dan yr un to; tŷ a rennir ag eraill; tŷ dan yr unto," ac mae'n bosibl mai dyna a geir yn yr enw 'City'. Boed hynny fel y bo, ni cheir enw Cymraeg cydnabyddedig ar y pentref.
Does dim siopau yn City heddiw. Bu yno dafarn y City Inn ond mae wedi cau rwan. Ceir neuadd pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#clawdd-coch">
            <name>Clawdd-coch</name>
            <lat>51.490112</lat>
            <lon>-3.361859</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cog">
            <name>Cog</name>
            <lat>51.4105935</lat>
            <lon>-3.2143371</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cog">A cog is a tooth of a gear or cogwheel or the gear or cogwheel itself.
A cog engages with another cog and motion in one will result in motion of the other. Gearwheels that engage with chains are sprockets, not cogs.
Cog, COG, or CoG may also refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cog">Aderyn sy'n aelod o deulu'r Cuculiformes yw'r gog (lluosog: cogau) neu'r gwcw (lluosog: cwcwod) (Cuculus canorus).
Mae'r gog yn nythu ar draws rhannau helaeth o Ewrop ac Asia, ac yn gaeafu yn Affrica. Un o nodweddion enwocaf yr aderyn yw ei fod yn dodwy ei wyau yn nyth rhywogaeth arall o aderyn, yn arbennig Llwyd y Gwrych, Corhedydd y Waun a Telor y Cyrs. Enw arall ar Gorhedydd y Waun yw "Gwas y Gog". Gall cyw'r gog daflu'r cywion eraill o'r nyth, i sicrhau ei fod ef yn cael yr holl fwyd.
Mae'n aderyn cymharol fawr, llwyd o ran lliw, a gall edrych yn debyg iawn i aderyn ysglyfaethus o gael cipolwg arno'n hedfan. Daw'r enw "cwcw" o alwad yr aderyn.
Er fod y gog yn parhau yn aderyn cymharol gyffredin yng Nghymru, mae ei niferoedd wedi gostwng dros yr ugain mlynedd diwethaf. Mae'n cyrraedd o Affrica tua chanol Ebrill fel rheol, ac mae clywed y gog yn cael ei ystyried yn arwydd o wanwyn. Caiff Clychau'r Gog eu henw oherwydd eu bod yn blodeuo yn yr un cyfnod.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cogan">
            <name>Cogan</name>
            <lat>51.444097</lat>
            <lon>-3.185902</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cogan">Cogan is a surname. Notable people with the surname include:
Alma Cogan, English singer
Andrew Cogan
Barry Cogan (footballer)
Barry Cogan (politician)
Brian Cogan
Dean Cogan, Irish priest and writer
Fanny Cogan
Frank Cogan
Henri Cogan, wrestler, stuntman, fight choreographer, actor
Kevin Cogan, Formula 1 driver
Maggie Cogan
Patrick Cogan
Philip Cogan (1750–1833), Irish composer
Pierre Cogan (1914–2013), French cyclist
Robert Cogan
Sara Cogan
Thomas Cogan (1736–1818), English physician and writer
Tony Cogan
William Cogan</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#coity">
            <name>Coity</name>
            <lat>51.521313</lat>
            <lon>-3.552574</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coity">Coity is a village in Bridgend County Borough, south Wales. Coity is part of the community of Coity Higher and is notable for being home to Coity Castle, one of the best preserved castles in Glamorgan. Other buildings of note in the village include St Mary, a 14th-century church, and Ty Mawr, a fine 16th-century house.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#colcot">
            <name>Colcot</name>
            <lat>51.41772</lat>
            <lon>-3.2861837</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colcot">Colcot is a northern district of Barry, Vale of Glamorgan, in the Dyfan ward of South Wales. Dyfan ward is situated in the north west of Barry and its most northern edge is on the green belt of the town. You can also find the Welsh Hawking Center on the edge of the ward on Weycock Road, better known as the 'five mile lane'. Port Road West runs through the ward and is the main route to Cardiff and Cardiff International Airport in Rhoose. Dyfan benefits from a sports center and Buttrills recreation field and The Barry Hospital can be found on Colcot Road. It also contains the Colcot Primary School, the Colcot Arms pub, the St David's Methodist Church, a fish and chip shop/Chinese takeaway, Barry Arts Centre and Merthyr Dyfan Cemetery.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#colwinston">
            <name>Colwinston</name>
            <lat>51.4692</lat>
            <lon>-3.526462</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colwinston">Colwinston (Welsh: Tregolwyn) is a village in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. By road the village is located 3.9 miles southeast of the centre of Bridgend and 20.5 miles west of the centre of Cardiff. The population of the village in 2005 was approximately 400. The novelist Agatha Christie was a frequent visitor to the village, where her descendants still live, at the former manor house of Pwllywrach.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#corntown">
            <name>Corntown</name>
            <lat>51.485027</lat>
            <lon>-3.556791</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corntown">Corntown (Welsh: Corntwn) is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan. It lies along the B4524 road, just outside Bridgend, 21.6 miles west of the centre of Cardiff. It has grown around Corntown Farm. It is home to The Stingers manager Harry Lee. Chapel Wood frames part of its western side. The Golden Mile Inn lies along the B4524 just to the northeast of the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cosmeston">
            <name>Cosmeston</name>
            <lat>51.4211209</lat>
            <lon>-3.1789527</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmeston">Ardal yn ardal Larnog gerllaw Penarth ym Mro Morgannwg yw Cosmeston. Mae'n cynnwys Parc Gwledig Llynnoedd Cosmeston a Pentref Canoloesol Cosmeston</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#court colman">
            <name>Court Colman</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cowbridge (y bont-faen)">
            <name>Cowbridge (Y Bont-Faen)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#coychurch">
            <name>Coychurch</name>
            <lat>51.505944</lat>
            <lon>-3.530772</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coychurch">Coychurch (Welsh: Llangrallo) is a small village that sits between Pencoed and Bridgend in Wales, bordering with Bridgend Industrial Estate.
It has a longstanding religious association, with an early Christian church having been built there possibly as long ago as the 8th century CE. The current church of St. Crallo was built in the 13th century.
According to a local legend, after his death in battle near Ogmore Castle, King Arthur was interred in a cave in Coed-y-Mwstwr Forest, just behind the village of Coychurch, secretly for fear that the news of his death might split the nation. When his son came of age to replace him at the throne, Arthur's death was announced, and his body moved to a grave at Cor Emrys church close to Pencoed.
The crematorium, built in 1970, was the last design of modernist architect Maxwell Fry.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#coytrahen">
            <name>Coytrahen</name>
            <lat>51.558812</lat>
            <lon>-3.601159</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#croeserw">
            <name>Croeserw</name>
            <lat>51.647155</lat>
            <lon>-3.638768</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croeserw">Croeserw is a village of approximately 1,380 inhabitants in Neath Port Talbot County Borough.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#crosstown">
            <name>Crosstown</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crosstown">Crosstown may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cwmfelin">
            <name>Cwmfelin</name>
            <lat>51.69855</lat>
            <lon>-3.310787</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwmfelin">Cwmfelin is a village out the southern outskirts of Maesteg, in the county borough of Bridgend, Wales. It was once part of the medieval commote of Tir Iarll, before becoming a part of the parish of Llangynwyd. Since 1974 it has been part of the community of Llangynwyd Middle.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#cymdda">
            <name>Cymdda</name>
            <lat>51.5358963</lat>
            <lon>-3.5827361</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#degar">
            <name>Degar</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degar">The Degar, also known as the Montagnard, are the indigenous peoples of the Central Highlands of Vietnam. The term Montagnard means "mountain people" in French and is a carryover from the French colonial period in Vietnam. In Vietnamese, they are known by the term người Thượng (Highlanders)—this term now can also be applied to other minority ethnic groups in Vietnam or Người dân tộc thiểu số (literally, "minority people"). Earlier they were referred to pejoratively as the mọi.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#derwen">
            <name>Derwen</name>
            <lat>53.046146</lat>
            <lon>-3.382486</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derwen">Derwen is a rural village in the south of Denbighshire, Wales. It lies approximately half way between Corwen and Ruthin, in the upper part of Dyffryn Clwyd ond the north side of the River Clwyd, opposite the village of Brynsaithmarchog. The population of the community as taken at the 2011 census was 426.
An old Celtic Cross stands in the village, near the church, dating from the early middle ages.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derwen">Erthygl am y goeden yw hon. Ceir erthygl arall am y pentref yma.
Coed a llwyni sy'n perthyn i'r genws Quercus yw derw. Maen nhw'n cynhyrchu ffrwyth a elwir yn fes. Ceir dwy rywogaeth frodorol yng Nghymru: Derwen goesog (Quercus robur) a Derwen ddigoes (Quercus petraea).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#dimlands">
            <name>Dimlands</name>
            <lat>51.4087155</lat>
            <lon>-3.490556</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimlands">Dimlands (also known as Dimland Castle or Dimland Lodge) is a small scale, gentry house on the north side of St Donats Road about 6 miles (9.7 km) southwest of Cowbridge in the Vale of Glamorgan, southeast Wales. Built like a small Tudor castle, it is situated about 1 kilometre (0.62 mi) back from the clifftops of the Bristol Channel between Llantwit Major and St Donats. It became a Grade II listed building on 9 October 1982.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#dinas powis">
            <name>Dinas Powis</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#downs">
            <name>Downs</name>
            <lat>51.464418</lat>
            <lon>-3.287143</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Downs">Downs or The Downs may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#drope">
            <name>Drope</name>
            <lat>51.4746695</lat>
            <lon>-3.2844826</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drope">Drope is a hamlet in the valley of the River Ely in Vale of Glamorgan, southeast Wales, just beyond the territorial border of western Cardiff. It lies immediately east from Michaelston-super-Ely, west of Ely, Cardiff and southeast of St Georges-super Ely and is accessed via a bridge along Drope Road across the A4232 road to the north of Culverhouse Cross. Drope was designated a special conservation area in March 1973 by the former Glamorgan County Council due to its architectural heritage.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#dyffryn">
            <name>Dyffryn</name>
            <lat>51.439704</lat>
            <lon>-3.304778</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn">Dyffryn or Duffryn may refer to one of these places in Wales:
Duffryn housing estate in Newport
Dyffryn, Bridgend
Dyffryn Cennen, Carmarthenshire
Dyffryn, Ceredigion
Dyffryn Cellwen, Neath Port Talbot
Dyffryn Clydach, Neath Port Talbot
Dyffryn, Pembrokeshire
Dyffryn, Vale of Glamorgan
Dyffryn Gardens</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn">Am y pentref yn Ynys Môn, gweler Y Fali; am yr ystad yng Nghasnewydd gweler Dyffryn, Casnewydd: gweler hefyd Cwm.

Tirffurf yw dyffryn, sef ardal o dir sydd yn is na thir cyfagos, ac yn amrywio o ran arwynebedd o ychydig filltiroedd sgwâr i gannoedd o filltiroedd sgwâr. Mae'n arferol, er nad yn angenrheidiol, i ddyffryn gynnwys afon yn llifo trwyddo, a'r afon yn rhoi enw i'r dyffryn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#east aberthaw">
            <name>East Aberthaw</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#east village">
            <name>East Village</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East Village">East Village is the name given to neighborhoods in a number of cities, and has other uses:

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#eastbrook">
            <name>Eastbrook</name>
            <lat>51.439188</lat>
            <lon>-3.205342</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastbrook">Eastbrook could refer to the following:
Eastbrook, Dagenham, public house in London
Eastbrook, Maine, a town in Hancock County, Maine, USA
Eastbrook High School, a public high school in Marion, Indiana, USA
Eastbrook railway station, a 2 platform train station located in Dinas Powys, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#eglwys-brewis">
            <name>Eglwys-Brewis</name>
            <lat>51.4108896</lat>
            <lon>-3.4502753</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ely">
            <name>Ely</name>
            <lat>51.483308</lat>
            <lon>-3.238867</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ely">Ely or ELY may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ely">Dinas yn Swydd Gaergrawnt, Lloegr yw Ely, a leolir 14 milltir (23 km) i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o ddinas Caergrawnt a thua 80 milltir (129 km) o ddinas Llundain. Sefydlodd Æthelthryth (Etheldreda) abaty yn Ely yn 673 OC ac yn 1083 dechreuwyd codi eglwys gadeiriol ar y safle gan y Normaniaid a thyfodd tref ac wedyn dinas o gwmpas yr eglwys. Ailwampiwyd y Gadeirlan yn 1845 a 1870 gan y pensaer George Gilbert Scott. Mae poblogaeth y ddinas yn 20,256 (2011) sy'n ei wneud yn un o ddinasoedd lleiaf Lloegr.
Amaethyddiaeth ydy asgwrn cefn economi'r ddinas, bellach, ers i'r canlynol ddod i ben: cynaeafu'r pren helyg, magu llysywod, torri mawn a dal adar i'w gwerthu a'u bwyta.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#evanstown">
            <name>Evanstown</name>
            <lat>51.597713</lat>
            <lon>-3.47432</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ewenny">
            <name>Ewenny</name>
            <lat>51.4843509</lat>
            <lon>-3.57887</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ewenny">Ewenny (Welsh: Ewenni) is a village on the River Ewenny in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. Over the years the village has grown into the neighbouring village of Corntown to such an extent that there is no longer a clear boundary between the two. The nearest town of significant size is Bridgend, 3.1 km (1.9 mi) away.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 9 April 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ffordd-y-gyfraith">
            <name>Ffordd-y-Gyfraith</name>
            <lat>51.5502949</lat>
            <lon>-3.6317703</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#flemingston">
            <name>Flemingston</name>
            <lat>51.421362</lat>
            <lon>-3.414493</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flemingston">Flemingston (also Lanmihangel y Twyn, or Treffelemin, or Michaelston Le Mont, or Flimstone) is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan in south Wales. It is located 8.5 miles (13.7 km) northwest by road from the town centre of Barry. It contains the Church of St. Michael the Archangel, the ruins of Flemingston Court, and Flemingston Manor or Grange, all of which are listed buildings. Historically, the parish of Flemingston was a sub-manor of Aberthaw or St Athan.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#fonmon">
            <name>Fonmon</name>
            <lat>51.398473</lat>
            <lon>-3.370748</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fonmon">Fonmon is a hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan in south Wales. It lies just off the B4265 road to the northwest of Font-y-Gary and Rhoose on the western side of Cardiff Airport. The hamlet is best known for its central duck pond and Fonmon Castle, a historical house located on the otherside of the B4265 road to the north. The largest house in the hamlet is called The Gables, accessed off a drive on the left approaching Fonmon from the north. A number of the houses in the area are thatched roofed.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#font-y-gary">
            <name>Font-y-gary</name>
            <lat>51.3911459</lat>
            <lon>-3.3636</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#fountain">
            <name>Fountain</name>
            <lat>42.054452</lat>
            <lon>-72.218821</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fountain">A fountain (from the Latin "fons" (genitive "fontis"), a source or spring) is a piece of architecture which pours water into a basin or jets it into the air to supply drinking water and/or for a decorative or dramatic effect.
Fountains were originally purely functional, connected to springs or aqueducts and used to provide drinking water and water for bathing and washing to the residents of cities, towns and villages. Until the late 19th century most fountains operated by gravity, and needed a source of water higher than the fountain, such as a reservoir or aqueduct, to make the water flow or jet into the air.
In addition to providing drinking water, fountains were used for decoration and to celebrate their builders. Roman fountains were decorated with bronze or stone masks of animals or heroes. In the Middle Ages, Moorish and Muslim garden designers used fountains to create miniature versions of the gardens of paradise. King Louis XIV of France used fountains in the Gardens of Versailles to illustrate his power over nature. The baroque decorative fountains of Rome in the 17th and 18th centuries marked the arrival point of restored Roman aqueducts and glorified the Popes who built them.
By the end of the 19th century, as indoor plumbing became the main source of drinking water, urban fountains became purely decorative. Mechanical pumps replaced gravity and allowed fountains to recycle water and to force it high into the air. The Jet d'Eau in Lake Geneva, built in 1951, shoots water 140 metres (460 ft) in the air. The highest such fountain in the world is King Fahd's Fountain in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia, which spouts water 260 metres (850 ft) above the Red Sea.
Fountains are used today to decorate city parks and squares; to honor individuals or events; for recreation and for entertainment. A Splash pad or spray pool allows city residents to enter, get wet and cool off in summer. The musical fountain combines moving jets of water, colored lights and recorded music, controlled by a computer, for dramatic effects. Drinking fountains provide clean drinking water in public buildings, parks and public spaces.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#garth">
            <name>Garth</name>
            <lat>52.133667</lat>
            <lon>-3.536803</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth">Garth may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth">Mae Garth yn enw sawl lle yng Nghymru, ac yn elfen mewn enwau lleoedd eraill:
Garth, pentref yng Ngheredigion
Garth, pentref ym mwrdeisdref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr
Garth, pentref ym Mhowys
Garth, pentref yn sir Wrecsam
Garth (mynydd), Bannau Brycheiniog, Cyfeirnod grid OS: SO053506
Hefyd:
Gwaelod-y-Garth
Garth Celyn, enw arall ar Ben-y-bryn, Abergwyngregyn
Chwarel y Garth, SoDdGA yn Ne Powys
Garth Isaf, SoDdGA ym Mhowys
Gartheli, pentrefan yng Ngheredigion
Gall hefyd fod yn enw person:
Garth Brooks, canwr gwlad Americanaidd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#gileston">
            <name>Gileston</name>
            <lat>51.393849</lat>
            <lon>-3.411138</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gileston">Gileston (Welsh: Silstwn) is a small Welsh village near West Aberthaw in Bro Morgannwg (the Vale of Glamorgan) on the coast of South Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#glynllan">
            <name>Glynllan</name>
            <lat>51.5729308</lat>
            <lon>-3.5264104</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#glynogwr">
            <name>Glynogwr</name>
            <lat>51.574361</lat>
            <lon>-3.508221</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#graig penllyn">
            <name>Graig Penllyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#greenway">
            <name>Greenway</name>
            <lat>51.9349816</lat>
            <lon>-4.8192637</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenway">Greenway or Greenways may refer to:
Greenway (landscape)
Another term for bicycle boulevards in some jurisdictions

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#gwern-y-steeple">
            <name>Gwern-y-Steeple</name>
            <lat>51.470778</lat>
            <lon>-3.3341759</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwern-y-Steeple">Gwern-y-Steeple is a hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. It lies north of the A48 road and north-westSt. Nicholas (to which it is linked by Chapel Lane) on the road south-west of Peterston-Super-Ely. Cottrell Park Golf Club lies to the south. Gwern-y-Steeple is part of the village of Peterston-Super-Ely and lies within the catchment area of both Peterson-Super-Ely Church in Wales Primary School and Pendoylan Primary School. The local member of Parliament is Conservative Alun Cairns and is part of the Vale of Glamorgan county council. The local county councillor is Rhodri Traherne.
The village of St. Nicholas once extended as far north as Gwern-y-Steeple, with Croes-y-Parc Chapel, originally being within the St. Nicholas boundary.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#heol-laethog">
            <name>Heol-laethog</name>
            <lat>51.548061</lat>
            <lon>-3.5430252</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#heol-las">
            <name>Heol-las</name>
            <lat>51.4287436</lat>
            <lon>-3.5603776</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#heol-y-cyw">
            <name>Heol-y-Cyw</name>
            <lat>51.5474758</lat>
            <lon>-3.5224409</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heol-y-Cyw">Heol-y-Cyw is a little village in Bridgend County Borough, Wales, located near Bridgend, in the community of Coychurch Higher. The village, and its surroundings, has roughly 300 inhabitants.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#heol-y-mynydd">
            <name>Heol-y-mynydd</name>
            <lat>51.6716028</lat>
            <lon>-4.0329768</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#heronston">
            <name>Heronston</name>
            <lat>51.4914608</lat>
            <lon>-3.572139</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#hirwaun common">
            <name>Hirwaun Common</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hirwaun Common">Mae Hirwaun Common yn gopa mynydd a geir rhwng Castell-nedd a Chas-gwent; cyfeiriad grid SN942035. Uchder cymharol, neu ”amlygrwydd” y copa, ydy 477 metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
Dosberthir copaon Cymru, a gweddill gwledydd Prydain, yn rhestri arbennig yn ôl uchder ac yn ôl amlygrwydd y copa; mae'r copa hwn yn cael ei alw'n Dewey. Mae sawl cymdeithas yn mesur, gwiro a chasglu'r rhestri hyn a dônt ynghŷd ar wefan “Database of British and Irish hills”. Uchder y copa o lefel y môr ydy 515 metr (1690 tr). Cafodd yr uchder ei fesur a'i gadarnhau ar 10 Mawrth 2007.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#kenfig">
            <name>Kenfig</name>
            <lat>51.5161004</lat>
            <lon>-3.7274378</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenfig">Kenfig (Welsh: Cynffig) is a village and former borough in Bridgend, Wales. It is situated 1 mile (1.6 km) inland on the north bank of the Bristol Channel, and just south-west of the M4 motorway. To the east is the town of Bridgend, at approximately 6 miles (10 km), and the capital city of Cardiff, at 24 miles (40 km).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#kenfig hill">
            <name>Kenfig Hill</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenfig Hill">Kenfig Hill is a village in Bridgend County, South Wales. It is bordered by Pyle to the south-west, Cefn Cribwr to the north-east, North Cornelly to the south and Moel Ton-Mawr mountain to the north.
The nearest station is Pyle on the South Wales Main Line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#laleston">
            <name>Laleston</name>
            <lat>51.5061227</lat>
            <lon>-3.6216732</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laleston">Laleston is a village and a community in Bridgend County Borough, south Wales, directly west of Bridgend town centre. The village takes its name from the Norman Lageles family who settled in the area. Buildings of note in the village include St David's church which still possesses features dating back to the 13th and 14th centuries, the Great House which was built in the early 16th century and Horeb Welsh Presbyterian Church (1831).
As a community, Laleston includes the villages of Bryntirion, Cefn Glas, Tythegston and Broadlands. The boundaries of the community are almost entirely set by transportation routes, with the western and north western border defined by the M4 motorway, where it then turns south-easterly at Stormy Down following the A48 back towards Bridgend town centre. It then takes in the Greenfields area, briefly following the banks of the River Ogmore, before heading north to Cefn Glas, but skirting Bridgend town centre and Newcastle. At the 2001 census, the community's population was 8,475.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#lavernock">
            <name>Lavernock</name>
            <lat>51.4073807</lat>
            <lon>-3.1756033</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lavernock">Lavernock (Welsh: Larnog) is a hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan in Wales, lying on the coast 7 miles (11 km) south of Cardiff between Penarth and Sully, and overlooking the Bristol Channel.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#leckwith">
            <name>Leckwith</name>
            <lat>51.461668</lat>
            <lon>-3.213893</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leckwith">Leckwith (Welsh: Lecwydd) is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan, just west of Cardiff. Historically, the parish of Leckwith also included land on the east side of the river Ely that is now part of Cardiff itself. This area is also commonly known as Leckwith.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#letty brongu">
            <name>Letty Brongu</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#lewistown">
            <name>Lewistown</name>
            <lat>51.581671</lat>
            <lon>-3.541738</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewistown">Lewistown is the name of several places in the United States of America:
Lewistown, Illinois
Lewistown, Kentucky
Lewistown, Frederick County, Maryland
Lewistown, Talbot County, Maryland
Lewistown, Missouri
Lewistown, Montana
Lewistown, Ohio
Lewistown, Pennsylvania
Lewistown is also the name of a place in Wales, in the United Kingdom:
Lewistown, Bridgend</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#litchard">
            <name>Litchard</name>
            <lat>51.5257077</lat>
            <lon>-3.5776385</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llampha">
            <name>Llampha</name>
            <lat>51.469145</lat>
            <lon>-3.551745</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llampha">Llampha (Welsh: Llanffa) is a hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, South Wales, near Bridgend. It mainly consists of farms and small holdings.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llanbad">
            <name>Llanbad</name>
            <lat>52.819718</lat>
            <lon>-4.101435</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llanbethery">
            <name>Llanbethery</name>
            <lat>51.419148</lat>
            <lon>-3.384</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbethery">Llanbethery (Welsh: Llanbydderi) is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan, south Wales. It is part of the community of Llancarfan.
Llanbethery was once served by Llanbethery Platform railway station. This opened in 1905 and closed in 1920.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llanblethian">
            <name>Llanblethian</name>
            <lat>51.4548569</lat>
            <lon>-3.459228</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llancadle">
            <name>Llancadle</name>
            <lat>51.40827</lat>
            <lon>-3.384124</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llancadle">Llancadle (Welsh: Llancatal) is a rural village south-west of Barry near Rhoose in the Vale of Glamorgan, in Wales.
Llancadle is located near the international airport for Wales, Cardiff International Airport.

It has a pub named the 'Green Dragon Inn' at the Northern end of the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llancarfan">
            <name>Llancarfan</name>
            <lat>51.4242599</lat>
            <lon>-3.366597</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llancarfan">Llancarfan is a rural village and community in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. The village, located west of Barry near Cowbridge, has a pub and a well-known parish church, the site of Saint Cadoc's 6th-century clas, famed for its learning. Cainnech of Aghaboe, Caradoc of Llancarfan and many other Welsh holy men studied there. At the 2001 census, the community had a population of 736.
The spacious church, which in the later Middle Ages belonged to Gloucester Abbey, contains a stoup and interesting remains of a rood screen, now adapted as a reredos. In early 2008, architects discovered medieval wall painting in the church under layers of whitewash, including one of only three depictions of St George to be found in churches in Wales. Conservation-restoration work is currently being undertaken to reveal the full mural.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llancarfan">Pentref a phlwyf sy'n gorwedd rhwng Y Bont-faen a'r Barri ym Mro Morgannwg yw Llancarfan. Ganwyd yr hynafiaethydd a llenor Iolo Morganwg ym mhentref Pennon yn y plwyf.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llandochau (llandough)">
            <name>Llandochau (Llandough)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llandough">
            <name>Llandough</name>
            <lat>51.445696</lat>
            <lon>-3.445823</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandough">not to be confused with Llandough, Penarth or Llandow

Llandough is a village located south of Cowbridge in the Vale of Glamorgan.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llandough (llandochau)">
            <name>Llandough (Llandochau)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llandow">
            <name>Llandow</name>
            <lat>51.4491338</lat>
            <lon>-3.5221746</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandow">Llandow (Welsh: Llandŵ) is a village in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. The community population taken at the 2011 census was 726. The village is located 15 miles (24 km) south west of Cardiff.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llangan">
            <name>Llangan</name>
            <lat>51.487353</lat>
            <lon>-3.502525</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangan">Llangan may also refer to Llangain, Carmarthenshire

Llangan (Welsh: Llan-gan) is a small village and community in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. It is located approximately 4 miles (6.4 km) outside the market town of Cowbridge. As a community it contains the settlements of St Mary Hill, Treoes and Llangan itself.
Llangan became an important religious site in the late 18th century due to the work and preaching of its church's Baptist minister David Jones.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangan">Gallai Llangan gyfeirio at:
Cymru
Llangan, plwyf eglwysig am y ffin rhwng Sir Gaerfyrddin a Sir Benfro
Llangan, pentref ym Mro Morgannwg
Llydaw
Langan, Llydaw, yn ardal Roazhon.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llangeinor">
            <name>Llangeinor</name>
            <lat>51.5767993</lat>
            <lon>-3.5674561</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangeinor">Llangeinor (Welsh: Llangeinwyr) is a small village located in the Garw Valley around 5 miles north of Bridgend in Bridgend County Borough, Wales. The ward population taken at the 2011 census was 1,243. The entire village is now protected as part of a conservation area.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llangynwyd">
            <name>Llangynwyd</name>
            <lat>51.587065</lat>
            <lon>-3.651747</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangynwyd">Llangynwyd is a village 2 miles to the south of Maesteg, in the county borough of Bridgend, Wales. It was part of the medieval commote (Welsh: cwmwd) of Tir Iarll.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangynwyd">Pentref a phlwyf a leolir tua 2 filltir i'r de o Faesteg, ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, de Cymru yw Llangynwyd (a Llangynwyd Isaf). Bu'n rhan o gwmwd canoloesol Tir Iarll. Yn ôl cyfrifiad 2001, mae gan y pentref boblogaeth o 2,843.
Yn y pentref ceir eglwys plwyf Llangynwyd, a sefydlwyd gan Sant Cynwyd, yn ôl traddodiad. Gerllaw ceir adfeilion Castell Llangynwyd.
Cedwir traddodiad y Fari Lwyd o hyd yn Llangynwyd, ar 31 Rhagfyr. Un o'r ardal yma oedd y bardd Rhisiart Iorwerth a elwir hefyd yn Rhisiart Fynglwyd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llanmaes">
            <name>Llanmaes</name>
            <lat>51.418085</lat>
            <lon>-3.466906</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanmaes">Llanmaes or Llanfaes is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan near the market town of Llantwit Major.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llanmihangel">
            <name>Llanmihangel</name>
            <lat>51.438164</lat>
            <lon>-3.46702</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llansannor">
            <name>Llansannor</name>
            <lat>51.488487</lat>
            <lon>-3.448291</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llansannor">Llansannor (Welsh: Llansanwyr) is a small hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales, United Kingdom.
It has a population of roughly 200 people. It contains a parish church, a pub (the City Inn, now closed), a primary school and a village hall, which has recently been rebuilt thanks to the efforts of the parishioners.
Llansannor is traditionally a parish, until the last century comprising little more than a collection of farms spread out across Llansannor Hill (Mynydd y Fforest) and now incorporating the present hamlet of City and a collection of houses built in the grounds of Llansannor Court between the 1970s and 90's. Present day farms in the parish include Church Farm, Gelli Goll Farm and Windmill Farm. While agriculture remains important to the character of the area, many residents of the village are retirees or commute to work in nearby Cardiff.
The Valeways Millennium Heritage Trail passes through the parish, and the source of the River Thaw is nearby.
Famous residents include JPR Williams, former Welsh rugby fullback.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llantrithyd">
            <name>Llantrithyd</name>
            <lat>51.447792</lat>
            <lon>-3.375601</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llantwit major">
            <name>Llantwit Major</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llantwit Major">Llantwit Major (Welsh: Llanilltud Fawr) is a small coastal town and community in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales, lying on the Bristol Channel coast. It is one of four towns in the Vale of Glamorgan and the third largest by population (13,366 (2001)) after Barry and Penarth, and ahead of Cowbridge, which lies about 4.5 miles (7.2 km) to the northeast. The town centre of Llantwit Major lies about 9 miles (14 km) southeast of the centre of Bridgend, 10 miles (16 km) west of the centre of Barry, and about 15 miles (24 km) miles south-west of the centre of the Welsh capital of Cardiff which lies further to the east beyond Barry.
The town's name in Welsh, Llanilltud Fawr, is derived from the name of Saint Illtud, who came to the area from Brittany, Gaul. He founded the monastery of Illtud and the college attached to it, Cor Tewdws, which would grow into one of the most esteemed Christian colleges of the times. At peak it attracted over 2000 students, including princes and numerous eminent clergymen, some now revered as saints. Destroyed by the Vikings in 987, the monastery was rebuilt in 1111 and continued to be a centre of learning governed by Tewkesbury Abbey until it closed in 1539 during the Dissolution of the Monasteries. The 13th-century St Illtyd's Church, built near the ancient monastery, today is a Grade I listed building and one of the oldest parish churches in Wales.
The modern town of Llantwit developed rapidly in the 20th century to accommodate Royal Air Force personnel from the base built at nearby St Athan, but it retains its medieval cobbled streets and buildings of the 15th and 16th centuries. Llantwit Major railway station on the Vale of Glamorgan Line was reopened in June 2005. Collugh Beach is a popular surfing venue and has the remnants of an Iron Age fort and some of the finest examples of Jurassic-period fossils in Wales. The pebble beach and its dramatic clifftops are part of a 14 miles (23 km)-long coastline protected under the Glamorgan Heritage Coast, which stretches from Gileston in the east to Newton Point beyond Southerndown in the west.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llwydarth">
            <name>Llwydarth</name>
            <lat>51.5997983</lat>
            <lon>-3.6472511</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#llysworney">
            <name>Llysworney</name>
            <lat>51.456682</lat>
            <lon>-3.492825</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llysworney">Llysworney (Welsh: Llyswyrni) is a small village in the Vale of Glamorgan, South Wales.
Llysworney is home to about 240 people and has around 100 houses. It is situated about 2 miles away from Cowbridge in the Vale of Glamorgan. The B4268, a major lorry route, connecting the A48 with Llandow and Llantwit Major, runs through Llysworney. The Village is home to the locally well-known Carne Arms Pub, St. Tydfils Church, a duck pond, and Llysworney Garage.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#lower penarth">
            <name>Lower Penarth</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#lower porthkerry">
            <name>Lower Porthkerry</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#maendy">
            <name>Maendy</name>
            <lat>51.478451</lat>
            <lon>-3.426208</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maendy">Maendy and variant spellings of the word, is a common place name in Wales and in other countries where people of Welsh descent have settled. It may refer to:

Maindee - a suburb of Newport
Maindy - a suburb of Cardiff
Maendy Quarry - a toxic waste land-fill</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#maesteg">
            <name>Maesteg</name>
            <lat>51.608562</lat>
            <lon>-3.660466</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maesteg">Maesteg (English translation: 'Fair field') is a town and community in Bridgend County Borough, Wales. Maesteg lies at the northernmost end of the Llynfi Valley, close to the border with Neath Port Talbot. In 2011, Maesteg had a population of 20,612.
Historically a part of Glamorgan, the growth of the town started with the opening of ironworks in the 1820s and 1830s. Once a coal mining area, the last pit closed in 1985. With the decline of the coal industry and, more recently, the closure of one large factory producing cosmetics and another manufacturing vehicle components, the valley has become a residential/dormitory area for the Port Talbot, Bridgend and Cardiff journey to work areas. 11% (1,867 out of 20,702) of the town's population speak Welsh.
^ Census 2011, Bridgend B.C. Ward Statistics for the upper Llynfi Valley (Caerau, Maesteg East and West, Llangynwyd). Retrieved 15 February 2013.
^ Davies, John; Jenkins, Nigel (2008). The Welsh Academy Encyclopaedia of Wales. Cardiff: University of Wales Press. p. 531. ISBN 978-0-7083-1953-6. 
^ http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/census/cyfrifiad-2011/ystadegau-allweddol-ar-gyfer-awdurdodau-unedol-yng-nghymru/stb-2011-key-statistics-for-wales---welsh.html</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maesteg">Mae Maesteg yn dref a chymuned ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yn ne Cymru. Mae Caerdydd 36.2 km i ffwrdd o Faesteg ac mae Llundain yn 246.2 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Abertawe sy'n 21.2 km i'r gorllewin. Yn 2011 roedd ei phoblogaeth yn 17,580, o'i gymharu â 17,859 yn 2001. Mae ganddi arwynebedd o 2,721 ha ac yn cwmpasu rhan uchaf Afon Llyfni. Gellir olrhain twf Maesteg i'r gwaith haearn a thunplat treflannau fel Porth-cawl, Llynfi a Llwydarth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#marcross">
            <name>Marcross</name>
            <lat>51.412418</lat>
            <lon>-3.547151</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcross">Marcross (Welsh: Marcroes) is a small village and civil parish in the Vale of Glamorgan, south Wales. It consists of a public house (the Horseshoes Inn) and a few scattered houses, farms, and a small medieval church in the centre of the village.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#mawdlam">
            <name>Mawdlam</name>
            <lat>51.5231661</lat>
            <lon>-3.7199599</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#merthyr dyfan">
            <name>Merthyr Dyfan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merthyr Dyfan">Merthyr Dyfan or Dyfan is a northeastern suburb of Barry in the Vale of Glamorgan, in south Wales, formerly an independent medieval village. It is also a traditional parish and a formal electoral ward of the Vale of Glamorgan. It borders Colcot to the west, Buttrills to the southwest and Gibbonsdown to the southeast. Its main roads are Merthyr Dyfan Road, a hilly road leading down from the A4050 road (Port Road) which leads into Wenvoe and Cardiff; and Skomer Road which separates it from Gibbonsdown and eventually also leads to the A4050 road. Merthyr Dyfan contains an old parish church, Barry Rugby Club, Bryn Hafren Comprehensive School and the Master Mariner Pub and Holm View Leisure Centre, although the last two could be considered to be in northern Gibbonsdown.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merthyr Dyfan">Pentref bychan a phlwyf ym Mro Morgannwg yw Merthyr Dyfan. Fe'i lleolir ar gwrr gogleddol Y Barri ar bwys y ffordd A4050, tua 6 milltir i'r de-orllewin o ddinas Caerdydd.
Enwir y pentref ar ôl Sant Dyfan a cheir eglwys a gysegrir iddo yn y pentref. Gall y gair merthyr yn y Gymraeg olygu "eglwys (er cof am sant neu ar ei fedd)" a dyna a geir yma; ceir enwau lleol tebyg eraill yn ne Cymru, e.e. Merthyr Tudful, Merthyr Cynog, a Merthyr Mawr, a cheir yr enwau cytras merther yn y Gernyweg a merzher yn Llydaweg hefyd, i gyd mewn enwau lleoedd.
Honnir mai dyma un o'r canolfannau Cristnogol cynharaf yng Nghymru. Yn ôl traddodiad, cafodd ei seyfydlu yn 180 OC pan anfonwyd Dyfan a Ffagan i Gymru gan y Pab Eleutherius. Cysylltir yr eglwys gyda Sant Teilo hefyd, sy'n nawddsant y plwyf gyda Dyfan. Cafodd ei difrodi yn sylweddol yng nghyfnod y Diwygiad Protestannaidd a'i hadfer yn y 19eg ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#merthyr mawr">
            <name>Merthyr Mawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merthyr Mawr">Merthyr Mawr is a village and community in Bridgend, Wales. The village is about 2½ miles from the centre of Bridgend town. The community occupies the area west of the Ewenny River, between Bridgend and Porthcawl. It takes in the settlement of Tythegston and a stretch of coastal sand dunes known as Merthyr Mawr Warren.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merthyr Mawr">Pentref a chymuned ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, de Cymru, yw Merthyr Mawr. Fe'i lleolir rhai milltiroedd i'r de o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, ar lan ogleddol Afon Ogwr.
Ystyr y gair merthyr yn yr enw yw 'eglwys (ar feddrod sant)'. Ceir croesau eglwysig wedi'u cofrestru gan Cadw yn yr eglwys, sef Croes Merthyr Mawr a Croes Tythegston.
Gerllaw'r pentref ceir Tywyn Merthyr Mawr, lle saethwyd rhai golygfeydd i'r ffilm enwog Lawrence of Arabia. Dyma'r ail tywyn mwyaf yn Ewrop, o ran uchder.
Yn ogystal mae dau gastell canoloesol, Castell Ogwr a Castell Candleston, yn daith gerdded hawdd i ffwrdd. Y pentref agosaf yw Ewenni, lle ceir Priordy Ewenni.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#michaelston-le-pit">
            <name>Michaelston-le-Pit</name>
            <lat>51.449978</lat>
            <lon>-3.222236</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michaelston-le-Pit">Michaelston-le-Pit (Welsh: Llanfihangel-y-pwll) is a village to the west of the city of Cardiff, Wales. The community population taken at the 2011 census was 309.
To the south lies Penarth, while to the south west lies the village of Dinas Powys.
The village is built near the confluence of two small streams, which join to form the Cadoxton River. The French suffix is possibly derived from a clay pit near the southern end of the village, it having been settled on a Norman family, the De Raneghs, after the conquest.
Llanfihangel-y-pwll means The Church of St Michael and All Angels of the Pool or Pit. It is not to be confused with Latin suffixed Michaelston-super-Ely or Welsh suffixed Michaelstone y Fedw</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#michaelston-super-ely">
            <name>Michaelston-super-Ely</name>
            <lat>51.477365</lat>
            <lon>-3.2708719</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michaelston-super-Ely">Michaelston-super-Ely is a village, to the west of the city of Cardiff, Wales.
Its Welsh name is Llanfihangel-ar-Elai where llan church + Mihangel Saint Michael + Elai River Ely). The historic church was decommissioned in 2010. It is approximately half a mile from the boundary with the Vale of Glamorgan. To the north lies the village of St Fagans, and to the east the Ely estate.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#monknash">
            <name>Monknash</name>
            <lat>51.425458</lat>
            <lon>-3.556041</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monknash">This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target article. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#monkton">
            <name>Monkton</name>
            <lat>51.4275405</lat>
            <lon>-3.5408054</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monkton">Monkton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monkton">Gallai Monkton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#morristown">
            <name>Morristown</name>
            <lat>40.7967667</lat>
            <lon>-74.4815438</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morristown">Morristown (infrequently spelled "Morice Town") may refer to:
Places
In Canada
Morristown, Nova Scotia (disambiguation)

In the United Kingdom
Morice Town, a part of Devonport in England that has now been subsumed within the city of Plymouth

In the United States of America
Morristown, Arizona
Morristown, Indiana
Morristown, Minnesota
Morristown, New Jersey in Morris County
Morristown, Middlesex County, New Jersey
Morristown (town), New York
Morristown (village), New York
Morristown, Ohio
Morristown, Tennessee
Morristown, West Virginia

Ships
USS Morristown (ID-3580), a United States navy cargo ship in commission from 1918 to 1919</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#moulton">
            <name>Moulton</name>
            <lat>51.422525</lat>
            <lon>-3.3334</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moulton">See also Molton
Moulton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#murch">
            <name>Murch</name>
            <lat>51.4335112</lat>
            <lon>-3.2089219</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murch">Murch may refer to:
Arthur Murch (1902–1989), Australian artist
Jamie Murch (born 1975), Australian cricketer
H.A. Murch (born c. 1896), photographer, Fellow of the Royal Photographic Society
Jordan Murch (born 1989), Scottish football midfielder
Simmy Murch (1880–1939), professional baseball player
Thompson H. Murch (1838–1886), nineteenth century politician, stonecutter, editor, publisher and merchant from Maine
Walter Murch (born 1943), Academy Award–winning film editor/sound designer
Walter Tandy Murch (1907–1967), painter whose still life paintings of machine parts, brick fragments, clocks, broken dolls, hovering light bulbs and glowing lemons are an unusual combination of realism and abstraction</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#nant-y-moel">
            <name>Nant-y-moel</name>
            <lat>51.626122</lat>
            <lon>-3.54221</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nant-y-moel">Pentref ger Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yn Nghwm Ogwr ym mwrdeisdref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ydy Nant-y-moel. Lleolir wrth droed Mynydd William Meyrick, a Craig Ogwr.
Roedd y bentref yn gymuned cloddio hyd i'r pwll glo cael ei gan yn yr 1980au.
↑ 1.0 1.1  A Tranquil Oasis. BBC South East Wales (3 Rhagfyr 2005).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#nantyffyllon">
            <name>Nantyffyllon</name>
            <lat>51.625093</lat>
            <lon>-3.658079</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#nash point">
            <name>Nash Point</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nash Point">Nash Point is a headland and beach in the Monknash Coast of the Vale of Glamorgan in south Wales. It is a popular location for ramblers and hiking along the cliffs to Llantwit Major beach.
A short circular walk of 4 miles from the lighthouses at Nash Point to St Donats can be accessed along the cliff tops. The walk covers part of the Glamorgan Heritage Coast path with dramatic views of the coast. The going is flat and easy although the cliff-tops can be muddy after rain. The walk goes past the Horse Shoe Inn at Marcross. Refreshments are sold at the Nash Point car park and there are toilets in the small building when it is open.
In 1962, the empty tanker BP Driver was pushed on the rocks and was abandoned. At low tide, remains of the wreck can be found about 200m north of the beach access by the light house.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#new beaupre">
            <name>New Beaupre</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#newcastle">
            <name>Newcastle</name>
            <lat>51.854012</lat>
            <lon>-2.806459</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcastle">Newcastle usually refers to either:
Newcastle upon Tyne, a city in Tyne and Wear, England
Newcastle, New South Wales, a metropolitan area in Australia
Newcastle or New Castle may also refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcastle">Gall Newcastle gyferirio at lleodd yn y byd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#newton">
            <name>Newton</name>
            <lat>51.5726783</lat>
            <lon>-4.0161386</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton">Newton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton">Gallai Newton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#north cornelly">
            <name>North Cornelly</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North Cornelly">North Cornelly is a village in Cornelly, Bridgend county borough, Wales. The village is close to South Cornelly, Pyle and Porthcawl, and junction 37 of the M4 motorway, which runs along its southern side.
The village is accessible from the motorway, the A4229 and the A48. There are regular buses to Porthcawl, Bridgend and Port Talbot. The nearest railway station is Pyle.
North Cornelly is first recorded as 'The Vill of Walter Lupellus' in a 12th-century document. The name North Cornelly probably derived from its close proximity to the crossroads where the road to the original village of Cornelly (present-day South Cornelly) branched off from the main road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#nottage">
            <name>Nottage</name>
            <lat>51.49062</lat>
            <lon>-3.703659</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nottage">Nottage (Welsh: Notais) is a small village near Porthcawl in Bridgend County Borough, Wales. The Bridgend ward population taken at the 2011 census was 3,293.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#nurston">
            <name>Nurston</name>
            <lat>51.395823</lat>
            <lon>-3.361203</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ogmore">
            <name>Ogmore</name>
            <lat>51.479396</lat>
            <lon>-3.608934</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogmore">Ogmore may refer to several places in south and southwest Wales:
Ogmore-by-Sea, a village in southeast Wales
River Ogmore, a river in south Wales
Ogmore Castle, a castle in south Wales
Ogmore (UK Parliament constituency), south Wales
Ogmore (National Assembly for Wales constituency), south Wales
Ogmore, Vale of Glamorgan, an ancient hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, south Wales
Ogmore Vale, a village in the County Borough of Bridgend, south Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ogmore vale">
            <name>Ogmore Vale</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogmore Vale">Ogmore Vale (Welsh: Cwm Ogwr) is a village in the county borough of Bridgend, Wales on the River Ogmore. The village's main source of income came from coal mining. Up until the year 1865, the Ogmore valley was a quiet, isolated, rural hill farming community of less than ten farms and a few cottages. Today, along with Nantymoel and Price Town it makes up the community of Ogmore Valley.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ogmore-by-sea">
            <name>Ogmore-by-Sea</name>
            <lat>51.4644285</lat>
            <lon>-3.6346563</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogmore-by-Sea">Ogmore-by-Sea (Welsh: Aberogwr, meaning "Mouth of the River Ogmore") is a seaside village in St Brides Major community in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. Ogmore river probably takes its name from the large caves on the seashore by the river mouth, Og being Welsh for cave. It lies on the western limit of the Glamorgan Heritage Coast of south Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#palmerstown">
            <name>Palmerstown</name>
            <lat>51.4173468</lat>
            <lon>-3.2413232</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmerstown">Palmerstown (Irish: Baile Phámar), officially but only occasionally referred to as Palmerston, is a civil parish and suburb in South Dublin, Ireland. It is located about 8 km west of Dublin city centre. The area is bordered to the north by the River Liffey, to the west by Lucan, to the south by Ballyfermot and to the east by the village of Chapelizod. Palmerstown village is situated near the Liffey Valley Shopping Centre. The area is situated near the major junction of the M50 motorway and the N4. It is 8.8 km from Dublin city centre. The Old Lucan Road, once the main route from the city to the west, passes through the centre of Palmerstown village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pancross">
            <name>Pancross</name>
            <lat>51.418406</lat>
            <lon>-3.370837</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pant-y-pyllau">
            <name>Pant-y-pyllau</name>
            <lat>52.1252054</lat>
            <lon>-3.3736765</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pant-yr-awel">
            <name>Pant-yr-awel</name>
            <lat>51.5782026</lat>
            <lon>-3.5458726</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-onn">
            <name>Pen-onn</name>
            <lat>51.6841</lat>
            <lon>-4.1620748</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-y-bont ar ogwr (bridgend)">
            <name>Pen-y-bont Ar Ogwr (Bridgend)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-y-cae">
            <name>Pen-y-cae</name>
            <lat>51.810283</lat>
            <lon>-3.677291</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-cae">Pen-y-cae may refer to one of these places in Wales:
Pen-y-cae, Bridgend
Pen-y-cae, Neath Port Talbot
Pen-y-cae, Powys
Penycae, Wrexham</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-y-fai">
            <name>Pen-y-fai</name>
            <lat>51.524357</lat>
            <lon>-3.595863</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-fai">Pentref ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yw Pen-y-fai. Fe'i lleolir i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ei hun, ar bwys y ffordd A4063. Poblogaeth: tua 2,000.
Ceir capel ymneilltuol, eglwys (Eglwys yr Holl Saint), siop a thafarn yn y pentref. Mae plant y pentref yn mynychu'r ysgol gynradd leol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-y-lan">
            <name>Pen-y-lan</name>
            <lat>51.502042</lat>
            <lon>-3.162457</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-lan">Ardal yng ngogledd Caerdydd, Cymru ydy Penylan, sy'n cael ei adnabod ei dai oes Fictoria a ffyrdd llydan gyda rhesi o goed ar eu hyd.
Mae'n pontio ffordd ddeuol yr A48 sy'n rhannu de a gogledd Penylan. Mae'n un o ardaloedd gwyrddaf Caerdydd, ac yn cynnwys rhan deheuol o Barc y Rhath.
Mae llyfrgell a chanolfan gymunedol wedi eu lleoli yn ne Penylan, ar gyffordd Ffordd Penylan a Ffordd Wellfield.
Agorwyd Synagogue Penylan ym 1955, a caewyd yn 2003 pan agorwyd synagogue newydd yng Ngerddi Cyncoed gerllaw.
↑  Penylan Library and Community Centre. library.wales.org.
↑  History. Cardiff United Synagogue. Adalwyd ar 2010-01-23.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pen-yr-heol">
            <name>Pen-yr-heol</name>
            <lat>51.7985217</lat>
            <lon>-2.8258365</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#penarth">
            <name>Penarth</name>
            <lat>51.438798</lat>
            <lon>-3.173507</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penarth">Penarth is a town in the Vale of Glamorgan (Welsh: Bro Morgannwg), Wales, 5.2 miles (8.4 km) south west from the city centre of the Welsh capital city of Cardiff and lying on the north shore of the Severn Estuary at the southern end of Cardiff Bay. Penarth is the wealthiest seaside resort in the Cardiff Urban Area, and the second largest town in the Vale of Glamorgan, next only to the administrative centre of Barry.
During the Victorian era Penarth was a highly popular holiday destination, promoted nationally as "The Garden by the Sea" and was packed by visitors from the Midlands and the West Country as well as day trippers from the South Wales valleys, mostly arriving by train. Today the town, with its traditional seafront, continues to be a regular summer holiday destination (predominantly for older visitors), but their numbers are much lower than was common from Victorian times until the 1960s, when cheap overseas package holidays were introduced.
Although the number of holiday visitors has greatly declined, the town retains a substantial retired population, representing over 25% of residents, but Penarth is now predominantly a dormitory town for Cardiff commuters. The town’s population was recorded as 20,396 in the United Kingdom Census 2001.
The town retains extensive surviving Victorian and Edwardian architecture in many traditional parts of the town, and house prices are usually significantly higher than similar properties in nearby Cardiff.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penarth">Mae Penarth yn dref ac yn gymuned arfordirol ym Mro Morgannwg, ger dinas Caerdydd. Mae Caerdydd 5 km i ffwrdd o Penarth ac mae Llundain yn 213.2 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Caerdydd sy'n 5 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pendoylan">
            <name>Pendoylan</name>
            <lat>51.4812524</lat>
            <lon>-3.3556796</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pendoylan">Pendoylan (Welsh: Pendeulwyn meaning 'head of two groves') is a rural village in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales, which has won many awards in Best Kept Village competitions and contains 27 entries in the Council's County Treasures database, 13 of which are listed buildings.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 10 April 2015. 
^ 
^ "Pendoylan" (PDF), Vale of Glamorgan County Treasures (Vale of Glamorgan Council), 2007, retrieved 17 August 2008</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pendre">
            <name>Pendre</name>
            <lat>51.518982</lat>
            <lon>-3.573769</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pendre">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanbadarn Fawr, Ceredigion, Cymru yw Pendre, sydd 73.9 milltir (118.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 178.1 milltir (286.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pendre yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Mark Williams (Y Democratiaid Rhyddfrydol).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#penllyn">
            <name>Penllyn</name>
            <lat>51.474035</lat>
            <lon>-3.479485</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penllyn">Penllyn may refer to the following places:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penllyn">Erthygl am yr ardal yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Am y pentref ym Mro Morgannwg gweler Pen-llin (Penllyn).
Penllyn yw'r ardal sydd o gwmpas Llyn Tegid a'r Bala ym Meirionnydd (de-ddwyrain Gwynedd). Mae'n cynnwys plwyfi Llandderfel, Llanfor, Llangywair, Llanycil a Llanuwchllyn. Mae Penllyn yn ardal sy'n enwog am ei chyfraniad i ddiwylliant Cymru a llenyddiaeth Gymraeg. Dyma ardal "Y Pethe", chwedl Llwyd o'r Bryn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#penmark">
            <name>Penmark</name>
            <lat>51.410817</lat>
            <lon>-3.358126</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmark">Penmark (Welsh: Pen-marc) is a rural village south-west of Barry near Rhoose in the Vale of Glamorgan, in South Wales. The village is a parish and is a Linear village. It has a parish church along the main road running through the village.
Penmark is located near the international airport for Wales, Cardiff International Airport.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#penprysg">
            <name>Penprysg</name>
            <lat>51.526827</lat>
            <lon>-3.495448</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pentre meyrick">
            <name>Pentre Meyrick</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#peterston-super-ely">
            <name>Peterston-super-Ely</name>
            <lat>51.4794234</lat>
            <lon>-3.3206234</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peterston-super-Ely">Peterston-super-Ely (Welsh: Llanbedr-y-fro) is a village in the Welsh county borough of the Vale of Glamorgan on th River Ely.The community population taken at the 2011 census was 874.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pitcot">
            <name>Pitcot</name>
            <lat>51.4553403</lat>
            <lon>-3.5878857</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pont rhyd-y-cyff">
            <name>Pont Rhyd-y-cyff</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pont-y-rhyl">
            <name>Pont-y-rhyl</name>
            <lat>51.592738</lat>
            <lon>-3.579878</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#pontycymer">
            <name>Pontycymer</name>
            <lat>51.612561</lat>
            <lon>-3.584162</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontycymer">Pontycymer is a former mining village in Wales. It is situated in the Garw Valley, in Bridgend County Borough . The name, sometimes spelled "Pontycymmer", is Welsh: pont signifies "bridge", while cymer signifies "confluence" of watercourses.
Original signs for the village use the incorrect spelling of Pontycymmer. Recent signage and postoffice records have now been changed to the correct spelling. At one side of the village, marking its boundary with Pantygog, the River Garw is joined by the Nant Forch Wen. At the other side, towards its boundary with Blaengarw, the River Garw is joined by the Nant Gelli Wern (marsh grove stream) at Ffaldau, the village square.
Among those born in the village are the artist and journalist Molly Parkin (Molly Thomas), snooker player Ryan Day, Wales rugby captain John Lloyd, and news reader Huw Edwards.
Numerous locations in Pontycymer feature as the fictional village of Ogw in the film Very Annie Mary. The oldest street in the village is Railway Terrace, originally named "Milk Row".</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontycymer">Mae Pontycymer yn dref ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yn ne Cymru. Mae Caerdydd 31.7 km i ffwrdd o Pontycymer ac mae Llundain yn 241.2 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Abertawe sy'n 26.1 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#porthkerry">
            <name>Porthkerry</name>
            <lat>51.391515</lat>
            <lon>-3.321825</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porthkerry">The hamlet of Porthkerry (Welsh: Porthceri) lies on the Bristol Channel coast of South Wales within the community of Rhoose between that village and the town of Barry to the east. It is very close to the end of the runway of Cardiff International Airport. To the east of the hamlet is Porthkerry Park which occupies the valley leading down to the coast.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#price town">
            <name>Price Town</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price Town">Price Town is situated 9 miles north of the County Town of Bridgend on the A4061 road in the upper reaches of the Cwm Ogwr Fawr (the Greater Ogmore Valley), Wales. It was developed to provide accommodation for the rapidly increasing work force of the Wyndham and Ocean Western Collieries.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price Town">Pentref yng Nghwm Ogwr ym mwrdeisdref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr yw Price Town. Saif ar y briffordd A4061 ac ar Afon Ogwr Fawr, ychydig i'r de o bentref Nant-y-moel ac i'r gogledd o dref Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#prisk">
            <name>Prisk</name>
            <lat>51.477775</lat>
            <lon>-3.421159</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisk">Prisk may refer to:
Charles H. Prisk (1875–1940), newspaper executive
Mark Prisk (born 1962), politician
William F. Prisk (1870–1962), newspaper executive</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#rhiwceiliog">
            <name>Rhiwceiliog</name>
            <lat>51.5463675</lat>
            <lon>-3.4954271</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#rhoose">
            <name>Rhoose</name>
            <lat>51.388917</lat>
            <lon>-3.349358</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoose">Rhoose (Welsh: Y Rhws) is a village and community located near the sea (the Bristol Channel) in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales, near Barry.
The village is the location of Cardiff International Airport, formerly RAF Rhoose, a Holiday Park (Fontygary Leisure Park), some shops, a library, two public houses (The Fontygary Inn and the Highwayman), Rhoose Social Club, and an active Surf Life Saving Club (Rhoose Lifeguards).
Rhoose is one of the fastest growing villages in the Vale of Glamorgan, with the two newest developments being "The Hollies", and more recently, Rhoose Point. Further development of Rhoose Point was halted in 2008, because of concerns the drainage infrastructure would not cope.
Rhoose Cardiff International Airport railway station, which was scheduled to re-open in 2003, suffered numerous bureaucratic delays before eventually re-opening in June 2005. There are now hourly train services to Cardiff and Bridgend via Barry and the Vale of Glamorgan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ruthin">
            <name>Ruthin</name>
            <lat>53.114725</lat>
            <lon>-3.310874</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthin">Ruthin (/ˈrɪθɪn/ RITH-in; Welsh: Rhuthun) is the county town of Denbighshire in north Wales. Located around a hill in the southern part of the Vale of Clwyd - the older part of the town, the castle and Saint Peter's Square are located on top of the hill, while many newer parts of the town are on the floodplain of the River Clwyd (which became apparent on several occasions in the late 1990s—new flood control works costing £3 million were inaugurated in autumn 2003). Ruthin also has villages on the outskirts of the town such as Pwllglas and Rhewl.
The name 'Ruthin' comes from the Welsh words rhudd (red) and din (fort), and refers to the colour of the new red sandstone which forms the geologic basis of the area, and from which the castle was constructed in 1277-1284. The original name of Rhuthin was 'Castell Coch yng Ngwern-fôr' (red castle in the sea-swamps). The town developed around the castle and the nearby mill. Maen Huail is a registered ancient monument attributed to the brother of Gildas and King Arthur and is located outside Barclays Bank (formerly Exmewe House), on St Peter's Square.
^ "Town/Ward population 2011". Retrieved 24 May 2015. 
^ "Ruthin flood defence plan unveiled". BBC Online. 2001-11-07. Retrieved 2007-06-08. 
^ Thomas Nicholas (1991-01-01). Annals and Antiquities of the Counties and County Families of Wales. ISBN 9780806313146. Retrieved 2007-10-08.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#sarn">
            <name>Sarn</name>
            <lat>51.54036</lat>
            <lon>-3.583936</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarn">Sarn may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarn">Gallai Sarn gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Tirffurfiau:
Sarn, tirffurf
Sarn Badrig, Bae Ceredigion
Ffyrdd:
Sarn Helen, yr hen ffordd Rufeinig yn cysylltu Gogledd a De Cymru
Pentrefi:
Sarn, Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, pentref yn ne Cymru
Sarn, Powys, pentref ym Mhowys
Sarn Bach, pentref yn Llŷn
Sarn Mellteyrn, pentref yn Llŷn
Gweler hefyd:
Sarnau (neu Y Sarnau), enw ar sawl pentref yng Nghymru</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#shelf">
            <name>Shelf</name>
            <lat>51.510119</lat>
            <lon>-3.532369</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shelf">Shelf may refer to:
Shelf (storage), a flat horizontal surface used for display and storage</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#shwt">
            <name>Shwt</name>
            <lat>51.565453</lat>
            <lon>-3.603123</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#sigingstone">
            <name>Sigingstone</name>
            <lat>51.4349975</lat>
            <lon>-3.4792305</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigingstone">Sigingstone is a small hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales.
It mainly consists of residential housing and two small working farms. There are two roads - one leading to the two nearby towns Llantwit Major and Cowbridge, and the other to Llanmihangel. It also has a 19th-century public house, called the Victoria Inn.
The village name is alternatively spelled "Sigginstone". This spelling is still used locally.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#south cornelly">
            <name>South Cornelly</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South Cornelly">South Cornelly is a village in Cornelly, Bridgend county borough, Wales. The village is close to North Cornelly, Pyle and Porthcawl, and junction 37 of the M4 motorway, which runs along its northern side.
The village is accessible from the motorway, the A4229 and the A48. There are regular buses to Porthcawl, Bridgend and Port Talbot. The nearest railway station is Pyle.
South Cornelly came into being as an Anglo-Norman settlement in the second half of the 12th century. The village is named after St Cornelius, and is the 'original' Cornelly, though a document of the time indicates that it was almost known as 'Thomastown' after Thomas son of William, an early local Lord of the Manor. His descendants subsequently adopted the name 'De Cornelly' and their house is believed to have been located at the site of the mansion called Ty Maen on the main road through the village.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#southerndown">
            <name>Southerndown</name>
            <lat>51.454553</lat>
            <lon>-3.612772</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southerndown">Southerndown is a village in South Wales to the southwest of Bridgend, in St Brides Major community, close to Llantwit Major and Ogmore-by-Sea. It is mostly known for its beach (officially named Dunraven bay), which is a popular tourist destination during the summer months and since 1972 has been designated a Heritage Coast and is part of the Southerndown Coast SSSI. When the tide is out there is an expanse of sand and pools. The cliffs are an obvious example of sedimentary rock.
As Southerndown, along with nearby Ogmore-by-Sea, is a west-facing beach (and hence on the Atlantic coast), off-shore winds from the East generate much good-quality surf, helped by the warming effects of the Gulf Stream.
There are actually two beaches separated by a headland. On the headland are the remains of Dunraven Castle.
The second beach is only accessible by steep steps and is largely unused. The steps also reach the beach fairly far out from the cliffside, so it's easy to become cut off from them and stranded on the beach at high tide. The second beach is one of the largest in Glamorgan and stretches all the way down the coast to Nash Point near Llantwit Major.
It has been used in the occasional TV production, including on Doctor Who: as Bad Wolf Bay in "Doomsday" and "Journey's End" and as the surface of the alien planet in "The Time of Angels" and "Flesh and Stone" and as the engine room of the ark ship in "Dinosaurs on a Spaceship". It also appeared in Merlin in the first season episode 'The Labyrinth of Gedref'. It was also featured in the Bob Dylan film Hearts of Fire, with Dylan looking out over the second beach down onto Rupert Everett.
During the summer, Southerndown Lifesaving Club use the beach as opposed to St Donat's Castle. It has a notable golf club, Southerndown Golf Club.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southerndown">Pentref ger Aberogwr ar arfordir Bro Morgannwg, de Cymru, yw Southerndown (ni cheir ffurf Gymraeg ar yr enw).
Gorwedd y pentref i'r de-orllewin o Ben-y-bont ar Ogwr ar lan Môr Hafren. Y pentrefi agosaf yw Aberogwr, ar hyd yr arfordir, a Saint-y-brid.
Prif atyniad y pentref bychan yw'r clogwyni ar y traeth a'r hwylfyrddio da sydd i'w gael yno.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#spelter">
            <name>Spelter</name>
            <lat>51.6277556</lat>
            <lon>-3.6582513</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spelter">Spelter, while sometimes used merely as a synonym for zinc, is often used to identify a zinc alloy. In this sense it might be an alloy of equal parts copper and zinc, i.e. a brass, used for hard soldering and brazing, or as an alloy, containing lead, that is used instead of bronze. In this usage it was common for many 19th-century cheap, cast articles such as candlesticks and clock cases and early 20th-century Art Nouveau ornaments and Art Deco figures.
Early twentieth-century Art Nouveau and Art Deco figures and lamps were often made of spelter. The metal has been used since about the 1860s to make statues, tablewares, and lamps that resemble bronze. Spelter is soft and breaks easily. To test for spelter, scratch the base of the piece. Bronze is solid; spelter will show a silvery scratch.
The word "pewter" is thought to be derived from the word "spelter". Zinc ingots formed by smelting might also be termed spelter.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st athan">
            <name>St Athan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Athan">St Athan (Welsh: Sain Tathan) is a village and community in the Vale of Glamorgan in South Wales. The village and its parish church are dedicated to Saint Tathan. The church dates to the 13th–14th century, though an earlier church was dated to the Norman period. The village and the adjacent dormitory village of Eglwys Brewis are known primarily for the MOD St Athan RAF base. There are two pubs in the village, as well as a football team and the RAF St Athan Golf Club.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st brides major">
            <name>St Brides Major</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Brides Major">St. Brides Major (Welsh: Saint-y-brid) is a village within the community also called St Brides Major in the Vale of Glamorgan in Wales. The community, which also includes Ogmore-by-Sea and Southerndown has a population of 2,009.
The village is the location of St. Bridget's church, the Fox &amp; Hounds and the Farmer's Arms pubs, Pitcot Pool and St. Brides Primary School.
The village is located approximately 1.5mi from the Vale of Glamorgan Heritage Coast. It is connected by bus to the nearby towns Llantwit Major and Bridgend 3 miles (5 km)).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st donats">
            <name>St Donats</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Donats">St Donats (Welsh: Sain Dunwyd) is a village and community in the Vale of Glamorgan in south Wales, located just west of the small town of Llantwit Major. The community includes the village of Marcross and the hamlets of Monknash and East and West Monkton. It is named after the 6th-century saint, Dunwyd, a friend of Saint Cadoc. It has a population of 686.

St. Donat's church lies in a depression and is unremarkable from the exterior but contains Stradling monuments.
The village is internationally known as the location of the 12th century St Donat's Castle which is now an international boarding school occupied by Atlantic College, the first of fourteen United World Colleges. Within the castle grounds lies St Donat's Arts Centre.
Saint Donat (Sveti Donat, Saint Donatus) (second half of 8th century - Zadar, Croatia first half of 9th century) was Dalmatian bishop and a diplomat of city of Zadar.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st hilary">
            <name>St Hilary</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st lythans">
            <name>St Lythans</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Lythans">St Lythans (Welsh: Llwyneliddon) is an affluent hamlet and former parish in the Vale of Glamorgan, southeast Wales, just outside of western Cardiff. It lies southwest of Culverhouse Cross, west of Wenvoe and southwest of Twyn-yr-Odyn and is also connected by road from Dyffryn and the Five Mile Lane in the west. It is one of the wealthiest communities in the Vale of Glamorgan, containing some notable mansions and cottages, valued on average at over £500,000 ($800,000) as of 2011. The megalithic St Lythans burial chamber, over 6000 years old, lies 1 km to the west of the village and the hamlet also contains the St.Lythans Parish Church or Church of St Bleddian, a Grade II* listed building.
↑ "St Lythan's home values". Zoopla. Retrieved 29 June 2011. 
↑ Castleden, Rodney (1992). Neolithic Britain: new stone age sites of England, Scotland, and Wales. Routledge. p. 383. ISBN 978-0-415-05845-2. Retrieved 28 June 2011.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st mary church">
            <name>St Mary Church</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st mary hill">
            <name>St Mary Hill</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Mary Hill">St Mary Hill is a settlement in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. It is located approximately 4 miles (6.4 km) outside the market town of Cowbridge. It is part of the community of Llangan along with Treoes and the village of Llangan itself.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st nicholas">
            <name>St Nicholas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#st y-nyll">
            <name>St y-Nyll</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#sully">
            <name>Sully</name>
            <lat>51.407086</lat>
            <lon>-3.219262</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sully">Sully can refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#swanbridge">
            <name>Swanbridge</name>
            <lat>51.400725</lat>
            <lon>-3.195282</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#thaw">
            <name>Thaw</name>
            <lat>51.4588936</lat>
            <lon>-3.4532108</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thaw">Thaw or THAW may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#the herberts">
            <name>The Herberts</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The Herberts">The Herberts is a hamlet in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. It is located immediately to the north of the village of St. Mary Church and southwest of Llandough, 2.2 miles by road southwest of the market town centre of Cowbridge along St. Athan Road. The River Thaw flows through The Herberts.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#the knap">
            <name>The Knap</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ton breigam">
            <name>Ton Breigam</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tondu">
            <name>Tondu</name>
            <lat>51.5450996</lat>
            <lon>-3.5976254</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tondu">Tondu (English: Black Sward) is a village in Bridgend County Borough, Wales, located about 3 miles (4.8 km) north of the town of Bridgend.
Tondu lies on the A4063 from Bridgend to Maesteg, and was established in the late 18th century as a coal mining village servicing the Parc Slip Colliery. In later years, an iron works was also established, and in the 19th century, a brick works was constructed using the clay from the carboniferous coal measures to make a variety of bricks, mostly for engineering. The brick works was demolished in 1977. The association with the coal industry was also reflected in the large area office of the National Coal Board in the village and a centre for the Mines Rescue Service.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tondu">Tref ger Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr ym mwrdeistref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, yn ne Cymru, yw Tondu. Saif ar y briffordd A4063.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tre-aubrey">
            <name>Tre-Aubrey</name>
            <lat>51.442834</lat>
            <lon>-3.384514</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tre-beferad">
            <name>Tre-Beferad</name>
            <lat>51.4037602</lat>
            <lon>-3.4661449</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tre-hill">
            <name>Tre-hill</name>
            <lat>51.4601008</lat>
            <lon>-3.3201258</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tre-pit">
            <name>Tre-pit</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tredogan">
            <name>Tredogan</name>
            <lat>51.400181</lat>
            <lon>-3.334536</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tremains">
            <name>Tremains</name>
            <lat>51.5062054</lat>
            <lon>-3.5733963</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#treoes">
            <name>Treoes</name>
            <lat>51.4941389</lat>
            <lon>-3.522416</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#trerhyngyll">
            <name>Trerhyngyll</name>
            <lat>51.4813059</lat>
            <lon>-3.433994</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tusker rock">
            <name>Tusker Rock</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tusker Rock">Tusker Rock (Welsh: Ynys Twsgr), is a rock in the Bristol Channel, situated about 2 miles west of Ogmore-by-Sea, Bridgend, Wales. It takes its name from Tuska the Viking, a Dane whose fellow Vikings semi-colonised the Vale of Glamorgan.
It is fully visible only at low tide, and was formerly a notorious hazard for ships.
On April 23, 1947 the SS Samtampa was wrecked nearby on Sker Point, leading to the loss of 39 officers and hands, plus eight of those of the crew of the Mumbles lifeboat while attempting a rescue.
Today, the waters around Tusker Rock are a popular diving location.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#twyn-yr-odyn">
            <name>Twyn-yr-odyn</name>
            <lat>51.456435</lat>
            <lon>-3.272815</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tyganol">
            <name>Tyganol</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#tythegston">
            <name>Tythegston</name>
            <lat>51.496828</lat>
            <lon>-3.648924</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wallston">
            <name>Wallston</name>
            <lat>51.452652</lat>
            <lon>-3.264716</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#walterston">
            <name>Walterston</name>
            <lat>51.432328</lat>
            <lon>-3.340104</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walterston">Walterston (Welsh: Tre-walter) is a small farming hamlet just north of Barry in the Vale of Glamorgan in South Wales and west of Dyffryn.
Walterston lies just to west of the Five Mile Lane leading down to Waycock Cross, Barry. The hamlet is very small and has just a few farms, all of which are twelfth to thirteenth century in origin. There are also several houses of which the two largest are the thatched 'Walterston Fach' and its neighbouring 'Trewalter Fawr'. The old monastic village of Llancarfan lies a further two miles to the west.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#waterton">
            <name>Waterton</name>
            <lat>51.4955153</lat>
            <lon>-3.5487207</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterton">Waterton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#waun y gilfach">
            <name>Waun y Gilfach</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#welsh st donats">
            <name>Welsh St Donats</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh St Donats">Welsh St Donats (Welsh: Llanddunwyd) is a village and a community in The Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. It is located North East of Cowbridge.
The electoral ward's population in 2011 was 471. The community includes the villages of: Maendy, Prisk and Tair Onen. A mile to the east from the village lies the Hensol Forest.
The church, St Dunwyd, is a Grade I Listed Building and was first mentioned in 1173.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wenvoe">
            <name>Wenvoe</name>
            <lat>51.4416242</lat>
            <lon>-3.2768121</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenvoe">Wenvoe (Welsh: Gwenfô) is a Welsh village between Barry and Cardiff in the Vale of Glamorgan, Wales. Nearby is the Wenvoe Transmitter near Twyn-yr-Odyn and the HTV Wales Television Centre at Culverhouse Cross in the suburbs of Cardiff. It is home to the Wenvoe Quarry, Wenvoe Castle Golf Club and the Walston Castle restaurant.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wern tarw">
            <name>Wern Tarw</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#west aberthaw">
            <name>West Aberthaw</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#west village">
            <name>West Village</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West Village">West Village is a neighborhood in the New York City borough of Manhattan. The area is roughly bounded by the Hudson River on the west and Sixth Avenue on the east, extending from West 14th Street south to West Houston Street. The Far West Village extends from the Hudson River to Hudson Street. Bordering neighborhoods are Chelsea to the north, Hudson Square – officially designated in 2009 – and South Village to the south, and Greenwich Village to the east. The neighborhood is primarily residential, with a multitude of small restaurants, shops, and services. The area is part of Manhattan Community Board 2, as well as of the Sixth Precinct of the New York City Police Department, which also covers an area east of the West Village between Sixth Avenue and Broadway from Houston to 14th Streets.
^ Wilson, Claire. "Neighborhoods: The West Village". topics.nytimes.com (The New York Times Company). Retrieved 2014-03-31. 
^ Cheslow, Jerry (April 18, 1993). "If You're Thinking of Living in: Far West Village". The New York Times. Retrieved 2014-03-31. 
^</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#west-end town">
            <name>West-end Town</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#westra">
            <name>Westra</name>
            <lat>51.432029</lat>
            <lon>-3.2293219</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wick">
            <name>Wick</name>
            <lat>51.439601</lat>
            <lon>-3.549989</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wick">Wick may refer to:
Candle wick, the cord used in a candle or oil lamp.
Solder wick, a copper-braided wire used to desolder electronic contacts.
WICK, the call letters of an AM broadcasting station located in Scranton, Pennsylvania, USA.
Wick (hieroglyph), an Ancient Egyptian alphabetic uniliteral sign.
Wick Communications (formerly Wick Newspaper Group), a United States community news company.
Wick product in probability theory
Wick rotation in physics
Capillary action ("wicking").
a nickname for Chadwick School, a private school in Los Angeles, California, USA.
An aircraft static discharger.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wick">Gallai Wick gyfeirio at:
Yr Alban
Wick, Ucheldiroedd yr Alban
Cymru
Y Wig (Saesneg: Wick), Bro Morgannwg
Lloegr
Wick, Dyfnaint
Wick, Swydd Gaerloyw
Wick, Gwlad yr Haf (dau le)
Wick, Sussex
Wick, Wiltshire
Wich, Swydd Gaerwrangon</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wig fach">
            <name>Wig Fach</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wild mill">
            <name>Wild Mill</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wyndham">
            <name>Wyndham</name>
            <lat>51.6124269</lat>
            <lon>-3.543501</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyndham">Wyndham may refer to:
Wyndham (name)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#wyndham park">
            <name>Wyndham Park</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#y bont-faen (cowbridge)">
            <name>Y Bont-Faen (Cowbridge)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="glamorgan#ystradowen">
            <name>Ystradowen</name>
            <lat>51.488889</lat>
            <lon>-3.424781</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ystradowen">Ystradowen is a small village twelve miles west of Cardiff, located in the Vale of Glamorgan in south Wales; its nearest town is Cowbridge which is about three miles to the south. The village was served by Ystradowen railway station between 1865 and 1951.
The name Ystradowen means "Owen's Valley" in English.
Local amenities include St Owain's parish church, The White Lion public house, Tudor Garage and Seven Oaks fisheries.
Notable residents: Tom Jones had a home in the village until 1998.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ystradowen">Pentref bychan sy'n gorwedd i'r gogledd o'r Bont-faen ym Mro Morgannwg, de Cymru, tua 12 milltir i'r gorllewin o ddinas Caerdydd, yw Ystradowen.
Ceir eglwys yn y pentref a thafarn y White Lion. Hyd at 1998 bu gan y canwr enwog o'r Cymoedd Tom Jones dŷ yn Ystradowen.</wikipedia>
        </town>
    </towns>
</county>