<?xml version="1.0"?>
<county name="Gwynedd">
    <postcodes>
        <postcode>LL21</postcode>
        <postcode>LL23</postcode>
        <postcode>LL33</postcode>
        <postcode>LL35</postcode>
        <postcode>LL36</postcode>
        <postcode>LL37</postcode>
        <postcode>LL38</postcode>
        <postcode>LL39</postcode>
        <postcode>LL40</postcode>
        <postcode>LL41</postcode>
        <postcode>LL42</postcode>
        <postcode>LL43</postcode>
        <postcode>LL44</postcode>
        <postcode>LL45</postcode>
        <postcode>LL46</postcode>
        <postcode>LL47</postcode>
        <postcode>LL48</postcode>
        <postcode>LL49</postcode>
        <postcode>LL51</postcode>
        <postcode>LL52</postcode>
        <postcode>LL53</postcode>
        <postcode>LL54</postcode>
        <postcode>LL55</postcode>
        <postcode>LL56</postcode>
        <postcode>LL57</postcode>
        <postcode>SY20</postcode>
    </postcodes>
    <towns>
        <town id="gwynedd#aber-cywarch">
            <name>Aber-Cywarch</name>
            <lat>52.730628</lat>
            <lon>-3.677661</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#aberdaron">
            <name>Aberdaron</name>
            <lat>52.804729</lat>
            <lon>-4.711515</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdaron">Aberdaron is a community and former fishing village at the western tip of the Llŷn Peninsula (Welsh: Penrhyn Llŷn) in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies 14.8 miles (23.8 km) west of Pwllheli and 33.5 miles (53.9 km) south west of Caernarfon, and has a population of 965. It is sometimes referred to as the "Land's End of Wales" (Welsh: Pendraw'r Byd). The community includes Bardsey Island (Welsh: Ynys Enlli), the coastal area around Porthor, and the villages of Anelog, Llanfaelrhys, Penycaerau, Rhoshirwaun, Rhydlios, Uwchmynydd and Y Rhiw.
The village was the last rest stop for pilgrims heading to Bardsey Island, the legendary "island of 20,000 saints". In the 18th and 19th centuries it developed as a shipbuilding centre and port. The mining and quarrying industries became major employers, and limestone, lead, jasper and manganese were exported, and there are the ruins of an old pier running out to sea at Porth Simdde, which is the local name for the west end of Aberdaron Beach. After the Second World War the mining industry collapsed, and Aberdaron gradually developed into a popular holiday resort. The beach was awarded a Seaside Award in 2008.
The coastal waters are part of Pen Llŷn a'r Sarnau Special Area of Conservation (Welsh: Ardal Cadwraeth Arbennig Pen Llŷn a'r Sarnau), one of the largest marine designated sites in the United Kingdom. The coast itself forms part of the Aberdaron Coast and Bardsey Island Special Protection Area (Welsh: Ardal Gwarchodaeth Arbennig Glannau Aberdaron ac Ynys Enlli), and was designated a Heritage Coast in 1974. In 1956 the area was included in Llŷn Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (Welsh: Ardal o Harddwch Naturiol Eithriadol Llŷn). Conservation Areas have been created in Aberdaron, Bardsey Island and Y Rhiw; and the area has been designated a Landscape of Historic Interest.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdaron">Pentref glan môr a chymuned yng ngorllewin Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Aberdaron. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 84612 10067. Fel y pentref agosaf at Ynys Enlli yr oedd yn gyrchfan bwysig i bererinion yn yr Oesoedd Canol. Sefydlwyd clas yno yn Oes y Seintiau.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#aberdesach">
            <name>Aberdesach</name>
            <lat>53.03569</lat>
            <lon>-4.34838</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdesach">Aberdesach is a village in the Welsh principal area of Gwynedd.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdesach">Pentref bychan ar arfordir gogleddol Gwynedd yw Aberdesach. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 42682 51369. Saif ar ffordd yr A499 o Gaernarfon i Bwllheli, rhwng Pontllyfni a Chlynnog Fawr. Mae Afon Desach yn tarddu gerllaw Bwlch Derwin uwchben y pentref ac yn cyrraedd y môr ger rhan ogleddol y pentref. Ystyrir y pentref yn rhan o Ddyffryn Nantlle.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#aberdyfi">
            <name>Aberdyfi</name>
            <lat>52.543963</lat>
            <lon>-4.046093</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdyfi">Aberdyfi (English: Mouth of the River Dyfi), or Aberdovey (the Anglicised spelling is in common use) is a village and community on the north side of the estuary of the River Dyfi in Gwynedd, on the west coast of Wales.
The village was founded around the harbour and shipbuilding industry, but is now best known as a seaside resort with a high quality beach. The town centre is on the river and seafront, around the original harbour, jetty and beach but it stretches back from the coast and up the steep hillside in the midst of typical Welsh coastal scenery of steep green hills and sheep farms. Penhelig, with its own railway station, is the eastern part of the town.
Aberdyfi is a popular tourist attraction, with many returning holidaymakers, especially from the metropolitan areas of England, such as the West Midlands, which is less than 100 miles to the east. A relatively large proportion of houses in the village are now holiday homes, resulting in high house prices. The town is located within the Snowdonia National Park. In the 2011 census, 38.5% of the population of Aberdyfi ward identified themselves as Welsh (or combined).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdyfi">Tref fach a chymuned ar lan ogleddol aber eang Afon Dyfi ym Meirionnydd, Gwynedd yw Aberdyfi. Cyfeirnod OS: SN 60728 96024. Mae ar yr A493 a Rheilffordd y Cambrian, rhwng Pennal a Machynlleth i'r dwyrain a Thywyn i'r gogledd. Twristiaeth yw'r prif ddiwydiant yno heddiw. Mae traeth eang tywodlyd yn ymestyn am filltiroedd o Aberdyfi i Dywyn ac mae'n boblogaidd iawn gydag ymwelwyr haf.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#abererch">
            <name>Abererch</name>
            <lat>52.903768</lat>
            <lon>-4.381498</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abererch">Abererch (Welsh for "Mouth of the Erch") is a small village and former civil parish on the Lleyn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. The village lies approximately 1 mile (1.6 km) east of Pwllheli. A river, the Afon Erch runs through the village.
The parish was abolished in 1934 and incorporated into that of Llannor, now the community of Llannor. It is a mostly Welsh-speaking village.

There is a primary school, playschool, and a railway station. The church of St Cawrdaf is a grade I listed building.
Abererch has a beach which is between Pwllheli and Penychain (Haven Holiday Park). Parking for the beach is near the railway station. From the beach you have a view of Harlech Castle in the east all the way down to Tywyn (on a clearer day even further south) and to the west Pwllheli and the St Tudwals. Access to the beach is through a footpath next the caravan and camp-site. This beach is ideal for days when the wind is from the north or north west due to the sheltered bay.
^ "Ward population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015. 
^ http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk/relationships.jsp?u_id=10413965 A Vision of Britain Through Time : Abererch Civil Parish Retrieved 12 January 2010
^ "2001 Census - Electoral Division Level Language Data" (in Excel format). Retrieved 25 November 2010. 
^ "Church of St Cawrdaf, Llannor". British Listed Buildings. Retrieved 4 January 2014.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abererch">Pentref ym Mhenrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd, rhyw filltir i'r dwyrain o dref Pwllheli yw Abererch. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 39930 36719. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llannor.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#abergwyngregyn">
            <name>Abergwyngregyn</name>
            <lat>53.233669</lat>
            <lon>-4.014381</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergwyngregyn">Abergwyngregyn is a village and community of historical note in Gwynedd, a county and principal area in Wales. Under its historic name of Aber Garth Celyn it was the seat of Llywelyn ap Gruffudd.
It is located at grid reference SH653726, adjacent to the A55, five miles (8 km) east of Bangor, eight miles (13 km) west of Conwy. Population 222.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergwyngregyn">Pentref bychan a chymuned yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Gwynedd yw Abergwyngregyn, neu Aber (Cyfeirnod OS: SH 66534 73367). Saif tua hanner milltir o'r môr wrth geg ceunant dwfn sy'n arwain i mewn i'r Carneddau. Ceir gwarchodfa natur ger y traeth ac mae glannau Traeth Lafan ei hun yn warchodfa adar lle gwelir nifer o rywogaethau o adar môr. Roedd teithwyr i Ynys Môn yn arfer croesi Traeth Lafan i ddal y cwch fferi drosodd i Lanfaes tan i Bont y Borth gael ei chodi. Mae'r caeau rhwng y pentref a'r traeth yn dir porfa bras a lleolir Fferm Prifysgol Cymru, Bangor ar ymyl y pentref. Mae'r eglwys, sy'n gysegredig i Sant Bodfan, yn dyddio yn ôl i 1878 ac yn sefyll ar safle'r hen eglwys. Mae Llwybr y Gogledd yn gweu drwy'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#abergynolwyn">
            <name>Abergynolwyn</name>
            <lat>52.64435</lat>
            <lon>-3.950379</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergynolwyn">Abergynolwyn (English: Mouth of the River with a Whirlpool) is a village in southern Gwynedd, Wales, located at the confluence of the Nant Gwernol and the Afon Dysynni.
Historically, the village was part of Merionethshire and its main industry was slate quarrying. The village was founded in the 1860s to house workers at the nearby Bryn Eglwys quarry. Today farming, forestry and tourism are the major local industries.
The village pub, the Railway Inn, is named after the Talyllyn Railway whose narrow gauge branch once reached into the heart of the village down an incline from a ledge on the hillside above. The railway now terminates at Nant Gwernol station above the village, although for many years the terminus was at Abergynolwyn Station outside the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergynolwyn">Pentref bychan yng Ngwynedd yw Abergynolwyn, gerllaw Afon Dysynni; Cyfeirnod OS: SH677069. Ar un adeg yr oedd diwydiant llechi pwysig yn yr ardal yma, a sefydlwyd y pentref yn y 1860au ar gyfer gweithwyr yn Chwarel Bryn Eglwys gerllaw yn Nant Gwernol. Heddiw ffermio a thwristiaeth yw’r prif ddiwydiannau. Cynhelir eisteddfod flynyddol yno.
Gerllaw’r pentref mae Rheilffordd Talyllyn, Llyn Mwyngil, Castell y Bere ger pentref cyfagos Llanfihangel-y-pennant a Chraig yr Aderyn lle mae bryngaer o Oes yr Haearn ac amrywiaeth o adar.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#abersoch">
            <name>Abersoch</name>
            <lat>52.824497</lat>
            <lon>-4.5053599</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abersoch">Abersoch is a large village in the community of Llanengan in Gwynedd, Wales. It is a popular coastal seaside resort with approximately 1,000 inhabitants, on the east-facing south coast of the Llŷn Peninsula at the southern terminus of the A499. It is about 7 miles (11 km) south-west of Pwllheli and 27 miles (43 km) south-west of the county town of Caernarfon. The village takes its name from the river, Afon Soch, which reaches the sea in the village.
Originally a fishing port, Abersoch is now a tourist centre specialising in dinghy sailing and other watersports such as windsurfing and jet-skiing. Nearby Porth Neigwl or Hell's Mouth, is also popular for surfing; it can hold large swells in the winter which can reach 5 feet (1.5m) however south westerly prevailing winds can affect quality.
Each year since 2000 Abersoch has been host to Wakestock a wakeboarding event. The Big Air competition on the main beach is held in July.
Central Abersoch has a variety of small shops as well as bars, restaurants, cafes and hotels. Boat trips around St Tudwal's Islands to see the seals and other wildlife are available from the village. It is also popular for its close proximity to Snowdonia National Park, with Snowdon being visible from Abersoch Bay on clear days. There is an 18 hole golf course.
Virtually all the indigenous residents of Abersoch are Welsh language speakers.
Abersoch has a primary school for 3 to 8 year olds. The neighbouring village of Sarn Bach has a primary school for 3 to 11 year olds. The two schools between them educate 74 pupils. The closest specialist school is Ysgol Hafod Lon in Pwllheli.
Year 7 pupils travel to Ysgol Botwnnog, 5 miles (8.0 km) inland, which is a Welsh speaking school. Non Welsh speakers tend to attend Ysgol Glan y Mor in Pwllheli, 7 miles (11 km) away.
^ "Ward population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abersoch">Pentref sylweddol o faint yw Abersoch a leolir ar benrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd, ym mhen draw'r A499 (cyfeiriad grid SH313282). Mae'n gorwedd 11 km (7 milltir) i'r dwyrain o dref Pwllheli a 43 km (27 milltir) o Gaernarfon. Enwir y pentref ar ôl aber Afon Soch, sy'n cyrraedd y môr yma ar ôl llifo trwy'r pentref.

Datblygodd Abersoch fel porthladd pysgota bychan, ond erbyn hyn twristiaeth yw’r prif ddiwydiant, yn enwedig hwylio. Daeth y pentref yn un o ganolfannau hwylio pwysicaf Prydain yn ystod y trigain mlynedd diwethaf. Oherwydd hyn mae nifer fawr o fewnfudwyr yn y pentref, wedi symud yno o Loegr yn bennaf, ac mae Cymreictod yr ardal a'r iaith Gymraeg wedi dioddef yn enbyd mewn canlyniad.
Ceir nifer o siopau a lleoedd bwyta yn y pentref. Gellir hefyd cymeryd taith mewn cwch i weld Ynysoedd Tudwal.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#abertrinant">
            <name>Abertrinant</name>
            <lat>52.3610003</lat>
            <lon>-3.9568073</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abertrinant">Abertrinant is a small settlement in Gwynedd, Wales. It is 7 kilometres (4 mi) northeast of the town of Tywyn.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#afon wen">
            <name>Afon Wen</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afon Wen">Afon Wen is a small hamlet on the Llŷn peninsula in the Welsh principal area of Gwynedd.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afon Wen">Am y pentref yn Sir Fflint, gweler Afon-wen.

Mae Afon Wen (weithiau Afonwen) yn bentref bychan ar afordir deheuol Penrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd; cyfeirnod OS: SJ 13324 71493. Saif ar y briffordd A497 tua hanner milltir i'r de o bentref Chwilog a thua hanner y ffordd rhwng Cricieth a Pwllheli, lle mae'r afon o'r un enw yn cyrraedd y môr. Mae gwersyll gwyliau Butlins ym Mhenychain ychydig i'r gorllewin.
Ar un adeg gorsaf Afon Wen oedd lle roedd rheilffordd yn gadael y brif reilffordd i Bwllheli ac yn rhedeg tua'r gogledd i gysylltu a'r rheilffordd ar hyd yr arfordir gogleddol yng Nghaernarfon. Caewyd y lein yma yn 1965 a chodwyd y trac. Mae rhan o'r lein yma, rhwng Dinas a Chaernarfon, yn awr yn rhan o drac Rheilffordd Ucheldir Cymru. Erys y cof amdani, er enghraifft yn y gân Ar y Trên i Afon Wen gan Sobin a'r Smaeliaid.
Mae'r Lôn Goed yn cychwyn yn Afon Wen. Ceir sawl cyfeiriad ati gan lenorion, e.e. gan y bardd R. Williams Parry yn ei gerdd 'Eifionydd'.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#anafon">
            <name>Anafon</name>
            <lat>52.614389</lat>
            <lon>-3.308348</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#anelog">
            <name>Anelog</name>
            <lat>52.814761</lat>
            <lon>-4.7396779</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#arthog">
            <name>Arthog</name>
            <lat>52.711596</lat>
            <lon>-4.009899</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthog">Arthog is a village, post town and community in the Meirionnydd area in Wales. It is located on the A493, approximately 8 miles (13 km) west of Dolgellau, and has a population of 1,010, increasing slightly to 1,031 at the 2011 census.
It is well known for its outdoor activity centres and the nearby Llynnau Cregennen (Cregennen lakes). The Arthog Outdoor Education Centre is owned by Telford and Wrekin Council and is primarily used in term-time by schools from the Shropshire and Telford &amp; Wrekin Local Education Authorities. The other outdoor activity centre, Min Y Don, has been family owned and run since the 1950s. They too are primarily used in term-time by schools from the Midlands, but are also heavily involved with local community work too.
In 1894, Solomon Andrews, a Cardiff entrepreneur, bought land overlooking the Mawddach estuary. On the site he completed Mawddach Crescent in 1902. The row of terraced properties was the start of a purpose-built holiday resort he intended for the area. However the planned development went no further because the surrounding land proved unsuitable for urban planning. During the Second World War, the Royal Marines commandeered Mawddach Crescent. It became known as Iceland Camp. The marines also built huts on nearby Fegla Fawr, the foundation bases can still be seen between the trees above the estuary.
The village was served by Arthog railway station (on the Barmouth - Ruabon line) until the complete closure of the line in 1964. The line is now a footpath known as the Llwybr Mawddach (English: Mawddach Trail), and is popular with both walkers and cyclists.
^ Office for National Statistics : Census 2001 : Parish Headcounts : Gwynedd
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 17 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthog">Pentref a chymuned arfordirol yng Ngwynedd yw Arthog. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 64388 14585. Saif ar ochr ddeheuol aber Afon Mawddach, i'r de-ddwyrain o Abermaw ac ar y briffordd A493. Mae Afon Arthog yn llifo trwy'r pentref i ymuno ag Afon Mawddach, a cheir rhaeadr gerllaw.
Gorwedd Llynnau Cregennen ychydig i'r dwyrain. Yn ne'r gymuned ceir Llyn Cyri.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#artro">
            <name>Artro</name>
            <lat>52.8177708</lat>
            <lon>-4.1010747</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bala">
            <name>Bala</name>
            <lat>52.909911</lat>
            <lon>-3.601584</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bala">Bala may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bala">Am y dref yng Ngwynedd, gweler Y Bala. Gweler hefyd Bala (gwahaniaethu).
Tirffurf afonol yw bala. Gair cyffredin Cymraeg am 'adwy, bwlch' oedd 'bala' gynt. Datlygodd yr ystyr i olygu man lle mae afon yn llifo allan o lyn, ac felly i raddau yn wrthwyneb i aber. Felly mae'r enw lle 'Y Bala' (Gwynedd) yn golygu yn benodol y fan lle rhed afon Dyfrdwy o Lyn Tegid.
Yn ogystal â thref Y Bala yng Ngwynedd, fe'i ceir hefyd yn enwau llefydd megis Baladeulyn yn Nyffryn Nantlle.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bangor">
            <name>Bangor</name>
            <lat>53.22739</lat>
            <lon>-4.129263</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangor">Bangor may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangor">Mae'r erthygl yma'n cyfeirio at Fangor, Gwynedd, gogledd Cymru. Gweler Bangor (gwahaniaethu) am leoedd eraill a elwir yn Fangor.
Dinas a chymuned yw Bangor yng Ngwynedd, gogledd-orllewin Cymru; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 58179 72393. Mae ganddi boblogaeth o tua 15,000 (neu tua 21,735 gan gynnwys ei chyrion). Mae Prifysgol Bangor ac Eglwys Gadeiriol Bangor yn y ddinas. Bangor yw canolfan Esgobaeth Bangor a sedd Esgob Bangor. Yr enw llawn tan yn ddiweddar oedd 'Bangor Fawr yn Arfon'.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bardsey island">
            <name>Bardsey Island</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bardsey Island">Bardsey Island (Welsh: Ynys Enlli), the legendary "Island of 20,000 saints", lies 1.9 miles (3.1 km) off the Llŷn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. The Welsh name means "The Island in the Currents", although its English name refers to the "Island of the Bards", or possibly the island of the Viking chieftain, "Barda".
Bardsey is 0.6 miles (1.0 km) wide, 1.0 mile (1.6 km) long and 179 hectares (440 acres; 0.69 sq mi) in area. The north east rises steeply from the sea to a height of 548 feet (167 m) at Mynydd Enlli, which is a Marilyn, while the western plain is low and relatively flat cultivated farmland. To the south the island narrows to an isthmus, connecting to a peninsula on which the lighthouse stands. Since 1974 it has been included in the community of Aberdaron. It is the fourth largest offshore island in Wales.
The island has been an important religious site since Saint Cadfan built a monastery in 516. In medieval times it was a major centre of pilgrimage and, by 1212, belonged to the Augustinian Canons Regular. The monastery was dissolved and its buildings demolished by Henry VIII in 1537, but the island remains an attraction for pilgrims to this day.
Bardsey Island is now as famous for its wildlife and rugged scenery. A bird observatory was established in 1953, largely due to the island's position on important migration routes. It is of European importance, cited as a nesting place for Manx shearwaters and choughs, its rare plants, and habitats undisturbed by modern farming practices. It is one of the best places in Gwynedd to see grey seals, and the waters around the island attract dolphins and porpoises.
The spirituality and sacredness of the island, its relative remoteness, and its legendary claim to be the burial site of King Arthur, have given it a special place in the cultural life of Wales, attracting artists, writers and musicians to its shores. It has inspired award winning literature, and attracted internationally renowned singers.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#barmouth">
            <name>Barmouth</name>
            <lat>52.722873</lat>
            <lon>-4.0560919</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barmouth">Barmouth (Welsh: Abermaw (formal); Y Bermo (colloquial)) is a town in the county of Gwynedd, north-western Wales, lying on the estuary of the River Mawddach and Cardigan Bay. Historically in Merionethshire, the English form of the name is derived from "Aber" (estuary) and the river's name "Mawddach"
The town is served by Barmouth railway station.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#beddgelert">
            <name>Beddgelert</name>
            <lat>53.0118834</lat>
            <lon>-4.1028234</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beddgelert">Beddgelert (English: Gelert's Grave), is a village and community in the Snowdonia area of Gwynedd, Wales. The population of the community taken at the 2011 census was 453. It is reputed to be named after the legendary hound Gelert.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beddgelert">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Beddgelert; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 59157 48176. Fe'i lleolir ar lecyn deniadol iawn yng nghanol Eryri. Saif ger aber Afon Glaslyn ac Afon Colwyn. Fymryn islaw'r aber rhed yr afon dan hen bont gerrig â dau fwa yng nghanol y pentref. Mae nifer o'r tai a'r gwestai wedi'u hadeiladu o gerrig tywyll lleol. I'r gorllewin mae Moel Hebog a'i chymdogion ac i'r gogledd ceir cyfres o fryniau sy'n codi i ben Yr Wyddfa. Mae lôn yr A4085 rhwng Caernarfon (13 milltir i'r gogledd) a Porthmadog (8 milltir i'r de) yn rhedeg trwy'r pentref. Mae lôn arall yn arwain i galon mynyddoedd Eryri trwy Nant Gwynant i Ben-y-gwryd, ac ymlaen i Gapel Curig neu Llanberis.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bethania">
            <name>Bethania</name>
            <lat>52.249481</lat>
            <lon>-4.084091</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethania">Bethania may refer to:
Bethania, North Carolina, Moravian Community Established 1759
Bethania, Queensland, a suburb of Logan City, Queensland, Australia
Bethany (Israel), a village near Jerusalem
Betania monastery, in the nation of Georgia
Bethania Rehabilitation Centre, in Kerala, India
Bethania, Ceredigion, a hamlet in Wales, home of Tŷ Nant spring water
Bethania de la Cruz (born 1989), Dominican Republic volleyball player
Short for Maria Bethânia, a Brazilian singer
Bethania, Aberdare, a chapel in Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethania">Gallai Bethania gyfeirio at:
Lleoedd
Bethania (Al-Eizariya), dinas yn y Testament Newydd a thref hanesyddol yn y Lan Orllewinol, ger Jeriwsalem
Bethania, Ceredigion, Cymru
Bethania, Gwynedd, Cymru
Bethania, De Carolina, UDA
Bethania, Queensland, un o faesdrefi Brisbane yn Awstralia
Adeiladau
Capel Bethania, Aberteifi, Cymru
Gweler hefyd
Betania</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bethasda">
            <name>Bethasda</name>
            <lat>53.178927</lat>
            <lon>-4.058833</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bethel">
            <name>Bethel</name>
            <lat>53.16313</lat>
            <lon>-4.212325</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethel">Bethel (Ugaritic: bt il, meaning "House of El" or "House of God", Hebrew: בֵּית אֵל, also transliterated Beth El, Beth-El, or Beit El; Greek: Βαιθηλ; Latin: Bethel) was a border city described in the Hebrew Bible as being located between Benjamin and Ephraim and also a location named by Jacob. Edward Robinson identified the village of Beitin in the West Bank with ancient Bethel in Biblical Researches in Palestine, 1838–52. He based this assessment on its fitting the location described in earlier texts, and on the philological similarities between the modern and ancient name, arguing that the replacement of the Hebrew el with the Arabic in was not unusual. During Israelite rule, Bethel first belonged to the Tribe of Benjamin, but was later conquered by the Tribe of Ephraim. Eusebius of Caesarea and Jerome describe it in their time as a small village that lay 12 Roman miles north of Jerusalem, to the right or east of the road leading to Neapolis.
Ten years after the Six Day War, the biblical name was applied to an Israeli settlement Beit El constructed adjacent to Beitin. In several countries - particularly in the US - the name was given to various locations (see Bethel (disambiguation)).
A second biblical Bethel, in the southern Judah, is mentioned in the Book of Joshua (Joshua 8:17 and Joshua 12:16), and seems to be the same as Bethul or Bethuel, a city of the tribe of Simeon.
↑ Bleeker and Widegren, 1988, p. 257.
↑ Robinson and Smith, 1856, pp. 449–450.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bethesda">
            <name>Bethesda</name>
            <lat>53.178927</lat>
            <lon>-4.058833</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethesda">Bethesda (Aramaic, בית חסדא, beth ḥesda, "House of Mercy"), originally referring to the Pool of Bethesda in Jerusalem (in the New Testament of the Christian Bible), may also refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethesda">Erthygl am y pentref yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Gweler hefyd Bethesda (gwahaniaethu).
Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd, yn Nyffryn Ogwen, a enwyd ar ôl Capel Bethesda. Y mae ei thrigolion yn aml yn cyfeirio ati fel Pesda. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 62262 66779. Mae Caerdydd 193.8 km i ffwrdd o Bethesda ac mae Llundain yn 334.4 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 18.6 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#betws garmon">
            <name>Betws Garmon</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betws Garmon">Betws Garmon is a community and small hamlet outside Waunfawr and near Beddgelert in Gwynedd, Wales. It has a population of 216.
The summit of Snowdon lies within the community boundaries. Bryn Gloch has the newly reopened narrow gauge Welsh Highland Railway passing alongside it.
Over the road from Bryn Gloch there is a parish church. Along the mountain you can see extensive slate workings.
Betws Garmon also has a park near it. Near the station there is a road which leads to Rhosgadfan. Up that road there is a footpath that leads to Y Fron. A river that flows through the hamlet is called Afon Gwyrfai.

There is a folk tale concerning the family of Pellings, who lived at Betws Garmon until the 19th century. It was said that they were descended from a man and a fairy named Penelope. Penelope lived happily with her human husband until she was accidentally touched with a piece of iron, whereupon she disappeared forever.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betws Garmon">Am enghreifftiau eraill o'r gair betws, gweler Betws (gwahaniaethu).

Pentref gwledig a chymuned yn ardal Arfon, Gwynedd, yw Betws Garmon. Saif ar yr A4085 ar ymyl Eryri, traean o'r ffordd rhwng Caernarfon a Beddgelert; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 54546 56819. Ar hyd y ffordd i gyfeiriad y gogledd, Waunfawr yw'r pentref agosaf ac i'r de mae'r ffordd yn ei gysylltu â Salem a Rhyd-ddu, pentref genedigol T.H. Parry-Williams.
Mae lleoliad y pentref yng ngogledd Eryri gyda bryniau Moel Eilio (2382') i'r dwyrain a thalp Mynydd Mawr (2290') i'r de-orllewin. Llifa Afon Gwyrfai sy'n tarddu yn Llyn Cwellyn tair milltir i'r de, heibio i'r pentref, sy'n sefyll ar ei glan ddwyreiniol. Filltir y tu allan i'r pentref i'r de, ar ymyl yr A4085, mae Melin y Nant a'i rhaeadr fach.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#blaenau ffestiniog">
            <name>Blaenau Ffestiniog</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaenau Ffestiniog">Blaenau Ffestiniog is a historic mining town in Gwynedd, Wales. It has a population of 4,875 according to the 2011 census, including the attached village of Llan Ffestiniog, which makes it the third largest town in Gwynedd unitary authority, behind Bangor and Caernarfon. Although the population reached 12,000 at the peak of the slate industry, the population fell due to a decrease in the demand for slate. Blaenau Ffestiniog at one time was the second largest town in North Wales, behind Wrexham. Today, the town relies heavily on tourists, who come to see the many attractions within and around the town such as the Ffestiniog Railway and the Llechwedd Slate Caverns.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaenau Ffestiniog">Mae Blaenau Ffestiniog yn dref yng Ngwynedd sydd gerllaw Parc Cenedlaethol Eryri; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 70078 41951. Mae ganddi boblogaeth o 4,830 (Cyfrifiad 2001). Mae Caerdydd 175.6 km i ffwrdd o Blaenau Ffestiniog ac mae Llundain yn 308.2 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 29 km i ffwrdd.
Roedd y dref yn ganolfan bwysig iawn yn y diwydiant llechi.
Mae'r tir o gwmpas y dref yn rhan o'r parc cenedlaethol, ond dyw'r dref ei hunan ddim - fe'i heithrwyd oherwydd yr olion diwydiannol sy'n amlwg o amgylch y dref. Dywedir ei bod yn bwrw llawer o law yno. Lleolir y Moelwynion yn agos i'r dref, uwchben pentref Tanygrisiau.
Mae'r cylch yn cael ei wasanaethu gan Bapur Bro o'r enw'r Llafar Bro sy'n cael ei gyhoeddi unwaith y mis.
Yn hanesyddol, roedd yn rhan o Sir Feirionydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#boduan">
            <name>Boduan</name>
            <lat>52.911443</lat>
            <lon>-4.4928</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boduan">Boduan is a village in Gwynedd, Wales.
Garn Boduan, a hillfort built soon after Roman occupation, is located in the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boduan">Pentref bychan a phlwyf yn Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Boduan (weithiau: Bodfuan neu'r ffurf hynafiaethol Bodfean); cyfeiriad grid SH323378). Mae'n rhan o gymuned Buan.
Gorwedd Boduan yng nghanol Llŷn ar yr A497, tua hanner ffordd rhwng Pwllheli i'r de-ddwyrain a Nefyn i'r gogledd-orllewin.
Enwir plwyf ac eglwys Boduan ar ôl Sant Buan, un o wyrion Llywarch Hen yn ôl traddodiad; ni wyddom dim arall amdano. Mae'r eglwys bresennol yn dyddio'n ôl i 1760, pan godwyd eglwys newydd ar y safle, a'r 1840au pan atgyweirwyd yr adeilad hwnnw yn drwyadl ar gryn draul, diolch i nawdd y Wynniaid. Mae'n eglwys fawr iawn am bentref mor fychan.
Tua milltir a hanner i'r gogledd-orllewin ceir bryn Garn Boduan a'i fryngaer.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bontddu">
            <name>Bontddu</name>
            <lat>52.749282</lat>
            <lon>-3.973009</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bontddu">Bontddu, Dolgellau, Gwynedd, Wales is a small settlement east of Barmouth.
Local tourism information describes a popular walk in the area of Bontddu:
'follows the 100 metre contour line along the estuary to the East of Borthwnog. Directly behind us walk up into the RSPB (Garth Gell) reserve and on up toward Cwm Mynach and beyond to the wilds of the Harlech Dome. Bear left from the latter path and double back behind the village of Bontddu and join the old drovers track across to Pont Scethin which allegedly was the scene of many highway robberies in the 17th century'.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bontddu">Treflan yn ardal Ardudwy, de Gwynedd, yw Bontddu. Mae'n gorwedd ar lan ogleddol afon Mawddach tua 3 milltir i gyfeiriad y gorllewin o dref Dolgellau. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 67151 18824.
Mae briffordd yr A496 yn rhedeg trwy Bontddu, a enwir ar ôl pont sy'n dwyn y ffordd honno dros afon Cwm Llechen. Mae'r ffordd yn cysylltu Bontddu ag Abermaw i gyfeiriad y gorllewin a Llanelltud, ger Dolgellau, i'r cyfeiriad arall.
Mae lôn gul yn rhedeg i fyny i gyfeiriad bryniau'r Rhinogydd i'r gogledd o'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bontnewydd">
            <name>Bontnewydd</name>
            <lat>53.116002</lat>
            <lon>-4.268163</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bontnewydd">Bontnewydd may refer to:
Bontnewydd, Ceredigion; a village in Ceredigion, Wales
Bontnewydd, Denbighshire; a hamlet in Denbighshire, Wales
Bontnewydd, Gwynedd; a village in Gwynedd, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bontnewydd">Ceir sawl lle o'r enw (Y) Bontnewydd:
Bontnewydd, Arfon, Gwynedd
Bontnewydd, Meirionnydd, Gwynedd
Bontnewydd ar Wy, Powys
Bont-newydd, Ceredigion
Gweler hefyd:
Ogof Bontnewydd, safle archaeolegol yn Sir Ddinbych
Pontnewydd, cymuned sy'n rhan o dref Cwmbrân, Torfaen</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#borth-y-gest">
            <name>Borth-y-Gest</name>
            <lat>52.914931</lat>
            <lon>-4.136272</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borth-y-Gest">This is a redirect from a topic that does not have its own page to a section of a page on the subject. For more information follow the category link.
This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target page. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#botwnnog">
            <name>Botwnnog</name>
            <lat>52.851572</lat>
            <lon>-4.583756</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Botwnnog">Botwnnog is a village and community in Gwynedd in Wales, located on the Llŷn Peninsula. It has a population of 955, increasing to 996 at the 2011 Census.
It lies between Mynytho and Sarn Meyllteyrn, and is the home to two schools, a primary Pont Y Gof Primary School, and secondary Ysgol Botwnnog. It also has the main branch of general practice (GP) medical practice, Meddygfa Rhydbach.
^ "Community/Ward population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015. 
^ Office for National Statistics : Neighbourhood Statistics : Census 2001 : Parish Headcounts : Gwynedd
^ http://www.nhsdirect.wales.nhs.uk/localservices/viewlocalservice.aspx?id=5132</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Botwnnog">Pentref a chymuned ym Mhen Llŷn yw Botwnnog. Saif ar y ffordd B4413, rhwng Mynytho a Sarn Mellteyrn, i'r gogledd-orllewin o Abersoch; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 26250 31201.
Mae yma ysgol uwchradd, Ysgol Botwnnog. Cysegrwyd yr eglwys i Sant Beuno. Adeiladwyd yr eglwys bresennol yn 1887, ond credir fod eglwys wedi bod yna ers y 7fed ganrif. Daw aelodau'r band Cowbois Rhos Botwnnog o'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#braichmelyn">
            <name>Braichmelyn</name>
            <lat>53.173007</lat>
            <lon>-4.05642</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#brithdir">
            <name>Brithdir</name>
            <lat>52.754706</lat>
            <lon>-3.826644</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brithdir">Brithdir is the name of a number of locations in Wales:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brithdir">Gallai Brithdir gyfeirio at:
Pentrefi
Brithdir, Caerffili
Brithdir, Ceredigion
Brithdir, Gwynedd
Caer Rufeinig Brithdir
Ysgol Gynradd Brithdir

Brithdir, Powys - Plasdy ac ardal yng nghymuned Aberriw, Powys
Brithdir a Chwm Mawr - Safle o Ddiddordeb Gwyddonol Arbennig ym Mhowys

Cymuned
Brithdir a Llanfachreth, Gwynedd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bronaber">
            <name>Bronaber</name>
            <lat>52.869623</lat>
            <lon>-3.913996</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bronaber">Bronaber is a village in Gwynedd, Wales, adjacent to the A470 north of Dolgellau and near Trawsfynydd.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bronaber">Pentref bychan yn Ngwynedd yw Bronaber. Saif ar y briffordd A470, ychydig i'r de o bentref Trawsfynydd; Cyfeirnod OS: SH 71076 31631. Llifa afon Eden ychydig i'r gorllewin iddo, ac mae hen ffordd Rufeinig Sarn Helen fymryn i'r dwyrain.
Roedd gwersyll milwrol yma o tua 1906 ymlaen, a defnyddir yr ardal ar gyfer ymarfer tanio. Caewyd ef fel gwersyll milwrol yn 1957-8, ond yna fe'i defnyddiwyd ar gyfer gweithwyr oedd yn adeiladu Atomfa Trawsfynydd. Mae rhan o'r hen wersyll milwrol yn awr yn bentref gwyliau. Gerllaw mae gwesty Rhiw Goch, lle dywedir i'r merthyr Catholig Sant John Roberts gael ei eni.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryn">
            <name>Bryn</name>
            <lat>51.6169859</lat>
            <lon>-3.7123799</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn">Bryn (which is Welsh for hill) is a component ward of the Metropolitan Borough of Wigan, Greater Manchester, England. It is part of the larger town of Ashton-in-Makerfield and is geographically indistinguishable from it. It forms a separate local council ward. Served by Bryn railway station, Bryn is home to the Three Sisters Recreation Area which has been created from three large spoil tips which remain from Bryn's role in Lancashire's coal mining past. The Three Sisters Recreation Area is also the site of the Three Sisters Race Circuit, which provides race driving instruction and plays host to kart racing events and motorcycle road race meetings at clubman level.
The former Bryn (or Brynne) Hall was the seat of the Gerard family beginning in the thirteenth century or earlier. It was a "safe house" for the English Roman Catholic martyr and saint Edmund Arrowsmith and his hand was reportedly preserved there after his execution. The house, dating to the fourteenth century, has now completely collapsed and remaining stones been cleared.
The Unitarian Park Lane Chapel in Wigan Road was built in 1697, though its congregation was founded in 1662. It is the oldest Non-conformist chapel and congregation in the whole district. By the nineteenth century Park Lane was only one of nine non-conformist chapels in the heavily recusant area.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn">Allt neu fynydd bychan yw bryn. Yn ogystal â bod yn elfen gyffredin iawn mewn enwau lleoedd ceir enghreifftiau ohono ar ben ei hun fel enw lle:
Cymru
Bryn (Bannau Brycheiniog); Cyfeirnod grid OS: SO073227
Bryn, Castell-nedd Port Talbot
Bryn, Llanelli
Bryn-y-Gefeiliau
Bryn-crug
Bryn Euryn
Bryn Iwan
Bryn Celli Ddu
Llanfair-ar-y-bryn
Bryn Gwyn
Brynrefail
Bryniau Clwyd
Lloegr
Bryn, Swydd Amwythig
Bryn, Wigan
Cyffredinol
bryngaer
Enw personol Cymraeg ydy Bryn, hefyd. Mae enghreifftiau o nod yn cynnwys:
Bryn Fôn
Bryn Terfel</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryn bwbach">
            <name>Bryn Bwbach</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryn eglwys">
            <name>Bryn Eglwys</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn Eglwys">Bryn Eglwys was a remote slate quarry located near Abergynolwyn in Gwynedd, Wales.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryn-mawr">
            <name>Bryn-mawr</name>
            <lat>52.87231</lat>
            <lon>-4.605495</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn-mawr">Gall Bryn-mawr gyfirio at:
Bryn-mawr, Blaenau Gwent, cymuned ym Mlaenau Gwent
Bryn-mawr (copa), copa mynydd ger y Bala.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryn-y-mor">
            <name>Bryn-y-mor</name>
            <lat>53.1770343</lat>
            <lon>-4.2171257</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryncir">
            <name>Bryncir</name>
            <lat>52.977869</lat>
            <lon>-4.265809</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncir">Mae Bryncir yn bentref yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd (cyfeiriad grid SH4812044837). Saif ar y briffordd A487 rhwng Pant Glas a Dolbenmaen, gyda Garndolbenmaen ychydig i'r de-ddwyrain. Mae gerllaw Afon Dwyfach.

Gellir gweld nifer o hynafiaethau yn yr ardal, yn cynnwys caer Rufeinig ym Mhen Llystyn, lle mae olion y muriau i'w gweld er bod y chwarel raean yno wedi difetha'r tu mewn. Ym mur yr ardd yn ffermdy Llystyn Gwyn, ychydig i'r gogledd o'r pentref mae carreg o'r 6ed ganrif gydag arysgrif mewn Lladin ac Ogam. Yn y Lladin mae'n darllen ICORI(X) FILIUS / POTENT / INI (Icorix, mab Potentinus). Mae cerrig dwyieithog, Lladin ac Ogam, yn gyffredin yn ne-orllewin Cymru, ond dyma'r unig un yn y gogledd-orllewin.
Mae Bryncir yn bentref prysur, gyda canolfan arddio, tafarnau a siopau, ac yn enwedig y farchnad anifeiliad sy'n denu ffermwyr o gryn bellter. Er gwaethaf yr enw, mae Ffatri Wlân Bryncir gryn bellter i'r de-ddwyrain, gerllaw Golan.
Mae llwybr Cenedlaethol Lôn Las Cymru yn rhedeg drwy'r pentre, ac yma dechreuir adran Lôn Eifion, ar lwybr y rheilffordd Caernarfon-Afonwen.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryncroes">
            <name>Bryncroes</name>
            <lat>52.851563</lat>
            <lon>-4.634877</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncroes">Bryncroes is a hamlet and former civil parish in Gwynedd in Wales, and lies on the Llŷn Peninsula approximately 2 km west of Sarn Mellteyrn. The parish was abolished in 1934 and divided between Botwnnog and Aberdaron. The village was the scene of fierce protests between 1969 and 1972 when it was proposed to close the village school. However, the protests were in vain and the school closed, and is now a village community centre.
Near the school is a well, which was used as a stopping-off point of the pilgrims on their way to Bardsey Island (Welsh: Ynys Enlli).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncroes">Pentref bychan ym Mhen Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Bryncroes. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 22698 31465. Fe'i lleolir tua 5 milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Aberdaron.
I'r de cyfyd Mynydd Rhiw (305m). Y pentrefi agosaf yw Sarn Mellteyrn, filltir i'r gogledd, a Botwnnog, 2 filltir a hanner i'r dwyrain.
Ceir ffynnon sanctaidd hynafol o'r enw Ffynnon Fair ger yr eglwys. Ceir llecyn o'r enw Mynachdy gerllaw, sy'n awgrymu ei fod yn perthyn i'r clas enwog ar Ynys Enlli ar un adeg. Ar lethrau Mynydd Rhiw ceir caer gynhanesyddol Castell Caeron.
Bu gan y pentref ysgol ond fe'i caewyd er gwaethaf protestiadau yn erbyn y penderfyniad ac mae'r adeilad yn cael ei ddefnyddio fel canolfan gymuned y pentref erbyn hyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bryncrug">
            <name>Bryncrug</name>
            <lat>52.610784</lat>
            <lon>-4.061369</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryncrug">Bryncrug, sometimes spelt Bryn-crug, is a village and community in Gwynedd, Wales. Afon Fathew flows through the village and into the River Dysynni The village is situated to the north east of the town of Tywyn, at the junction of the A493 and B4405 roads. Although the village is usually spelt Bryncrug in English, the community name uses the Welsh language version, Bryn-crug. The population of the community taken at the 2011 census was 622.
To the south west of the village stood Ynysymaengwyn, a mansion built in 1758 but now demolished. To the south stood Cynfal motte-and-bailey castle, built in 1137 by Cadwaladr ap Gruffydd, brother of Owain Gwynedd.
The poet David Richards (1751-1827), better known as Dafydd Ionawr, was born at Glanyrafon near Bryncrug.
Mary Jones, famous for walking to Bala at the age of sixteen to buy a Bible, lived in the village when older, and was buried in the village after her death in 1864.
The football club, Tywyn &amp; Bryncrug FC (Welsh language: Clwb Pel-droed Tywyn a Bryncrug), play their home matches in the village.
^ "Key Figures for 2011 Census: Key Statistics: Bryn-crug". Neighbourhood Statistics. Office for National Statistics. Retrieved 22 March 2013. 
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015. 
^ "Castell Cynfal, Bryn-Y-Castell Castle mound". Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Wales. Retrieved 1 February 2009. 
^ "Bala and the Bible: Thomas Charles, Ann Griffiths and Mary Jones". Cardiff University. Retrieved 1 February 2009.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#brynglas sta">
            <name>Brynglas Sta</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#brynrefail">
            <name>Brynrefail</name>
            <lat>53.141036</lat>
            <lon>-4.1549319</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynrefail">Brynrefail is a small village in north-east Anglesey, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynrefail">Gall Brynrefail (bryn + gefail) gyfeirio at:
Brynrefail, pentref yng Ngwynedd gerllaw Llanberis.
Brynrefail, pentref bychan yng ngogledd-ddwyrain Ynys Môn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bwlch">
            <name>Bwlch</name>
            <lat>51.8910259</lat>
            <lon>-3.240574</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bwlch">Bwlch (meaning a 'pass' in Welsh) is a small village in Powys, southern Wales. The settlement is strung out along the A40 road which crosses a low col above the Usk Valley at this point on its route between Brecon and Crickhowell. The village is a part of the administrative community of 'Llanfihangel Cwmdu with Bwlch and Cathedine'.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bwlch">Am y pentref ym Mhowys, gweler Bwlch, Powys.
Bwlch yw rhywle lle gellir tramwyo rhwng rhywbeth. Gall fod rhwng dau fynydd, neu ddwy ochr o gwm neu hyd yn oed lle gwag mewn clawdd. Ceir yr enw ar sawl enw lle.
Mae un pentre o'r enw Bwlch rhwng Aberhonddu a'r Fenni. Hefyd Tan y Bwlch yng Ngwynedd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bwlch-derwin">
            <name>Bwlch-derwin</name>
            <lat>52.99847</lat>
            <lon>-4.297784</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bwlchtocyn">
            <name>Bwlchtocyn</name>
            <lat>52.805196</lat>
            <lon>-4.506746</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bwlchtocyn">Pentref bychan yn ne-orllewin penrhyn Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Bwlchtocyn (cyfeiriad grid SH308262). Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanengan.
Gorwedd y pentref tua milltir i'r de-ddwyrain o bentref Llanengan a thua milltir a hanner i'r de o Abersoch. I'r gorllewin ceir Mynydd Cilan ym mhen dwyreiniol Porth Neigwl. Fymryn i'r dwyrain o Fwlchtocyn ceir pentref bychan Marchros lle ceir Porth Tocyn. I'r de o'r pentref ceir bae Porth Ceiriad.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#bwlchyllyn">
            <name>Bwlchyllyn</name>
            <lat>53.0728312</lat>
            <lon>-4.2318139</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cadair">
            <name>Cadair</name>
            <lat>52.6993814</lat>
            <lon>-3.9080548</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadair">Gallai'r gair cadair gyfeirio at sawl peth:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cadair idris">
            <name>Cadair Idris</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadair Idris">Cadair Idris or Cader Idris is a mountain in Gwynedd, Wales, which lies at the southern end of the Snowdonia National Park near the town of Dolgellau. The peak, which is one of the most popular in Wales for walkers and hikers, is composed largely of Ordovician igneous rocks, with classic glacial erosion features such as cwms, moraines, striated rocks, and roches moutonnées.
^ "Cadair Idris". SnowdoniaGuide.com. Retrieved October 31, 2006.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadair Idris">Un o fynyddoedd enwog gogledd Cymru yw Cadair Idris (neu Cader Idris ). Fe'i lleolir ym Meirionnydd, de Gwynedd, ger Dolgellau, ym mhen deheuol Parc Cenedlaethol Eryri.
Mae ganddo bedwar copa sef Geugraig, yna tua'r gorllewin Mynydd Moel, wedyn Pen y Gadair ei hun ac (sef y fam-gopa) yna'r Cyfrwy a'r Tyrau Mawr yn ymestyn i'r dwyrain tua'r môr. Mae Pen y Gadair 893 metr uwch ben lefel y môr.
Mae cwt cysgodi ar gopa Pen y Gadair, ac yn ôl hen dradoddiad, bydd pob un a gwsg ar y mynydd, yn deffro naill ai fel bardd neu fel gwallgofddyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cae clyd">
            <name>Cae Clyd</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#caeathro">
            <name>Caeathro</name>
            <lat>53.130937</lat>
            <lon>-4.240614</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caeathro">Caeathro is a village situated on the A4085 road between Caernarfon and Waunfawr in Gwynedd, northwest Wales. It is approximately 2 km from Caernarfon and 1.5 km from Waunfawr. It is part of Waunfawr community</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caeathro">Pentref yn Arfon, Gwynedd yw Caeathro, ar yr A4085 rhwng Caernarfon a Waunfawr, tua 1.17 milltir o Gaernarfon a 0.72 milltir o Waunfawr. Mae tafarn, gorsaf betrol a maes carafanau yno.
Ganwyd y nofelydd Emily Huws yng Nghaeathro.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#caerdeon">
            <name>Caerdeon</name>
            <lat>52.743193</lat>
            <lon>-4.001533</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#caerhun">
            <name>Caerhun</name>
            <lat>53.217094</lat>
            <lon>-3.838875</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerhun">Caerhun (Welsh: Caerhûn) is a scattered rural community, and former civil parish, on the west bank of the River Conwy. It lies to the south of Henryd and the north of Dolgarrog, in Conwy County Borough, Wales, and includes the villages of Llanbedr-y-cennin, Rowen, Tal-y-bont and Ty'n-y-groes. At the 2001 census, it had a population of 1,200, increasing to 1,292 at the 2011 census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerhun">Pentref bychan a chymuned yn Sir Conwy yw Caerhun, sy'n adnabyddus am safle caer Rufeinig Canovium. Er nad yw'r pentref ei hun yn fawr, mae'r gymuned yn ymestyn o lan Afon Conwy hyd at brif grib y Carneddau yn Eryri ac yn cynnwys sawl mynydd a heneb. Yn 2011 roedd 1,292 o bobl yn byw yn y gymuned (gweler isod).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#caernarfon">
            <name>Caernarfon</name>
            <lat>53.139551</lat>
            <lon>-4.273911</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caernarfon">Caernarfon (/kərˈnɑrvən/; Welsh: [kaɨrˈnarvɔn]) is a royal town, community and port in Gwynedd, Wales, with a population of 9,615; this figure does not include nearby Bontnewydd or Caeathro as they are in separate communities. It lies along the A487 road, on the eastern shore of the Menai Strait, opposite the Isle of Anglesey. The city of Bangor is 8.6 miles (13.8 km) to the north-east, while Snowdonia fringes Caernarfon to the east and south-east. Carnarvon and Caernarvon are Anglicised spellings that were superseded in 1926 and 1974 respectively.
Abundant natural resources in and around the Menai Straits enabled human habitation in the area during prehistory. The Ordovices, a Celtic tribe, lived in the region during classical antiquity. The Roman fort Segontium was established around AD 80 to subjugate the Ordovices during the Roman conquest of Britain. The Romans and occupied the region until their departure in the 5th century, after which Caernarfon became part of the Kingdom of Gwynedd. In the late 11th century, William the Conqueror ordered the construction of a motte at Caernarfon, as part of an attempt at conquering the region. He was unsuccessful and most of Wales remained independent until around 1283.
In the 13th century, Llywelyn ap Gruffudd, ruler of Gwynedd, refused to pay homage to Edward I prompting the English conquest of Gwynedd. This was followed by the construction of Caernarfon Castle, one of the largest and most imposing fortifications built by the English in Wales. In 1284, the English-style county of Caernarfonshire was established by the Statute of Rhuddlan; the same year, Caernarfon was made a borough, a county and market town, and the seat of English government in North Wales.
The ascent of the Tudor dynasty to the throne of England eased hostilities between the English and resulted in Caernarfon Castle falling into a state of disrepair. The city has flourished, leading to its status as a major tourist centre and seat of Gwynedd Council, with a thriving harbour and marina. Caernarfon has expanded beyond its medieval walls and experienced heavy suburbanisation. Its population includes the largest percentage of Welsh-speaking citizens anywhere in Wales. The status of Royal Borough was granted by Queen Elizabeth II in 1963 and emended to Royal Town in 1974.
^ "Town population 2011". Retrieved 15 May 2015. 
^ "Caernarfon Castle". Castlewales.com. Retrieved 2012-09-29. 
^ Gareth Edwards. "Caernarfon Tourist Information". Visitcaernarfon.com. Retrieved 2012-09-29. 
^ "BBC News - How does a town get a 'royal' title?". Bbc.co.uk. 2011-03-17. Retrieved 2012-09-29.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caernarfon">Mae Caernarfon yn dref yng Ngwynedd, yng ngogledd-orllewin Cymru. Mae'n enwog yn bennaf oherwydd Castell Caernarfon, sy'n gastell mawr o feini a godwyd gan Edward I o Loegr. Daw enw'r dref o gaer gynharach, sef Segontium, y gaer Rufeinig sydd ar dir uwch ar gyrion y dref. Y gaer hon a roddodd yr enw "Caer Seiont yn Arfon" neu "Caer Saint yn Arfon", a ddaeth yn ddiweddarach yn Gaernarfon. Mae gan y dref boblogaeth o 9,611 gyda 81.6% yn siaradwyr Cymraeg (97.7% yn yr oedran 10-14), yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2001. "Cofi" y gelwir rhywun a aned yn y dre.
Mae Caerdydd 198.7 km i ffwrdd o Gaernarfon ac mae Llundain yn 335.9 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 12.7 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#capel uchaf">
            <name>Capel Uchaf</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capel Uchaf">Pentref gwledig ym Mrycheiniog, de Powys, yw Capel Uchaf. Mae'n gorwedd wrth lethrau deheuol Mynydd Epynt ar lan afon Honddu, un o ledneintiau pwysicaf afon Wysg.
Lleolir y pentref ar bwys lôn wledig sy'n dringo i gyfeiriad Epynt o Aberhonddu, tua 7 milltir i'r de. Fymryn i'r gogledd o'r pentref mae'r lôn yn fforcio, gydag un ffordd yn mynd i lawr i'r A483 ger Llangamarch a'r brif lôn yn mynd yn ei blaen i Llanfair-ym-Muallt. Y pentrefi cyfagos yw Merthyr Cynog, a gysylltir â'r pentref gan lôn sy'n dringo dros y bryn i'r gorllewin, a Chastell Madog, Capel Isaf, Pwllgloyw, a Llandefaelog Fach i'r de, ar y lôn i Aberhonddu. I'r gogledd ceir Pentref Dolau Honddu.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#capel-y-graig">
            <name>Capel-y-graig</name>
            <lat>53.203535</lat>
            <lon>-4.174346</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#carmel">
            <name>Carmel</name>
            <lat>53.281435</lat>
            <lon>-3.241424</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel">Carmel in the Bible refers to two distinct places:
Mount Carmel, coastal mountain range in Israel overlooking the Mediterranean Sea
Carmel (biblical settlement), an ancient Israelite town in Judea
The word Carmel (Hebrew language: כַּרְמֶל) means "fresh" (planted), or "vineyard" (planted) and Karmiel (Hebrew: כַּרְמִיאֵל) is a portmanteau meaning "God's Vineyard".
In modern times, the name was also given to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmel">Gallai Carmel gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#carnedd dafydd">
            <name>Carnedd Dafydd</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnedd Dafydd">Carnedd Dafydd is a mountain peak in the Carneddau range in Snowdonia, North Wales, and is the third highest peak in Wales, or the fourth if Crib y Ddysgl on the Snowdon ridge is counted. Situated south-west of Carnedd Llewelyn and north of Pen yr Ole Wen, Carnedd Dafydd is on the main ridge of the Carneddau, and on the border between Gwynedd and Conwy. The average annual temperature of the mountain is around 3-4 °C.
Carnedd Dafydd rises to height of 1,044m (according to OS maps detail) and is usually climbed by first ascending Pen yr Ole Wen and then following the ridge along to Carnedd Dafydd, though it is also possible to make a direct ascent from Tal y Llyn Ogwen, first following the stream, Afon Lloer, to the mountain lake of Ffynnon Lloer then climbing up the slope to the summit.
Like most of the summits in the southern Carneddau, it has a flat, boulder-strewn summit plateau. Immediately to the north lie the crags of Ysgolion Duon, well-known to climbers.
The origin of its name, which translates as Dafydd's (or David's) cairn, like that of its neighbouring peak, Carnedd Llewelyn (Llywelyn's cairn), are named after Llywelyn ap Gruffudd, the last independent prince of Wales, and his younger brother, Dafydd ap Gruffudd. The nearby peak Carnedd Lladron, commonly known as Carnedd Uchaf, has now been renamed by O.S. Carnedd Gwenllian in memory of Llywelyn's daughter Lady Gwenllian. Dafydd was captured at Nanhysglain, near Bera, on 21 June 1283; taken to Shrewsbury where he was hanged, drawn and quartered.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnedd Dafydd">Mae Carnedd Dafydd yn fynydd yn y Carneddau yn Eryri. Mae rhyw 20m yn is na'r mynydd uchaf yn y Carneddau, Carnedd Llywelyn, ond dim ond y mynydd hwnnw a'r Wyddfa sy'n uwch nag ef yng Nghymru (os na ystyrir Carnedd Ugain/Crib y Ddysgl ar yr Wyddfa yn fynydd ar wahan). Saif ar brif grib y Carneddau, gyda Carnedd Llywelyn i'r gogledd-ddwyrain a Pen yr Ole Wen i'r de. Mae'r ffin rhwng Gwynedd a sir Conwy yn mynd tros y copa. Ar ochr ogleddol y grib rhwng Carnedd Dafydd a Charnedd Llywelyn mae creigiau Ysgolion Duon, sy'n ffefrynnau gan ddringwyr.

Mae modd dringo'r mynydd yn uniongyrchol trwy gychwyn gerllaw Tal-y-llyn Ogwen ger pen dwyreiniol Llyn Ogwen a dilyn Afon Lloer hyd at lyn Ffynnon Lloer sydd wrth droed Carnedd Dafydd. Yna gellir dringo i fyny'r llechweddau i'r copa. Y ffordd arferol o'i ddringo, fodd bynnag, yw dringo Pen yr Ole Wen gyntaf, ac yna mae'n hawdd dilyn y grib i gopa Carnedd Dafydd.
Nid oes sicrwydd pa un o ddau Ddafydd sy'n cael ei goffáu gan yr enw, Dafydd ap Llywelyn, mab Llywelyn Fawr, ynteu Dafydd ap Gruffudd, brawd Llywelyn ap Gruffudd. Dywed Terry Marsh nad oes amheuaeth nad Dafydd ap Llywelyn a roddodd ei enw i'r mynydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#carnedd llewelyn">
            <name>Carnedd Llewelyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnedd Llewelyn">Carnedd Llewelyn, usually spelt Carnedd Llywelyn in Welsh, is a mountain massif in the Carneddau range in Snowdonia, north-west Wales. It is the highest point of the Carneddau and the second highest peak by relative height in Wales, 49th in the British Isles and lies on the border between Gwynedd and Conwy.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#carreg ddu">
            <name>Carreg Ddu</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#carreg y garth">
            <name>Carreg y Garth</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cefn-ddwysarn">
            <name>Cefn-ddwysarn</name>
            <lat>52.935588</lat>
            <lon>-3.539398</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#ceunant">
            <name>Ceunant</name>
            <lat>53.127516</lat>
            <lon>-4.198994</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#chwilog">
            <name>Chwilog</name>
            <lat>52.919911</lat>
            <lon>-4.330451</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chwilog">Chwilog is a village in Eifionydd on the Llŷn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It forms part of the community of Llanystumdwy. The name means 'abounding in beetles' and was perhaps transferred from an earlier name of the river (or a part of it).
The village is fairly linear, built up around the B4354 which crosses the peninsula to Boduan. The Afon Wen flows through the lower part of the village on its way to the sea at Afonwen, less than 1 mile (1.6 km) away.
Nearby is Lôn Goed, a wide tree-lined avenue created in the 18th century for transporting lime from the coast to the upland farms of Eifionydd. The track is no longer used for this purpose but is now popular with walkers.
Talhenbont Hall is a Grade II listed manor house. It was built in 1607 was once the home of William Vaughan. In 1642, the owner William Lloyd was arrested as a Royalist sympathiser as Cromwell’s men took over the Hall. In 1758 Talhenbont was the largest single owned piece of land in the district of Eifionydd. The estate was occupied by Sir Thomas Mostyn, the sixth baronet, from 1796. In 1884 the estate was split into sections to pay off debts that had crept up during the Napoleonic Wars. It is now operated as a holiday centre. 
^ Owen, H.W. &amp; Morgan, R. 2007 Dictionary of the Place-names of Wales Gomer Press, Ceredigion
^ "Talhenbont Hall".</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chwilog">Mae Chwilog yn bentref bach yng ngorllewin Eifionydd, yng Ngwynedd, rhwng Pwllheli a Llanystumdwy. Saif ar lan Afon Wen, sy'n rhedeg i Fae Tremadog filltir islaw'r pentref. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanystumdwy.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cilgwyn">
            <name>Cilgwyn</name>
            <lat>51.99125</lat>
            <lon>-4.805601</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#clwt-y-bont">
            <name>Clwt-y-bont</name>
            <lat>53.145176</lat>
            <lon>-4.132769</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#clynnog-fawr">
            <name>Clynnog-fawr</name>
            <lat>53.020583</lat>
            <lon>-4.364979</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#clywedog">
            <name>Clywedog</name>
            <lat>53.0361706</lat>
            <lon>-2.94065</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clywedog">Clywedog may refer to:
Afon Clywedog - a tributary of the River Severn at Llanidloes
River Clywedog, a tributary of River Dee near Wrexham
A tributary of the River Mawddach in Gwynedd
Clywedog Reservoir, a reservoir in Powys
River Clywedog, Denbigh, a tributary of the River Clwyd
Clywedog Brook, Powys, a tributary of the Wye.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#coed mawr">
            <name>Coed Mawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coed Mawr">Mae Coed Mawr yn gopa mynydd a geir ym Mhumlumon rhwng Aberystwyth a'r Trallwng; cyfeiriad grid SO013874. Uchder cymharol, neu ”amlygrwydd” y copa, ydy 183metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
Dosberthir copaon Cymru, a gweddill gwledydd Prydain, yn rhestri arbennig yn ôl uchder ac yn ôl amlygrwydd y copa; mae'r copa hwn yn cael ei alw'n HuMP. Mae sawl cymdeithas yn mesur, gwiro a chasglu'r rhestri hyn a dônt ynghŷd ar wefan “Database of British and Irish hills”. Uchder y copa o lefel y môr ydy 308m (1010tr). Cafodd yr uchder ei fesur a'i gadarnhau ddiwethaf ar 28 Mawrth 2010.
↑ “Database of British and Irish hills”</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#coed ystumgwern">
            <name>Coed Ystumgwern</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#coed-y-parc">
            <name>Coed-y-parc</name>
            <lat>53.1752536</lat>
            <lon>-4.07104</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#colwyn">
            <name>Colwyn</name>
            <lat>52.5118198</lat>
            <lon>-3.3075764</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colwyn">The Borough of Colwyn was one of six districts of the county of Clwyd, north-east Wales, from 1974 to 1996.
It was formed under the Local Government Act 1972 from the following parts of the administrative county of Denbighshire:
The municipal borough of Colwyn Bay
The urban district of Abergele
Parts of the rural districts of Aled and Hiraethog.
The borough was abolished in 1996, when wales was divided into unitary authorities created by the Local Government (Wales) Act 1994. The area of Colwyn was split: a large part going to Aberconwy and Colwyn county borough, (soon renamed as Conwy), and the remainder going to Denbighshire unitary authority.
Colwyn is currently an electoral ward. It consists in part the Community of Old Colwyn with a total population of 4,566
Colwyn is twinned with Konstanz, Germany and Roissy-en-Brie, France.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colwyn">Gallai Colwyn gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Ci
Colwyn, ci bach, cenau; hefyd ci mynwes (lapdog)
Afonydd
Afon/Nant Colwyn: Enw ar sawl afon fechan a nant yng Nghymru, yn cynnwys
Afon Colwyn, Gwynedd

Ardal Bae Colwyn
Bae Colwyn, tref yn Sir Conwy
C.P.D. Bae Colwyn
Theatr Colwyn, theatr ym Mae Colwyn

Hen Golwyn, pentref ar gyrion Bae Colwyn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#congl-y-wal">
            <name>Congl-y-wal</name>
            <lat>52.981461</lat>
            <lon>-3.929986</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#conwy">
            <name>Conwy</name>
            <lat>53.282872</lat>
            <lon>-3.82948</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conwy">Conwy (Welsh pronunciation: [ˈkɔnʊɨ]; English Conway) is a walled market town and community in Conwy County Borough on the north coast of Wales. The town, which faces Deganwy across the River Conwy, formerly lay in Gwynedd and prior to that in Caernarfonshire. The community, which includes Deganwy and Llandudno Junction, had a population of 14,208 at the 2001 census, and is a popular tourist destination. The population rose to 14,753 at the 2011 census. The Welsh language can still be heard in widespread, casual and official usage.

Conwy Castle and the town walls were built, on the instruction of Edward I of England, between 1283 and 1289, as part of his conquest of the principality of Wales. Conwy was the original site of Aberconwy Abbey, founded by Llywelyn the Great. Edward and his troops took over the abbey site and moved the monks down the Conwy valley to a new site at Maenan, establishing Maenan Abbey. The parish church still retains some parts of the original abbey church in the east and west walls. English settlers were given incentives to move to the walled garrison town, which for decades the Welsh were forbidden from entering.
Across the estuary is Bodysgallen Hall, which incorporates a medieval watchtower that was later used as a signal place for Conwy Castle.
Conwy has other tourist attractions that help draw visitors to the town. Conwy Suspension Bridge, designed by Thomas Telford to replace the ferry, was completed in 1826 and spans the River Conwy next to the castle. Telford designed the bridge's supporting towers to match the castle's turrets. The bridge is now open to pedestrians only and, together with the toll-keeper's house, is in the care of the National Trust.
The Conwy Railway Bridge, a Tubular bridge, was built for the Chester and Holyhead Railway by Robert Stephenson in 1849. The bridge is still in use on the North Wales Coast Line, along with station, which is located within the town walls. In addition to a modern bridge serving the town, the A55 road passes under the river by a tunnel which was built between 1986 and 1991. The old mountain road to Dwygyfylchi and Penmaenmawr runs through the Sychnant Pass, at the foot of Conwy Mountain.

The National Trust also owns Aberconwy House, which is Conwy's only surviving 14th-century merchant's house, one of the first buildings built inside the walls of Conwy. Another fine house open to the public is Plas Mawr, an Elizabethan house built in 1576 by the Wynn family, which has been extensively refurbished to its original 16th-century appearance and is now in the care of Cadw.
The church standing in Conwy, has been marked as the oldest building in Conwy and has stood in the walls of Conwy since the 14th century. However, the oldest structure is part of the town walls, at the southern end of the east side. Here one wall and the tower of Llewellyn the Great's Llys [court house] have been incorporated into the wall. Built on a rocky outcrop, with an aspidal tower, it is a classic, native, Welsh build and stands out from the rest of the town walls, due to the presence of 4 window openings. It dates from the early 13th century and is the most complete remnant of any of his Llys.

The house named in the Guinness Book of Records as The Smallest House in Great Britain, with dimensions of 3.05 metres x 1.8 metres, can be found on the quay. It was in continuous occupation from the 16th century (and was even inhabited by a family at one point) until 1900 when the owner (a 6 ft fisherman – Robert Jones) was forced to move out on the grounds of hygiene. The rooms were too small for him to stand up in fully. The house is still owned by his descendants today, and you can go on a tour around it for a small charge.
Conwy Morfa, a marshy spit of land on the west side of the estuary, was probably the location where golf was first played on Welsh soil. It was also the place where Hugh Iorys Hughes developed, and later built, the floating Mulberry Harbour, used in Operation Overlord in World War II.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#corris">
            <name>Corris</name>
            <lat>52.653861</lat>
            <lon>-3.839825</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corris">Corris is a village and community in the south of Snowdonia in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies in the historic county of Merionethshire/Sir Feirionnydd. Although the Snowdonia National Park covers much of the area around Corris, the village is not within the park.
The name is possibly derived from the English word "quarries", and the extensive slate quarries that surround the village are its most prominent historical feature. However, The Place Names of Wales (published Newport, 1912) states : "We find the forms Corys and Corus in the Cambrian Register for 1795. Some think the place takes its name from a saint called Corus. It is also said that Cunedda Wedig had a son called Coras. Others think that the river which gives the place its name, was called Corus from its making round excavations in the angles of its banks." The name Corris is also shared with a small river in Denbighshire, a tributary of the Clywedog which in turn flows into the river Clwyd. It is extremely unlikely that the name Corris is a derivation from the English word 'quarry'. Both the Meirionydd and Denbigh Corris predate the rise of the slate industry.
The population of Corris community was 723 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corris">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Gwynedd yw Corris. Credir mai tarddiad Saesneg sydd i'r enw, o quarries. Ar un adeg gelwid y pentref yn Abercorris (Abercorys ar rai mapiau cynnar). Roedd y pentref ar yr hen ffordd dyrpeg o Ddolgellau i Fachynlleth; mae priffordd yr A487 a gymerodd ei lle yn osgoi canol y pentref.
Saif Corris ar lan orllewinol Afon Dulas, sy'n ffin rhwng Gwynedd a Phowys yma. Mae Afon Deri yn llifo trwy'r pentref ei hun cyn ymuno ag Afon Dulas. Yn ôl pob tebyg yr oedd ffordd Rufeinig Sarn Helen hefyd yn rhedeg trwy'r pentref. Ceir yma sawl tafarn gan gynnwys "Tafarn y Chwarelwr".
Ar un adeg yr oedd nifer o chwareli llechi yma. a defnyddid Rheilffordd Corris i gludo'r llechi i Fachynlleth ac ymlaen at Afon Dyfi i'w llwytho i gychod o'r cei yn Derwenlas neu Morben. Mae rhan o'r hen reilffordd wedi ei hail-agor: o Gorris i Gyffordd Maespoeth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#corris uchaf">
            <name>Corris Uchaf</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corris Uchaf">Corris Uchaf (English: Upper Corris), locally known as Top Corris, is a village lying in the south of the Snowdonia National Park in Gwynedd, Wales. The name is believed to be derived from the English word "quarries", and the extensive slate quarries that surround the village are its most prominent historical feature.
The village lies in the valley of the Afon Deri, and is threaded by the A487 road, a trunk road between Dolgellau and Machynlleth. To the south the Deri runs into the Afon Dulas in the neighbouring village of Corris.
Among the quarries that once thrived around the village are Abercwmmeiddaw and Abercorris (also known as Cwmodyn) on the east bank of the river, and Gaewern and Braichgoch on the western slopes of the valley.
A narrow-gauge horse-drawn tramway carried slate in waggons from the quarries to Maespoeth Junction, where they joined the main line of the narrow gauge Corris Railway which took them onward to Machynlleth.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#criccieth">
            <name>Criccieth</name>
            <lat>52.919565</lat>
            <lon>-4.233645</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criccieth">Criccieth (Welsh: Cricieth [ˈkrɪkjɛθ]) is a town and community on Cardigan Bay, in the Eifionydd area of Gwynedd in Wales. The town lies 5 miles (8 km) west of Porthmadog, 9 miles (14 km) east of Pwllheli and 17 miles (27 km) south of Caernarfon. It has a population of 1,826, reducing to 1,753 at the 2011 census.
The town is a seaside resort, popular with families. Attractions include the ruins of Criccieth Castle, which have extensive views over the town and surrounding countryside. Nearby on Ffordd Castell is Cadwalader's Ice Cream Parlour, opened in 1927, whilst Stryd Fawr has several bistro style restaurants. In the centre lies Y Maes, part of the original medieval town common.
The town is noted for its fairs, held on 23 May and 29 June every year, when large numbers of people visit the fairground itself and the market which spreads through many of the streets of the town.
Famous people associated with the town include the British prime minister, David Lloyd George, who grew up in the nearby village of Llanystumdwy, and poet William George. Group Captain Leslie Bonnet, RAF officer, writer and originator of the Welsh Harlequin Duck and his wife Joan Hutt, artist both lived at Ymwlch just outside Criccieth from 1949 until their deaths in 1985.
Criccieth hosted the National Eisteddfod in 1975 and in 2003 was granted Fairtrade Town status. It won the Wales in Bloom competition each year from 1999 to 2004.
The town styles itself The Pearl of Wales on the Shores of Snowdonia.
^ Census 2001
^ "Town/electoral ward population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015. 
^ a b Visit Wales : Criccieth Accommodation
^ Cadw : Criccieth Castle
^ Cadwalader's Ice Cream : About Us
^ Eira and James Gleasure, Criccieth : A Heritage Walk, 2003, Cymdeithas Hanes Eifionydd, Wales, 28 pages
^ Criccieth Business and Shop Alert : Criccieth Fair Days
^ British Broadcasting Corporation : Lloyd George Nephew Dies Aged 94
^ "Leslie Bonnet", by Frank Dancaster. THE OLD LADY, June 1986.
^ "Obituary:Mrs J.V. Hutt. Caernarfon and Denbigh Herald, 1 February 1985.
^ Eisteddfod Genedlaethol Cymru : Eisteddfod Locations
^ Fairtrade Foundation : Fairtrade Towns
^ Criccieth in Bloom : Trophies
^ Criccieth Business and Shop Alert : Croeso</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#croesor">
            <name>Croesor</name>
            <lat>52.981436</lat>
            <lon>-4.039413</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croesor">Croesor is a small village in Gwynedd, Wales.
Croesor is located at the foot of Cnicht, in Cwm Croesor, in the community of Llanfrothen. The Croesor Tramway travelled along the bed of the cwm, before rising steeply to Bwlch Rhosydd via Croesor Incline.
To the south of the village is the site of Parc, which was the ancient estate of the Anwyl Family, with a claim to be the direct descendants in the male line of Owain Gwynedd, prince of Gwynedd.
Croesor is a Welsh speaking village, where the language is used every day.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croesor">Mae Croesor yn bentref bychan yng Nghwm Croesor wrth droed Cnicht a'r Moelwyn Mawr yng Ngwynedd. Mae'r boblogaeth tua 105. Mae yno un capel ac ysgol gynradd, ond dim siop. Gellir cyrraedd yno ar hyd dwy ffordd fechan o ardal Llanfrothen. Yn y 18fed ganrif roedd ffordd dyrpeg yn cysylltu Tan y Bwlch â Nantmor yn mynd trwy'r pentref.
Datblygodd y pentref gyda thŵf y chwareli llechi yn y 19eg ganrif. Mae sawl chwarel yn y cylch, yn enwedig Chwarel Croesor a Chwarel Rhosydd. Agorwyd Chwarel Croesor yn 1856 a daeth yn eithaf llewyrchus dan reolaeth Moses Kellow o gwmpas troad y ganrif. Adeiladwyd trac tram i ddod a'r llechi i lawr o'r chwarel. Datblygwyd y pentref gan Hugh Beaver Roberts, perchennog stâd Croesor.
Efallai fod y pentref yn fwyaf enwog fel cartref Bob Owen, Croesor y casglwr llyfrau ac ysgolhaig.
Agorwyd Ysgol Gynradd Croesor ym 1873, a caewyd yn 2008 oherwydd diffyg disgyblion.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#croesywaun">
            <name>Croesywaun</name>
            <lat>53.112999</lat>
            <lon>-4.20986</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cutiau">
            <name>Cutiau</name>
            <lat>52.736415</lat>
            <lon>-4.024459</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cutiau">Mae Cutiau wedi'i ddynodi'n Safle o Ddiddordeb Gwyddonol Arbennig yng Nghymru (SoDdGA neu SSSI) ers 18 Gorffennaf 1986 fel ymgais gadwraethol i amddiffyn a gwarchod y safle. Mae ei arwynebedd yn 9.93 hectar. Cyfoeth Naturiol Cymru yw'r corff sy'n gyfrifol am y safle.
↑ Gwefan Cyngor Cefn Gwlad Cymru (bellach 'Cyfoeth Naturiol Cymru'); adalwyd 25 Rhagfyr 2013</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cwm-cewydd">
            <name>Cwm-Cewydd</name>
            <lat>52.7046629</lat>
            <lon>-3.667912</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cwm-mynach">
            <name>Cwm-mynach</name>
            <lat>52.1399585</lat>
            <lon>-4.1430015</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cwm-y-glo">
            <name>Cwm-y-glo</name>
            <lat>53.139639</lat>
            <lon>-4.1667189</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwm-y-glo">Pentref yng Ngwynedd yw Cwm-y-glo, hefyd Cwm y Glo. Saif fymryn oddi ar ar y briffordd A4086 gerllaw cyffordd y ffordd honno a'r A4244, yn agos at ben gogleddol Llyn Padarn, lle mae Afon Rhythallt yn gadael y llyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#cwrt">
            <name>Cwrt</name>
            <lat>52.583913</lat>
            <lon>-3.934182</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dee">
            <name>Dee</name>
            <lat>53.3157488</lat>
            <lon>-3.186886</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dee">Dee might refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dee">Gallai Dee gyfeirio at:
Dr John Dee, ysgolhaig Seisnig o dras Cymraeg
Enw Saesneg ar Afon Dyfrdwy
Afon Dee, enw nifer o afonydd yn yr Alban a Lloegr. Yr enwocaf yw Afon Dee (Swydd Aberdeen)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#deiniolen">
            <name>Deiniolen</name>
            <lat>53.148079</lat>
            <lon>-4.130075</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deiniolen">Deiniolen is a village in Gwynedd, Wales, at the foot of Elidir Fawr. Deiniolen has views over Caernarfon (7 miles away) and on a clear day, Holyhead Mountain and occasionally the Wicklow Mountains in Ireland, can be seen. The population of the electoral ward was 1,909 as of 2011, including nearby Dinorwig.
The slate industry was an important employer in Deiniolen, but since the closure of the quarry in 1969, the economy of the village has been in decline.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deiniolen">Gall Deiniolen gyfeirio at:
Pentref Deiniolen yng ngogledd Gwynedd
Deiniolen neu "Deiniol Fab", sant, mab Deiniol sant.
Gweler hefyd:
Llanddeiniolen</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#denio">
            <name>Denio</name>
            <lat>52.8925585</lat>
            <lon>-4.4199264</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denio">Denio can refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dinas">
            <name>Dinas</name>
            <lat>53.107137</lat>
            <lon>-4.270416</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas">Dinas may refer to :
Dinas (weevil), a beetle genus in the tribe Sciaphilini</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas">Dinas yw lle trefol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dinas dinlle">
            <name>Dinas Dinlle</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas Dinlle">Dinas Dinlle is a small settlement in Gwynedd, north-west Wales which is also, historically, part of Caernarfonshire.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas Dinlle">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Gwynedd yw Dinas Dinlle (cyfeiriad grid SH4356). Saif ar lan Bae Caernarfon i'r de o Abermenai, tua 5 milltir i'r de-orllewin o dref Caernarfon. Mae ym mhlwyf Llandwrog. Mae traeth Morfa Dinlle a'i dywod braf yn boblogaidd gan bobl leol ac ymwelwyr. Siaredir y Gymraeg gan 77.9% o'r boblogaeth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dinas-mawddwy">
            <name>Dinas-Mawddwy</name>
            <lat>52.724112</lat>
            <lon>-3.688959</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dinorwic">
            <name>Dinorwic</name>
            <lat>53.1340503</lat>
            <lon>-4.1139368</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinorwic">Dinorwic is the anglicised form of the Welsh name Dinorwig, a village in Wales.
It may also refer to:
Dinorwic Quarry, a former slate quarry near Dinorwig, Wales
Dinorwic, Ontario, a community in Canada
Dinorwic (crater), a crater on Mars, named after the Canadian settlement

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dol-ffanog">
            <name>Dol-ffanog</name>
            <lat>52.686142</lat>
            <lon>-3.877239</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dolbenmaen">
            <name>Dolbenmaen</name>
            <lat>52.964847</lat>
            <lon>-4.225456</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolbenmaen">Dolbenmaen is a village and community in the Welsh county of Gwynedd, located in Eifionydd, of which it was the administrative centre until 1239. The community includes the villages of Bryncir, Cenin, Garndolbenmaen, Golan, Llanfihangel-y-Pennant, Penmorfa and Pentrefelin, and has a population of 1,300, increasing slightly to 1,343 at the 2011 Census. The summit of Moel Hebog is shared between Beddgelert and Dolbenmaen.

The parish church of St Mary's is a grade II* listed building.
^ Criccieth Visitors' Map and Brief History, 2002, Cymdeithas Hanes Eifionydd, Wales
^ Office for National Statistics : Census 2001 : Parish Headcounts : Gwynedd Retrieved 13 January 2010
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 15 May 2015. 
^ "Parish Church of St Mary, Dolbenmaen". British Listed Buildings. Retrieved 16 December 2013.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolbenmaen">Pentref bychan a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Dolbenmaen. Arferai fod yn blwyf, rhan o hen gwmwd Eifionydd, Teyrnas Gwynedd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dolgellau">
            <name>Dolgellau</name>
            <lat>52.74215</lat>
            <lon>-3.8844</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolgellau">Dolgellau (/dɔːlˈɡɛli/; Welsh pronunciation: [dɔlˈɡɛɬaɨ]; formerly anglicised Dolgelley or Dolgelly) is a market town in Gwynedd, north-west Wales, lying on the River Wnion, a tributary of the River Mawddach. It was the county town of Merionethshire (Welsh: Meirionnydd, Sir Feirionnydd) before that became a part of the county of Gwynedd. Dolgellau is the main base for climbers of Cader Idris.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolgellau">Tref farchnad yn ne Gwynedd yw Dolgellau, ger mynydd Cader Idris. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 72901 18024. Mae afon Wnion, un o lednentydd yr afon Mawddach, yn llifo trwy’r dref gan basio dan Y Bont Fawr.

Mae Caerdydd 148.3 km i ffwrdd o Ddolgellau ac mae Llundain yn 292.5 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 56 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dolgoch">
            <name>Dolgoch</name>
            <lat>52.623972</lat>
            <lon>-3.993354</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolgoch">Dolgoch can refer to:
Dolgoch railway station – a station on the preserved Talyllyn Railway
Dolgoch (locomotive) – a preserved steam locomotive on the Talyllyn Railway
Dolgoch Falls – a series of waterfalls near Tywyn in Mid-Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dolhendre">
            <name>Dolhendre</name>
            <lat>52.8634109</lat>
            <lon>-3.7065334</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dolydd">
            <name>Dolydd</name>
            <lat>53.090191</lat>
            <lon>-4.274911</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dwyfach">
            <name>Dwyfach</name>
            <lat>53.0028537</lat>
            <lon>-4.3069858</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dwyfor">
            <name>Dwyfor</name>
            <lat>51.6834537</lat>
            <lon>-4.1187363</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwyfor">Dwyfor was one of the five local government districts of Gwynedd, Wales from 1974 to 1996, covering the Llŷn peninsula. Its council was based in Pwllheli.
It was formed on 1 April 1974 as a successor to the borough of Pwllheli, the urban districts of Criccieth and Porthmadog, along with Llŷn Rural District, and part of Gwyrfai Rural District, all previously in the administrative county of Caernarfonshire. It was named after the river Dwyfor.
Dwyfor was notable for being the last stronghold of the Sabbatarian temperance movement in Wales. Under the terms of the Licensing Act 1961, local referendums prevented the opening of public houses on Sundays until 1982, and a further referendum (on a 9% turnout) reimposed Sunday closing between 1989 and 1996.
It was abolished as a district when Gwynedd was reconstituted as a unitary authority on 1 April 1996. It remains in use as an area covered by an area committee of Gwynedd Council.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwyfor">Gweler hefyd: Dwyfor Meirionnydd (etholaeth seneddol) a Coleg Meirion-Dwyfor.
Roedd Dwyfor yn un o bum dosbarth llywodraeth leol sir Gwynedd, yng ngogledd-orllewin Cymru, o 1974 hyd 1996, yn cyfateb yn fras i ardal penrhyn Llŷn ac Eifionydd. Lleolwyd pencadlys y cyngor yn nhref Pwllheli.
Sefydlwyd Dwyfor ar y 1af o Ebrill, 1974, fel olynydd i fwrdeistref Pwllheli, dosbarthau trefol Cricieth a Porthmadog, Dosbarth Gwledig Llŷn, a rhan o Ddosbarth Gwledig Gwyrfai, a fuont yn rhan o'r hen sir weinyddol, Sir Gaernarfon. Fe'i enwyd ar ôl Afon Dwyfor.
Roedd Dwyfor yn un o gadarnleoedd olaf y mudiad dirwest yng Nghymru. Dan dermau Deddf Drwyddedu 1961, gwrthodwyd refferendau lleol agor tafarndai ar y Sul hyd 1982 ; ailgaewyd y tafarndai ar y Sul ar ôl refferendwm arall yn 1989, gyda 9% yn pleidleisio, ond maent ar agor eto ers 1996.
Dileuwyd y dosbarth pan ailgreuwyd sir Gwynedd ar y 1af o Ebrill 1996. Ond mae'n aros fel ardal a wasanaethir gan un o bwyllgorau ardal Cyngor Gwynedd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dwyryd">
            <name>Dwyryd</name>
            <lat>52.97562</lat>
            <lon>-3.94496</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dyffryn ardudwy">
            <name>Dyffryn Ardudwy</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn Ardudwy">Dyffryn Ardudwy is a village and community in the Ardudwy area of Gwynedd, Wales. The ward had a population of 1,540 according to the 2011 census.
The village of Dyffryn Ardudwy is situated on the A496 coastal road between the towns of Harlech and Barmouth and at the foot of Moelfre, part of the Rhinogydd range.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn Ardudwy">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Gwynedd yw Dyffryn Ardudwy. Saif ar y ffordd A496 rhwng Harlech ac Abermaw yn ardal Ardudwy. Mae pentref Llanbedr ychydig i'r gogledd a Thalybont i'r de.
Mae twristiaeth yn bwysig i'r pentref bellach, gan ei fod gerllaw traethau Morfa Dyffryn. Ychydig i'r gorllewin o ganol y pentref mae un o orsafoedd trên Rheilffordd Arfordir Cymru.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dyfi">
            <name>Dyfi</name>
            <lat>52.547325</lat>
            <lon>-3.9953425</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dyfrdwy">
            <name>Dyfrdwy</name>
            <lat>53.2304449</lat>
            <lon>-4.1299727</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#dysynni">
            <name>Dysynni</name>
            <lat>52.5828477</lat>
            <lon>-4.0931566</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#eden">
            <name>Eden</name>
            <lat>53.110595</lat>
            <lon>-2.9429546</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eden">Eden may refer to:
Garden of Eden, biblical "garden of God" described in the Book of Genesis
Garden Route, Eden District located in the Western Cape, South Africa</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eden">Gall y gair Eden gyfeirio at:
Gardd Eden, yn y Beibl
Anthony Eden (1897-1977), gwleidydd
William Eden (1744-1814), diplomydd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#edern">
            <name>Edern</name>
            <lat>52.9262159</lat>
            <lon>-4.562308</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edern">Edern may refer to:
Edern, Carinthia, Austria
Edern, Finistère, France
Edern, Gwynedd, Wales

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edern">Enw dyn Cymraeg a Llydaweg ydy Edern, sy'n amrywiad ar Edeyrn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#efailnewydd">
            <name>Efailnewydd</name>
            <lat>52.896442</lat>
            <lon>-4.452472</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efailnewydd">Efailnewydd is a village on the Llŷn Peninsula (Welsh: Penrhyn Llŷn) in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies 1.2 miles (2 km) north west to the market town of Pwllheli. The village forms part of the community of Llannor along with the villages of Abererch and Rhos-fawr.
Pwllheli Rugby Club's playing field and clubhouse are located in the village. There is also a small shop located at the centre of the village.
^ "Efail-newydd/Buan ward population 2011". Retrieved 15 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efailnewydd">Pentref yn ardal Dwyfor, Gwynedd yw Efailnewydd. Fe'i lleolir ar benrhyn Llŷn ar y ffordd A497 tua 2 filltir i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Pwllheli.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#eisingrug">
            <name>Eisingrug</name>
            <lat>52.8896573</lat>
            <lon>-4.0606201</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eisingrug">Eisingrug (meaning: a place where corn was winnowed after husking) is a rural hamlet near Harlech, Gwynedd, Wales. It is located to the southeast of Porthmadog. On December 10, 1845, Eisingrug was visited by a Methodist missionary.
The Cambrian Line railway passes close to the village. The nearest railway station is to the north at Talsarnau.
In the northeast is the 14th century manor house, Maes-y-Neuadd Hotel. To the southwest is The Glyn and Brogyntyn Estate and to the northwest is Black Wood, a conifer plantation on a steep east-facing hillside with alternating rows of 2 separate conifer species.
The area affords good views over northern parts of Cardigan Bay.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#erch">
            <name>Erch</name>
            <lat>52.9037549</lat>
            <lon>-4.3833812</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erch">Gallai Erch gyfeirio at:
Afon Erch, afon sy'n aberu ger Pwllheli ac Abererch
Ynysoedd Erch yng ngogledd-ddwyrain yr Alban</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#esgairgeiliog">
            <name>Esgairgeiliog</name>
            <lat>52.637335</lat>
            <lon>-3.829651</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esgairgeiliog">Esgairgeiliog (also known as Ceinws) is a village in the valley of the Afon Dulas in Powys, Wales. The Afon Glesyrch joins the Dulas in the middle of the village.
The ERA slate quarry lay in the Glesyrch valley, behind the village.
The Centre for Alternative Technology lies about a mile south of the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esgairgeiliog">Pentref yn ardal Maldwyn, Powys yw Esgairgeiliog, a adnabyddir hefyd fel Ceinws yn lleol. Fe'i lleolir ar bwys y briffordd A487 tua 2 filltir i'r de o Gorris, rhwng y pentref hwnnw a thref Machynlleth, bron iawn ar y ffin sirol rhwng Powys a Gwynedd.
Mae'n rhan o blwyf eglwysig Llanwrin. Llifa Afon Dulas heibio i ymuno yn Afon Dyfi ger Machynlleth.
Ceir gorsaf reilffordd ar lein Rheilffordd Corris yn y pentref. Tua milltir a hanner i'r de ceir Canolfan y Dechnoleg Amgen.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#fachell">
            <name>Fachell</name>
            <lat>53.1731375</lat>
            <lon>-4.1781024</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#fachwen">
            <name>Fachwen</name>
            <lat>53.1346149</lat>
            <lon>-4.1392939</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#fairbourne">
            <name>Fairbourne</name>
            <lat>52.696651</lat>
            <lon>-4.054346</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairbourne">Fairbourne is a village on the coast of Barmouth Bay to the south of the estuary of the River Mawddach in Gwynedd, surrounded by the Snowdonia National Park. Before the seaside resort was built the coastal area was known as Morfa Henddol, while the outcrop now occupied by the Fairbourne Hotel was called Ynysfaig. Fairbourne was founded as a seaside resort by Arthur McDougall (of flour making fame.) It is in an area listed by Gwynedd council for managed retreat due to rising sea levels 
The original Fairbourne Golf Club (now defunct) was founded in the early 1890s. The club disappeared in the early 1960s.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairbourne">Pentref yn ne Gwynedd yw Fairbourne. Yn anarferol iawn i bentrefi Gwynedd, nid oes enw Cymraeg arno. Defnyddir Friog weithiau fel enw Cymraeg Fairbourne, ond mewn gwirionedd mae Friog yn bentref ar wahân. Gelwid yr ardal yn "Morfa Henddol" cyn adeiladu'r pentref, a chredir fod yr enw Rowen wedi ei ddefnyddio am y pentref ar un adeg.
Saif Fairbourne yng nghymuned Arthog ar bwys y briffordd A493 rhwng Dolgellau a Thywyn. Mae ar ochr ddeheuol aber Afon Mawddach, gyferbyn a thref Abermaw. Sefydlwyd Fairbourne gan Arthur McDougall, o'r teulu oedd yn cynhyrchu blawd McDougall's, fel pentref gwyliau glan-y-môr.
Ceir olion yr Ail Ryfel Byd yn y tywynni traeth, amddiffyniadau i rwystro tanciau, a elwir yn lleol yn "Ddannedd y Draig".

</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#ffestiniog">
            <name>Ffestiniog</name>
            <lat>52.959065</lat>
            <lon>-3.933458</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ffestiniog">Ffestiniog is a community in Gwynedd in Wales, containing several villages, in particular the settlements of Llan Ffestiniog and Blaenau Ffestiniog. It has a population of 4,875.
Ffestiniog was a parish in Cantref Ardudwy; in 1284, Ardudwy became part of the county of Meirionnydd, which became an administrative county in 1888. The parish was created an urban district in 1894. On 1 April 1974, under the Local Government Act 1972, Ffestiniog Urban District was abolished, becoming merged with other districts to form Meirionnydd District, which was itself abolished in 1996. Ffestiniog became a community with an elected town council.
Ffestiniog Golf Club (now defunct) was founded in 1893. The club closed at the end of March 2014.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ffestiniog">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf yng Ngwynedd yw Ffestiniog neu Llan Ffestiniog, a saif rhwng Blaenau Ffestiniog a Maentwrog, yng Nghwm Ffestiniog. O'r pentref ceir golygfeydd braf o'r Moelwynion, Cnicht a bryniau Blaenau. Yn y plwyf ceir Rhaeadr y Cwm a Phwlpud Huw Llwyd ar lan Afon Cynfal.
Enw ysgol y pentref yw Ysgol Bro Cynfal. Mae un tafarn yn y pentref o'r enw'r Pengwern ac un siop, Swyddfa'r Post ac hefyd Neuadd Bentref. Llan Ffestiniog yw cartref Clwb Golff Ffestiniog.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#foel-fras">
            <name>Foel-Fras</name>
            <lat>53.1945286</lat>
            <lon>-3.952353</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#friog">
            <name>Friog</name>
            <lat>52.690079</lat>
            <lon>-4.049557</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friog">Friog is a small village in North Wales, near Fairbourne.
Its lake and beach are a tourist attraction to over 1,000 visitors a year.
Friog is notable for a rockfall-prone section of railway track, scene of two fatal accidents on the Aberystwyth and Welsh Coast Railway line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#fron">
            <name>Fron</name>
            <lat>52.6230609</lat>
            <lon>-3.1412122</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fron">Fron is a former municipality in Gudbrandsdal in Oppland, Norway.
It was created in 1837 as Fron formannskapsdistrikt, but in 1851 the municipality was split into Nord-Fron and Sør-Fron. They were reunited in 1966, during a nationwide municipality merging process, but split again in 1977.
There have been talks about reuniting the two municipalities, but the plans have not come into life due to unwillingness in Sør-Fron, the smaller of the two. Nord-Fron has instead made inquiries to merge with Sel.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fron">Mae Fron (Y Fron) yn elfen gyffredin mewn enwau lleoedd Cymraeg. Gallai gyfeirio at un o sawl bryn neu le, yn cynnwys:
Fron, Aberriw, Powys
Fron, Llanbadarn Fawr, Powys
Gweler hefyd
Y Fron, Gwynedd
Y Fron, Powys</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#frongoch">
            <name>Frongoch</name>
            <lat>52.939627</lat>
            <lon>-3.6304261</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frongoch">The village of Frongoch is located in Gwynedd, Wales. It lies close to the market town of Bala, on the A4212 road in north Wales.
It was the home of the Frongoch internment camp, used to hold German prisoners-of-war during First World War, and then Irish Republican prisoners from the 1916 Rising.
Frongoch railway station was on the Bala Ffestiniog Line. It closed to passenger services on 2 January 1960 and freight services on 27 January 1961.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gaedol">
            <name>Gaedol</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gallt-y-foel">
            <name>Gallt-y-foel</name>
            <lat>53.140121</lat>
            <lon>-4.124961</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#ganllwyd">
            <name>Ganllwyd</name>
            <lat>52.805086</lat>
            <lon>-3.889463</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganllwyd">Ganllwyd is a small village and community in southern Gwynedd, Wales. It lies in the Snowdonia National Park to the north of Dolgellau. A470 passes through it. The Community population taken at the 2011 Census was 179.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganllwyd">Pentref yng Ngwynedd yw'r Ganllwyd, sydd wedi ei leoli mewn dyffryn ar yr A470 ger Dolgellau. Yno mae'r Afon Gamlan yn ymuno gyda'r Afon Mawddach. Mae'n gymuned hefyd.
Mae olion y diwydiant aur i'w gweld yno tu ôl i'r neuadd pentref. Y mwyngoddfa fwyaf oedd Ffridd Goch a'r chyfadeiladau yng Nghefn Coed. Cynhyrchwyd 80 owns o aur o’r safleoedd hyn rhwng 1896 a 1902. Y tro diwethaf y mwyngloddwyd yn yr ardal oedd rhwng 1919 ac 1922. Roedd hefyd mwynfa fechan Tyddyn Gwladys o tua 1830, a'i weithwyd yn ysbeidiol i gynhyrchu plwm ac aur. Cloddiwyd 43 tunell o fwyn aur, gan gynhyrchu 7 owns o aur yn ei blwyddyn olaf yn 1899.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#garndolbenmaen">
            <name>Garndolbenmaen</name>
            <lat>52.973726</lat>
            <lon>-4.240343</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garndolbenmaen">Garndolbenmaen, known colloquially as Garn, is a village in the county of Gwynedd, Wales. It lies near the A487, approximately 6 miles north west of Porthmadog, in the community of Dolbenmaen, which has a population of 1,300. The closest villages are Dolbenmaen and Bryncir. The Papur Bro, the local Welsh language paper, is called Y Ffynnon (The Source/Spring).
Blaen y Cae recording studios are located in the village, where Pep Le Pew's album, Un tro yn y Gorllewin and the last album by Gwyneth Glyn, Wyneb Dros Dro, were recorded. The producer and musician Dyl Mei also lives in Garndolbenmaen.
Approximately 50 pupils attend Ysgol Gynradd Garndolbenmaen, many pupils travel from nearby villages including Pant Glas, Bryncir, Cwm Pennant and Golan. The number of pupils attending the school has remained consistent over the past 20 years.
Many of the old cottages in Garndolbenmaen have been turned into holiday homes.
There is a pub in the village, the Cross Foxes. However at the turn of the 20th century there were several pubs including the Cross Pipes and Dafarn Faig, this was located on the "lôn gefn" (back road) leading to Bryncir.
The Gwynedd county councillor for the Dolbenmaen ward, Steve Churchman, a member of the Liberal Democrats, is the postmaster and runs a small shop.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garndolbenmaen">Pentref yng Ngwynedd yw Garndolbenmaen. Gorwedd ger yr A487 tua 6 milltir i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Porthmadog. Y pentrefi agosaf yw Dolbenmaen a Bryncir. Mae'n ran o gymuned Dolbenmaen, sydd â phoblogaeth o 1,300. Y Ffynnon yw papur bro Garndolbenmaen.
Yno hefyd mae stiwdio recordio Blaen y Cae, ble recordwyd albym Pep Le Pew, Un tro yn y Gorllewin ac albym diweddaraf Gwyneth Glyn, sef Wyneb Dros Dro. Mae'r cynhyrchydd a'r cerddorwr Dyl Mei hefyd yn byw yng Ngarndolbenmaen.
Mae tua 50 o ddisgyblion yn Ysgol Gynradd Garndolbenmaen, mae nifer yn teithio yno o bentrefi cyfagos megis Pant Glas, Bryncir, Cwm Pennant a Golan. Mae'r nifer yma wedi aros yn gyson am oleiaf ugain mlynedd.
Eisioes mae nifer o hen fythynod yng Ngarndolbenmaen wedi eu troi yn dai haf.
Mae Cynghorwr Sir Gwynedd ar gyfer ward Dolbenmaen, Steve Churchman, o blaid Democratiaid Rhyddfrydol Cymru, yn bostfeisr ac yn rhedeg siop yno.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#garnfadryn">
            <name>Garnfadryn</name>
            <lat>52.88221</lat>
            <lon>-4.563226</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#garreg">
            <name>Garreg</name>
            <lat>52.9542689</lat>
            <lon>-4.065282</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garreg">Mae Garreg (treiglad meddal carreg) yn elfen gyffredin mewn enwau lleoedd yng Nghymru. Gallai gyfeirio at:
Garreg, Gwynedd, pentref yng Ngwynedd
Garreg Lwyd (dau le)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#garth">
            <name>Garth</name>
            <lat>52.133667</lat>
            <lon>-3.536803</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth">Garth may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth">Mae Garth yn enw sawl lle yng Nghymru, ac yn elfen mewn enwau lleoedd eraill:
Garth, pentref yng Ngheredigion
Garth, pentref ym mwrdeisdref sirol Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr
Garth, pentref ym Mhowys
Garth, pentref yn sir Wrecsam
Garth (mynydd), Bannau Brycheiniog, Cyfeirnod grid OS: SO053506
Hefyd:
Gwaelod-y-Garth
Garth Celyn, enw arall ar Ben-y-bryn, Abergwyngregyn
Chwarel y Garth, SoDdGA yn Ne Powys
Garth Isaf, SoDdGA ym Mhowys
Gartheli, pentrefan yng Ngheredigion
Gall hefyd fod yn enw person:
Garth Brooks, canwr gwlad Americanaidd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gellilydan">
            <name>Gellilydan</name>
            <lat>52.938733</lat>
            <lon>-3.958852</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gellilydan">Gellilydan is a village in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies 1.7 miles (2.8 km) south east of Blaenau Ffestiniog.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gellilydan">Pentref bychan yng Ngwynedd yw Gellilydan, rhwng Trawsfynydd a Blaenau Ffestiniog yng nghymuned Maentwrog.
Mae'r pentref ar ochr cefnffordd de-gogledd yr A487 yn agos at gyffordd y ffordd honno gyda'r A470 ar ben allt sy'n cael ei hadnabod fel Dreif yr Oakley sy'n codi o bentref cyfagos Maentwrog. Dyma'r pentref agosaf at atomfa Trawsfynydd sydd lai na milltir i ffwrdd o ganol y pentref.
O safbwynt gweinyddol, mae'r pentref yn rhan o ward Trawsfynydd ac yn cael ei gynrychioli ar Gyngor Gwynedd gan y Cynghorydd Thomas Ellis (Annibynnol).
Mae ysgol gynradd yn y pentref o'r enw Ysgol Edmwnd Prys, sy'n rhan o ddalgylch Ysgol y Moelwyn, Blaenau Ffestiniog. Mae un tafarn yn y pentref o'r enw'r Bryn Arms.
Mae gwasanaeth bws eithaf rheolaidd ar gael o'r pentref i Ddolgellau a Blaenau Ffestiniog ac mae hefyd yn cael ei wasanaethu gan fysus y Trawscambria o Fangor i Aberystwyth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gerlan">
            <name>Gerlan</name>
            <lat>53.177607</lat>
            <lon>-4.050495</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glan adda">
            <name>Glan Adda</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glan dwyfach">
            <name>Glan Dwyfach</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glan-y-wern">
            <name>Glan-y-wern</name>
            <lat>52.892792</lat>
            <lon>-4.0711</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glan-y-wern">Glan-y-wern is a hamlet in the community of Borth, Ceredigion, Wales, which is 78.2 miles (125.9km) from Cardiff and 179.6 miles (289km) from London. Glan-y-wern is represented in the National Assembly for Wales by Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) and the Member of Parliament is Mark Williams (Liberal Democrats).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glan-y-wern">Erthygl am y pentref yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Am y pentref yng Ngheredigion gweler Glan-y-wern.
Pentref bychan yn ne Gwynedd yw Glan-y-wern. Mae'n gorwedd yn ardal Ardudwy ar bwys y briffordd A496 tua hanner ffordd rhwng Harlech i'r de a Maentwrog i'r gogledd.
Y pentrefi agosaf yw Talsarnau, llai na filltir i'r gorllewin, a Llanfihangel-y-traethau ('Ynys'), filltir i'r gogledd ar yr A496. Gwasaneithir Glan-y-wern a Llanfihangel gan orsaf reilffordd Tŷ Gwyn ar lein Rheilffordd Arfordir Cymru chwarter milltir i'r de-orllewin o'r pentref. Mae lôn hynafol yn dringo o Lan-y-wern trwy Lyn Cywarch ac Eisingrug i Gwm Eisingrug lle mae llwybr yn arwain heibio i'r llynnoedd wrth droed Moel Ysgyfarnogod a trosodd i gyfeiriad Trawsfynydd.
Mae Pont Glan-y-wern yn dwyn yr A496 dros afon Eisingrug yn y pentref. I'r de-orllewin o'r pentref ceir gwastadedd eang Morfa Harlech, sy'n Warchodfa Natur Cenedlaethol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glan-yr-afon">
            <name>Glan-yr-afon</name>
            <lat>52.971617</lat>
            <lon>-3.4577463</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glan-yr-afon">Gallai Glan-yr-afon neu Glanrafon gyfeirio at:
Glan-yr-afon, Bodffordd, Ynys Môn
Glan-yr-afon, Mariandyrys, Ynys Môn
Glan'rafon, Caerdydd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glasinfryn">
            <name>Glasinfryn</name>
            <lat>53.198236</lat>
            <lon>-4.116159</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasinfryn">Glasinfryn is a small village in Gwynedd, Wales, between the village of Tregarth and the city of Bangor, Gwynedd. The village is residential in nature but with many outlying farms.
It is noted, perhaps, for having two bridges, one carries the old Bethesda, Wales to Bangor railway trackbed on an attractive Victorian architecture viaduct, the other is a concrete flyover built in the 1980s carrying the A55.
It is credited as the start of the A4244 road but in reality the road lies approximately 1 kilometre (0.62 mi) south of the village. "Infryn" means turf, therefore the name of the village means literally "blue turf".</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasinfryn">Pentref bychan i'r de o ddinas Bangor yng Ngwynedd yw Glasinfryn. Saif ar Afon Cegin, ac ar ffordd gefn rhwng y priffyrdd A55 ac A4244. Mae Tregarth ychydig i'r dwyrain.
Mae Lôn Las Ogwen yn arwain heibio'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glaslyn">
            <name>Glaslyn</name>
            <lat>53.0699344</lat>
            <lon>-4.0676853</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glaslyn">Glaslyn (Welsh: Blue lake) is a lake in the Snowdonia National Park in Gwynedd, north-west Wales.
It is found at approximately 600 metres (2,000 ft) above sea level in a cwm on the eastern flanks of Snowdon. It is a rough ellipse in shape, about 500 metres (1,600 ft) east–west and about 300 metres (980 ft) north–south, and the Miners' Track runs along the northern shore.
Glaslyn is the source of the Afon Glaslyn, the major river of Gwynedd, which runs east to the reservoir of Llyn Llydaw before turning south-west to reach the sea at Porthmadog.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glaslyn">Gallai Glaslyn gyfeirio at:
Daearyddiaeth
Glaslyn, llyn ym Mhowys.
Llyn Glaslyn, neu 'Glaslyn' yn unig, ar yr Wyddfa.
Afon Glaslyn, sy'n tarddu o'r llyn.

Aberglaslyn, ger Beddgelert.
Pobl
Glaslyn, enw barddol Richard Owen (Glaslyn) (1831-1909), hynafiaethydd a llenor</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#glyder fawr">
            <name>Glyder Fawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glyder Fawr">Glyder Fawr is a mountain in Snowdonia, Wales, the highest in the Glyderau at just over 1,000m. It is the fifth highest mountain in Wales.
The summit lies on the ridge between Glyder Fach and Y Garn, and has views to the north, across the Ogwen Valley, of Pen yr Ole Wen and the Carneddau, and views south to the Snowdon Horseshoe. The summit plateau is very rocky, making progress slow.
Routes to the summit start at Ogwen Cottage on the shores of Llyn Idwal to the north, from Pen-y-Pass to the south, and along the Glyder ridge to the east. One of the most popular routes from Ogwen Cottage follows the shore of Llyn Idwal to the base of the famous Idwal Slabs (a popular rock climbing crag), it then makes its way out of the cwm via the steep Devil's Kitchen path, arriving at a small lake called Llyn Y Cwn. From here a steep scree path ascends the western shoulder to the summit of Glyder Fawr.
Until late-2010, most maps showed a height of 999m for Glyder Fawr, however it was resurveyed with accurate GPS equipment and found to be 1,000.8m.
The summit marks the boundary of Gwynedd and Conwy County Borough.
According to Sir Ifor Williams, the word "Glyder" derives from the Welsh word "Gludair", meaning a heap of stones.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glyder Fawr">Mae'r Glyder Fawr yn fynydd yn Eryri, ac ar y ffin rhwng Gwynedd a Sir Conwy. Mae'n un o nifer o fynyddoedd dros 3,000 o droedfeddi yn y Glyderau, er ei fod un medr yn fyr o fod yn gopa 1,000 medr o uchder. Ceir creigiau mawr ar y copa, yn arbennig y casgliad o greigiau a elwir yn "Castell y Gwynt".
Y ffordd orau o gyrraedd y copa yw dilyn y llwybr o Lyn Ogwen at Lyn Idwal. Wedi mynd heibio Llyn Idwal mae'r llwybr yn dringo'n serth heibio'r Twll Du i gyrraedd tir gwastad ger Llyn y Cŵn. (Sylwer na ddylid ceisio dringo i fyny hafn y Twll Du heb raff.) Gellir troi i'r chwith yma a dilyn llwybr sy'n arwain i gopa'r Glyder Fawr ac yna ymlaen i'r Glyder Fach. Gellir dringo'r mynydd o Pen-y-Pass hefyd, neu gellir dringo Tryfan gyntaf ac yna dilyn y grib i'r Glyder Fach a'r Glyder Fawr, ond mae'r llwybr yma'n anoddach.

Yn ôl Syr Ifor Williams, "Gludair" oedd y ffurf gywir ar yr enw. Aeth yn "Glydar" yn nhafodiaith Arfon, yna'n "Glyder". Yr ystyr yw "cruglwyth o gerrig".</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#golan">
            <name>Golan</name>
            <lat>52.958934</lat>
            <lon>-4.199001</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golan">Golan (Hebrew: גּולן‎; Arabic: جولان‎ Gōlān or Jōlān; Greek: Γαυλανῖτις Gaulanítis) was a biblical city in Land of Israel. It was in the territory of Manasseh in the Bashan.
Golan was the most northerly of the three cities of refuge east of the Jordan River (Deuteronomy 4:43). Manasseh gave this city to the Gershonite Levites (Joshua 21:27; 1 Chronicles 6:71). According to the Bible, the Israelites conquered Golan from the Amorites. The city was known to Josephus. Near Golan, Alexander Jannaeus was ambushed by Obodas, king of the Arabians, and his army. It formed the eastern boundary of Galilee and was part of the tetrarchy of Philip. It was described by Eusebius in his Onomasticon as a large village that gave its name to the surrounding country.
Archaeologists have speculated that the ancient city of Golan may be Sahm el-Jaulān, a large village 4 miles (6.4 km) east of Nahr ‛Allān and 4 miles (6.4 km) southeast of Tsīl, where ruins were found from the early Byzantine era.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golan">Ceir mwy nag un enghraifft o'r enw Golan:
Golan - dinas yn y Beibl; mae ei union leoliad yn anhysbys
Ucheldiroedd Golan - ucheldir o bwys strategol rhwng Syria ac Israel
Golan - pentref yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gorddinog">
            <name>Gorddinog</name>
            <lat>53.242806</lat>
            <lon>-3.989313</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#groesffordd">
            <name>Groesffordd</name>
            <lat>52.925565</lat>
            <lon>-4.570753</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#groeslon">
            <name>Groeslon</name>
            <lat>53.076701</lat>
            <lon>-4.280573</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groeslon">Groeslon (Welsh: Y Groeslon, "the crossroads") is a small village in the community of Llandwrog in the Welsh traditional county of Caernarfonshire. Groeslon is administered by Gwynedd Council.

The population was 1,256 at the 2011 census
Nearby villages are Penygroes, Carmel and Dinas. The village lies approximately five miles south of Caernarfon. It has one primary school in the centre of the village and no secondary schools. Most secondary school age pupils go to Ysgol Dyffryn Nantlle in Penygroes.
Groeslon was by-passed in 2002 by the A487 road, a trunk road which cost around £12 million to complete. A bat bridge was constructed in 2010 to guide lesser horseshoe bats across the road.
Formerly an agricultural and slate mining village, Groeslon is now expanding as a commuter village for the surrounding towns, especially Caernarfon and Bangor. Its initial growth came as a result of the construction of the LMS railway in 1867. Groeslon railway station closed in December 1964. The railway line is now part of the national cycle route.
In the village there is one pub called the Penionyn.
At the bottom of the village, bordering the A487, a huge wall becomes visible. This is the wall to the Glynllifon estate, formerly the seat of Lord Newborough, which is now a country park and college (Meirion Dwyfor) specialising in land based industries, e.g. agriculture, equine studies and arboriculture.
Groeslon is covered by a Neighbourhood Policing Team based in Penygroes.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groeslon">Mae Groeslon neu Y Groeslon yn bentref yn Nyffryn Nantlle yng Ngwynedd. Saif gerllaw priffordd yr A487 rhwng Caernarfon a Phenygroes, ac ychydig i'r gorllewin o bentref Carmel a bryn Moel Tryfan. Hyd yn ddiweddar yr oedd yr A487 yn mynd trwy'r pentref, ond yn 2002 agorwyd ffordd osgoi newydd.
Tyfodd y Groeslon fel pentref i'r gweithwyr yn y chwareli llechi yn yr ardal. Datblygodd y pentref yn sgil agor gorsaf rheilffordd yr LMS yn 1867. O'r Groeslon yr oedd y dramodydd John Gwilym Jones a'r bardd Tom Huws yn enedigol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gryn goch">
            <name>Gryn Goch</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gwastadgoed">
            <name>Gwastadgoed</name>
            <lat>52.6737239</lat>
            <lon>-4.0783546</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gwastadnant">
            <name>Gwastadnant</name>
            <lat>53.099414</lat>
            <lon>-4.073432</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#gwyrfai">
            <name>Gwyrfai</name>
            <lat>53.0984467</lat>
            <lon>-4.193172</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwyrfai">Gallai Gwyrfai gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#harlech">
            <name>Harlech</name>
            <lat>52.858894</lat>
            <lon>-4.107858</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harlech">Harlech (Welsh pronunciation: [ˈharlɛx]) is a town and seaside resort in Gwynedd, within the historical boundaries of Meirionnydd in northwest Wales. Lying on Tremadog Bay and within the Snowdonia National Park, it has a population of 1,447, of whom 51% speak Welsh. The town is located in the unitary authority of Gwynedd which was formed in 1996, from 1974 to 1996 it was in the Meirionydd District of the 1974 County of Gwynedd, and before 1974 it was in the historic county of Merionethshire.
The town is best known for the landmark Harlech Castle, begun in 1283 by Edward I of England, captured by Owain Glyndŵr, and later the stronghold of Henry Tudor. The castle was originally built next to the sea, but geological processes have changed the shape of the coastline, and the castle now lies on a cliff face, about half a mile (800 m) inland. The town has since developed with housing estates on the flat low town area and hillside properties in the high town around the shopping street, church, and castle. The two areas are linked by a steep and winding road called "Twtil".</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harlech">Tref hanesyddol a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Harlech. Mae'n enwog am ei chastell a gysylltir a chwedl Branwen ferch Llŷr ym Mhedair Cainc y Mabinogi. Saif ardal yn Ardudwy uwchben Morfa Harlech yn wynebu ar Fae Tremadog. Y tu cefn i'r dref cyfyd y bryniau i gopaon y Rhinogau. Yn y gorffennol bu'n ganolfan sirol Sir Feirionnydd. Rhed yr A496 trwy'r dref, sy'n gyrchfan poblogaidd gan ymwelwyr yn yr haf.

</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#hawddamor">
            <name>Hawddamor</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#hendre">
            <name>Hendre</name>
            <lat>51.5262874</lat>
            <lon>-3.529573</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#hirael">
            <name>Hirael</name>
            <lat>53.233364</lat>
            <lon>-4.119727</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanaber">
            <name>Llanaber</name>
            <lat>52.74035</lat>
            <lon>-4.074871</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanaber">Llanaber is a linear village in north west Wales, near the resort of Barmouth. It is situated between Talybont and Barmouth on the coast, 1 km north of Barmouth on the A496 road. The Irish Sea lies directly to the west and the Rhiniog mountains lie directly to the east. The main attraction of Llanaber is the vast beautiful beach that is clean and flat and never overcrowded, making it ideal for a range of recreational activities, including horse riding, cycling, rounders, cricket and football. A protective promenade runs alongside the beach, taking walkers and cyclists all the way into Barmouth town centre.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanaber">Pentref bychan yn ne Gwynedd yw Llanaber. Saif ar briffordd yr A496 tua 3 milltir i'r gogledd o Abermaw ac mae'n rhan o gymuned Aberffraw.
Ceir eglwys hynafol a gysegrir i Sant Bodfan a'r Forwyn Fair yn Llanaber. Yn yr eglwys, sy'n dyddio o'r 13eg ganrif, ceir Maen Calixtus sy'n coffhau tywysog cynnar o'r enw Caelixtus.
Ceir Gorsaf reilffordd Llanaber ar linell Rheilffordd y Cambrian yn y pentref hefyd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanaelhaearn">
            <name>Llanaelhaearn</name>
            <lat>52.97622</lat>
            <lon>-4.405328</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanaelhaearn">Llanaelhaearn is a village and community on the Llŷn Peninsula in the county of Gwynedd, Wales. The community includes the village of Trefor and has a population of 1,067, increasing to 1,117 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanaelhaearn">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf eglwysig ar Benrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd yw Llanaelhaearn, yn ardal Eifionydd.
Saif ar y briffordd A499 rhwng Caernarfon a Pwllheli, lle mae ffordd y B4417 yn fforchio o'r briffordd i gyfeiriad Nefyn. Daeth y pentref yn adnabyddus pan oedd Antur Aelhaearn yn yn ei anterth. Roedd hwn yn gynllun a anelai at adfywio economi'r pentref ac felly warchod ei ddiwylliant. Cynhelir eisteddfod flynyddol, yn awr yn festri Capel y Babell, sydd wedi ei addasu i fod yn ganolfan gymdeithasol. Mae nifer o enwgion yn gyn-enillwyr yma, yn cynnwys Bryn Terfel.
Mae nifer o hynafiaethau diddorol o gwmpas y pentref. Ar gopa dwyreiniol Yr Eifl uwchben y pentref mae Tre'r Ceiri, bryngaer o Oes yr Haearn a ystyrir yn un o'r bryngaerau mwyaf tarawiadol yn Nghymru. Yn Eglwys Sant Aelhaearn mae dwy garreg ac arysgrifau Lladin arnynt. Y mwyaf diddorol yw carreg sy'n dyddio o tua diwedd y 5ed ganrif, gyda'r arysgrif ALIORTUS ELMETIACO(S) / HIC IACET ("Aliortus, gŵr o Elmet, sy'n gorwedd yma"). Elmet ("Elfed" mewn Cymraeg Diweddar) yw'r hen deyrnas Frythonig yn ardal Leeds heddiw, felly mae'n ymddangos fod Aliortus wedi marw ymhell o gartref. Efallai ei fod ar bererindod i Ynys Enlli. Mae'r ail garreg yn rhoi enw, Melitus, ond dim manylion pellach.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanarmon">
            <name>Llanarmon</name>
            <lat>52.928581</lat>
            <lon>-4.3467969</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanarmon">Llanarmon could refer to one of several villages in Wales:
Llanarmon, Gwynedd
Llanarmon Dyffryn Ceiriog, near Wrexham
Llanarmon Mynydd Mawr, a small settlement and parish in Powys
Llanarmon-yn-Iâl, Denbighshire (the name is often shortened to plain Llanarmon)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanarmon">Gall Llanarmon gyferio at:
Llanarmon Dyffryn Ceiriog, pentref yn Sir Wrecsam
Llanarmon-yn-Iâl, pentref yn Sir Ddinbych.
Llanarmon, pentref yng Ngwynedd
Llanarmon Mynydd Mawr, pentref ym Mhowys</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanbedr">
            <name>Llanbedr</name>
            <lat>52.819718</lat>
            <lon>-4.101435</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedr">Llanbedr is a village and community in the Ardudwy area, formerly Meirionnydd, of Gwynedd, Wales.
The village originally grew around the slate quarrying industry. Attractions in Llanbedr include Neolithic standing stones; the Stones of Llanbedr and Bronze Age hut circles. The Morfa Dyffryn sand dunes and Mochras (Shell Island) lie nearby. It also boasts two public houses; Ty Mawr Hotel and The Victoria Inn.
The church of St Peter, after whom the village is named (Pedr being the Welsh for Peter), is a class II* listed building. 
A mile from the village is the hamlet of Pentre Gwynfryn whose chapel, Capel Salem, was the subject of a painting by the artist Sydney Curnow Vosper. The painting, entitled Salem, showed a member of the congregation, Siân Owen, in traditional Welsh costume and became famous throughout Britain in the mid 20th century.
Llanbedr has a recently reopened airport which, until 2004, was operated by the Defence Evaluation and Research Agency (DERA) and QinetiQ as a launch site for remotely piloted drone 'aircraft' for use as aerial targets by the RAF and other UK forces. Opposite the airfield is one of two NACATC units (National Air Cadets Adventure Training Centres) in the UK (the other being in the village of Windermere in the English Lake District). The airfield was included in the Snowdonia Enterprise Zone by the Welsh Government in January 2013.
To the north of the village is the smaller village of Pensarn, situated at the estuary of the river Artro. This is the location of Llanbedr &amp; Pensarn Yacht Club and the Christian Mountain Centre, a residential adventure activity centre.
In 2008 Llanbedr was twinned with Huchenfeld, Germany, following many years of exchanges between schools, churches, musicians and community leaders, in remembrance of the ghastly occurrences in 1945 at Pforzheim and Huchenfeld during the Second World War.
Llanbedr railway station, formerly known as Talwrn Bach Halt, is a little out of the village itself and is served by the Cambrian Line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedr">Mae nifer o leoedd yn Nghymru yn dwyn yr enw Llanbedr:
Llanbedr, cymuned yn Ardudwy, Gwynedd
Llanbedr, pentref ym Mhowys
Llanbedr Dyffryn Clwyd, yn Sir Ddinbych
Llanbedr Efelffre, yn Sir Benfro
Llanbedr Gwynllŵg, yn Sir Fynwy
Llanbedr Pont Steffan, yn Sir Aberteifi
Llanbedr Ystrad Yw, ym Mhowys
Llanbedr-ar-fynydd, yn Rhondda Cynon Taf
Llanbedr-goch, ym Môn
Llanbedr-y-cennin, yn sir Conwy
Llanbedr-y-fro, ym Mro Morgannwg
Gweler hefyd:
Llanbedrog, Gwynedd
Peterstow, Lloegr
Sant Pedr</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanbedrog">
            <name>Llanbedrog</name>
            <lat>52.857872</lat>
            <lon>-4.484416</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedrog">Llanbedrog is a village and community on the Llŷn peninsula of Gwynedd in Wales. It is situated on the south side of the peninsula on the A499 between Pwllheli and Abersoch. Formerly in the county of Caernarfonshire, it has a population of 1,020, reducing slightly to 1,002 at the 2011 Census.

The village takes its name from Saint Petroc, a 6th-century Celtic saint. Petroc may be a form of the name Patrick, but Saint Petroc should not be confused with Saint Patrick. Saint Petrog's church is a grade II* listed building.
South of the village is the headland and open area of Mynydd Tir-y-cwmwd. Granite quarrying was commercially important in the late 19th century and the first half of the 20th century. The quarry closed down in 1949.

Holiday-makers started coming to Llanbedrog in significant numbers in the early 20th century, and the Pwllheli and Llanbedrog Tramway was built, linking the village to Pwllheli. Most of the track has now eroded and washed away but sections are still visible. The beach is now managed by the National Trust. In 1856 a dower house, "Plas Glyn-y-Weddw", was built in lower Llanbedrog for Lady Love Jones Parry. The house is now an important centre for the arts.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbedrog">Am yr eglwys a phlwyf ger Penfro, gweler Llanbedrog, Sir Benfro.

Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf eglwysig yn ne-orllewin Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Llanbedrog. Mae'n gorwedd ar lan Bae Ceredigion tua hanner ffordd rhwng Pwllheli i'r dwyrain ac Abersoch i'r de. Rhed y ffordd A499 trwy'r pentref.
Mae penrhyn Mynydd Tir y Cwmwd (343 troedfedd) yn ei gysgodi i'r de. O'r copa ceir golygfeydd braf dros Fae Ceredigion ac Ynysoedd Tudwal ac i fryniau Eryri yn y gogledd-ddwyrain.
Mae eglwys y plwyf yn bur hynafol. Fe'i cysegrir i Sant Pedrog. Eglwys un siambr hir ydyw, sy'n dyddio yn rhannol i'r 13eg ganrif. Ychwanegwyd clochdy yn y 19eg ganrif pan gafodd ei hatgyweirio'n sylweddol a'i thrawsnewid gan golli llawer o'i chymeriad hynafol. Mae'r bedyddfaen yn dyddio i'r 15fed ganrif.
Mae traeth Llanbedrog yn ddeniadol ac yn boblogaidd gan ymwelwyr. I'r gogledd ceir craig isel Carreg y Defaid.

Mae Llwybr Arfordir Cymru yn cysylltu Llanbedrog a Phwllheli.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanberis">
            <name>Llanberis</name>
            <lat>53.1180329</lat>
            <lon>-4.127549</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanberis">Llanberis is a village in Gwynedd, North Wales, on the southern bank of the lake Llyn Padarn and at the foot of Snowdon, the highest mountain in Wales. It is a popular centre for outdoor activities in Snowdonia, including walking, mountaineering, climbing, mountain biking and pony trekking as well as water sports such as Scuba Diving. The international fell race known as the Snowdon Race (Welsh: Ras Yr Wyddfa) to the summit of Snowdon begins in the village.
Llanberis takes its name from Saint Peris, an early Welsh saint. It is twinned with the Italian town of Morbegno in Lombardy.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanberis">Pentref mawr a chymuned yng nghalon Eryri, yng Ngwynedd, yw Llanberis. Daw'r enw o sant Peris, er mai eglwys pentref cyfagos Nant Peris oedd y sefydliad gwreiddiol. Sant o'r 6ed ganrif oedd Peris. Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2001, roedd y boblogaeth yn 1,954 ac roedd 81% yn siarad Cymraeg yn rhugl, a 100% o'r bobl ifanc rhwng 10 - 15 oed yn siarad Cymraeg.
Tyfodd y pentref o amgylch Chwarel Dinorwig a chwaraeodd y diwydiant llechi ond bellach y cyflogwr mwyaf yn yr ardal ydy twristiaeth, Pwerdy Dinorwig a gwaith dŵr y Mynydd Trydan; mae yma hefyd ffatrioedd gan gwmniau Siemens Diagnostics a DMM. Gerllaw, saif adfeilion Castell Dolbadarn: castell a godwyd gan Llywelyn II yn y 13eg ganrif. Peiniwyd y llyn a'r castell gan lawer o artistiaid gan gynnwys Richard Wilson and J.M.W. Turner.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llandanwg">
            <name>Llandanwg</name>
            <lat>52.834564</lat>
            <lon>-4.12546</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandanwg">Llandanwg is a village in the Ardudwy area of Gwynedd, Wales.
The village of Llandanwg is situated to the west of the coastal road between Llanbedr and Harlech, close to the village of Llanfair. Originally it was a small collection of farms to the north of the river Artro, close to where it enters the sea. Later developments expanded the size of the village. There is an easily accessible beach, which is popular in the summer months, at the end of the road through the village.
The parish church of Saint Tanwg at Llandanwg is situated just behind the beach in the sand dunes. The church is medieval, probably dating from the 13th century, however there are two 6th century inscribed stones which indicates much earlier activity, and it has probably been a place of worship from the early 5th century.
Llandanwg Halt on the Cambrian Line serves the village.
The area in front of the church, known as the Maes (Y Maes), and some of the sand dunes surrounding the church are owned by the National Trust.
^ Llandanwg - Llanddyvnan', A Topographical Dictionary of Wales (1849), pp. 505-11. URL: http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid=47844</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandanwg">Pentref bychan a phlwyf ar arfordir Ardudwy, de Gwynedd, yw Llandanwg. Lleolir y pentref 2 filltir i'r de o Harlech. Mae'n adnabyddus am ei eglwys ganoloesol a'i draeth llydan.
Mae Llandanwg yn gorwedd ger aber Afon Artro ym Mae Ceredigion, hanner milltir i'r gorllewin o bentref Llanfair. Mae ganddo orsaf ar Reilffordd y Cambrian. Mae'r traeth braf yn denu nifer o ymwelwyr yn yr haf.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanddeiniolen">
            <name>Llanddeiniolen</name>
            <lat>53.17146</lat>
            <lon>-4.181125</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddeiniolen">Llanddeiniolen is a community in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, and is 124.4 miles (200.2km) from Cardiff and 206.0 miles (331.5km) from London. The community also includes the village of Rhiwlas. In 2011 the population of Llanddeiniolen was 4870 with 76.2% of them able to speak Welsh.
Castell Llanddeiniolen motte and baile lies nearby. the name comes from St Deiniol (fl. 550?), a Welsh saint.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddeiniolen">Pentref a chymuned ym mryniau Arfon, Gwynedd, yw Llanddeiniolen. Fe'i lleolir ar y B4366, 5 milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o dref Caernarfon a thua'r un pellter i'r de-orllewin o ddinas Bangor.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llandderfel">
            <name>Llandderfel</name>
            <lat>52.926403</lat>
            <lon>-3.515416</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandderfel">Llandderfel is a village and community in Gwynedd, Wales, formerly served by the Llandderfel railway station. The community also includes the settlement of Rhiwlas. The Community population taken at the 2011 census was 1,095.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandderfel">Pentref gwledig a chymuned yn nwyrain Gwynedd yw Llandderfel, tua 3 milltir i'r dwyrain o'r Bala. Mae plwyf Llandderfel yn un o bump plwyf Penllyn. Mae'n gorwedd yn rhan uchaf Dyffryn Edeirnion yn agos i'r Sarnau a Chefnddwysarn, wrth odre'r Berwyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanddwywe">
            <name>Llanddwywe</name>
            <lat>52.779913</lat>
            <lon>-4.097228</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddwywe">Pentref bychan a phlwyf eglwysig ger arfordir Bae Ceredigion yn ne Gwynedd yw Llanddwywe. Mae'n gorwedd fymryn i'r de o bentref Dyffryn Ardudwy ar ffordd yr A496.
Mae eglwys Llanddwywe yn hynafol. Fe'i cysylltir â'r santes Dwywe, gwraig Dunod Fawr a mam i'r seintiau Deiniol, Cynwyl a Gwarthan, yn ôl traddodiad. Pan fu farw y bardd Wiliam Phylip o Hendrefechan yn 92 oed, cafodd ei gladdu ym mynwent eglwys Llanddwywe ar 11 Chwefror, 1669 : gwelir ei feddrod yno o hyd. Cedwir ar glawr cywydd marwnad iddo gan Phylip Siôn Phylip.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llandecwyn">
            <name>Llandecwyn</name>
            <lat>52.911186</lat>
            <lon>-4.032029</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandecwyn">Llandecwyn is a village stretching from the estuary of the Afon Dwyryd to the hills of the Rhinogs in Gwynedd, Wales. It is served by Llandecwyn railway station. The church lies at an altitude of a little over 150m, and is the only ancient church in Meirionnydd not on the coast (although the present building is actually Victorian). It is dedicated to Saint Tecwyn, and boasts spectacular views over northern parts of Cardigan Bay and across to Portmerion.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandecwyn">Plwyf a phentrefan gwasgaredig yn ardal Ardudwy, de Gwynedd, yw Llandecwyn (cyfeiriad grid SH632375). Yn ôl traddodiad fe'i cysylltir â Sant Tecwyn (fl. 6ed ganrif?), a sefydlodd llan yno. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Talsarnau
Gorwedd y plwyf yng ngogledd-orllewin Ardudwy ar lan ddeheuol Afon Dwyryd. Mae'n ymestyn o'r arfordir i fyny i fryniau gogleddol y Rhinogau. Ceir Llyn Tecwyn Uchaf a Llyn Llennyrch yng ngogledd y plwyf.
Yn yr Oesoedd Canol bu'n rhan o gwmwd Ardudwy Uwch Artro. Prin bod Llandecwyn yn "bentref" o gwbl, ond yn hytrach mae'n gymuned o dai a ffermydd gwasgaredig o gwmpas yr eglwys. Adeilad newydd a godwyd yn 1879 yw'r eglwys bresennol, ond mae'n sefyll ar safle egwlys ganoloesol. Erys carreg o tua'r 11eg ganrif yno, yn coffa'r sant a ddaeth yma, yn ôl traddodiad, yng ngosgordd Cadfan. Ceir Plas Llandecwyn gerllaw.
Brodor o Landecwyn oedd y pregethwr a llenor D. Tecwyn Evans (David Evans). Yma hefyd y ganed J. H. Jones, cyn-olygydd Y Brython.
Ceir gorsaf Llandecwyn ar Reilffordd Arfordir Cymru.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llandegai">
            <name>Llandegai</name>
            <lat>53.216808</lat>
            <lon>-4.100664</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llandwrog">
            <name>Llandwrog</name>
            <lat>53.079079</lat>
            <lon>-4.313792</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandwrog">Llandwrog (Welsh language: meaning 'The church of Saint Twrog') is a village and community in Gwynedd, north-west Wales, most notable for the presence of the headquarters of Welsh record label Sain and the site of Caernarfon Airport. It has a population of 2,466, increasing to 2,539 at the 2011 Census.
As suggested by the village name, the parish church is dedicated St Twrog.
It was the base of the first ever Sea and Mountain Rescue team, and includes the estate of Glynllifon.
RAF Llandwrog was a training airfield during World War II, and was later used as a weapons storage facility. It had a key role in Operation Sandcastle, where a large quantity of Nazi Tabun weapons were stored prior to eventual disposal at sea.
There is a local legend told about a midwife from Llandwrog. It is said that the she was once summoned by a stranger to an underground palace where she helped a queen give birth to a child. The stranger then gave the midwife some ointment for the baby's eyes. When the midwife accidentally touched it to her own eyes, the queen instantly changed into the midwife's former serving-maid, Eilian. Weeks later, when the midwife recognised the mysterious stranger at the local fair, she enquired about Eilian. The stranger replied that Eilian was well, and then asked the midwife which eye she saw him with. When she indicated the eye, he immediately poked it out.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandwrog">Pentref a chymuned ger Caernarfon, Gwynedd, yw Llandwrog. Mae ar yr A499 hanner ffordd rhwng Caernarfon a Chlynnog. Yn ymyl y pentref ceir Parc Glynllifon, hen blasdy mawr sydd bellach yn ganolfan i weithgareddau o bob math. I'r gogledd mae Morfa Dinlle a'i draeth braf a Bae'r Foryd, lle rhed Afon Gwyrfai i'r môr.
Mae'r pentref wedi bod yn gartref i Gwmni Recordiau Sain ers iw stiwdio recordio cyntaf agor ar fferm Gwernafalau yn 1975.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanegryn">
            <name>Llanegryn</name>
            <lat>52.628549</lat>
            <lon>-4.06985</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanegryn">Llanegryn is a village and a community in Gwynedd, north-west Wales. It was formerly part of the historic county of Merionethshire (Welsh: Meirionnydd, Sir Feirionnydd). It is located within Snowdonia National Park south of the Snowdonia (Eryri) mountain range. Travelling by road, it is around 4 miles (6 km) north-east of Tywyn and 17 miles (27 km) south-west of Dolgellau. The nearest railway stations are at Tonfanau and Llwyngwril, both less than 3 miles (5 km) away.
Llanegryn is named for St Egryn, with llan meaning church or parish – a common feature in Welsh place names. The village lies in the Dysynni Valley (Dyffryn Dysynni).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanegryn">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf ym Meirionnydd, de Gwynedd, ar lan ddwyreiniol Dyffryn Dysynni yw Llanegryn. Mae'r pentref yn sefyll chwarter milltir i'r gogledd o lôn yr A493, tua 3 milltir i'r gogledd o Dywyn, ar lethrau isaf yr Allt-lwyd, y bryn cyntaf yn yr esgair hir o fryniau sy'n dringo i gyfeiriad Cadair Idris. Mae Afon Dysynni yn llifo heibio i waelod y pentref.
Mae pont fwa yn croesi ffrwd fechan ar ymyl y pentref. Ychydig o dai sydd yn y pentref ei hun ond ceir tri chapel yno ynghyd â'r eglwys hynafol sy'n sefyll ychydig o'r neilltu i'r pentref ei hun. Mae'r lôn sy'n rhedeg trwy'r pentref yn eich tywys i fyny'r dyffryn i gyfeiriad Castell y Bere a Llanfihangel-y-pennant.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanelltyd">
            <name>Llanelltyd</name>
            <lat>52.756821</lat>
            <lon>-3.904207</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanelltyd">Llanelltyd (Welsh: Llanelltyd) is a small village and community in Gwynedd, to the north of Dolgellau. The Community population taken at the 2011 Census was 517.
It is home to the 12th-century Cymer Abbey, a grade I listed building. St Illtyd's church, one of the oldest parish churches in Wales, is a grade II* listed building.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanenddwyn">
            <name>Llanenddwyn</name>
            <lat>52.78937</lat>
            <lon>-4.103739</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanenddwyn">Pentref bychan ger Dyffryn Ardudwy, Gwynedd yw Llanenddwyn. Yn hanesyddol bu'n blwyf yng nghantref Ardudwy. Fe'i lleolir milltir i'r de o Harlech i'r gorllewin rhwng y ffordd A496 a'r arfordir.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanengan">
            <name>Llanengan</name>
            <lat>52.8136719</lat>
            <lon>-4.532121</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanengan">Llanengan (Welsh for "St. Einion's") is a small village and community 1.2 mi (1.9 km) southwest of Abersoch in Gwynedd in northern Wales. It has a population of 2,024 at the 2001 census, reducing to 1,989 at the 2011 Census.
The parish church is dedicated to Saint Einion Frenin. Established in the late 5th or early 6th century and rebuilt in the late 15th or early 16th, it is one of the oldest churches on the Llŷn peninsula. The popular seaside resort village of Abersoch falls within the community. The local public house is called the Sun.

Lead was formerly obtained from a lead mine just outside the village. A chimney can be seen on the left from the road to Porth Neigwl ("Hell's Mouth"): it marks the entrance to the former lead workings.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanengan">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Llanengan (cyfeiriad grid SH294269). Mae'n gorwedd tuag wyth milltir i'r de-orllewin o dref Pwllheli.
Saif pentref Llanengan heb fod ymhell o'r môr, i'r de-orllewin o Abersoch. Cysegrwyd yr eglwys, sy'n dyddio o oddeutu'r 15fed ganrif, i Sant Engan.
Heblaw pentref Llanengan, mae cymuned Llanengan yn cynnwys pentrefi Abersoch, Mynytho, Bwlchtocyn a Llangïan. Mae'r boblogaeth yn 2,124.
I'r gorllewin ceir traeth llydan Porth Neigwl. Gellir cyrraedd y bae trwy ddilyn lôn o'r pentref i Dai-morfa lle ceir maes pebyllio a llwybr sy'n arwain i'r traeth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfachreth">
            <name>Llanfachreth</name>
            <lat>52.785175</lat>
            <lon>-3.849302</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfachreth">Llanfachreth is a settlement some three miles north-east of Dolgellau (its post town) within the historic boundaries of Merionethshire (Welsh: Meirionnydd, Sir Feirionnydd., Wales. The village is on the slopes of the valley of the river Mawddach and at the foot of Moel Orthrwm. To the south-west on another prominent hill, the Foel Cynwch,is the famous Precipice Walk.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfachreth">Ceir mwy nag un pentref yng Nghymru o'r enw Llanfachreth (ffurf amgen: Llanfachraeth):
Llanfachreth, Ynys Môn (Llanfachraeth) - pentref yng ngogledd-orllewin Môn
Llanfachreth, Gwynedd - pentref ym Meirionnydd, Gwynedd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfaglan">
            <name>Llanfaglan</name>
            <lat>53.117104</lat>
            <lon>-4.287154</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaglan">Llanfaglan is a parish in Gwynedd, north-west Wales. It lay in the medieval cwmwd of Is Gwyrfai.
Llanfaglan is a medieval parish bordering with the parish of Llanbeblig, Caernarfon, on the shore of the Menai Strait and Traeth y Foryd.
The church in Llanfaglan, St Baglan's (Grid reference SH 455 606) stands alone in the middle of a field and is now owned by the Friends of Friendless Churches. In 2005, it was discovered that the church and the older part of the cemetery were part of a pentagonal enclosure. The period of this enclosure isn't known as it is the only one of this type know of in Europe up to now. A 5th or 6th Century gravestone inscribed with Fili Lovernii Anatemori, has been reused as a lintel over the door. This was the gravestone of Anatemarios, mab Loverniws. Although the Christian church probably dates from the 13th century, additions date from the 17th century as do the internal fittings. The church remains consecrated and is still in occasional use.
The church is usually open during the European heritage Open Door weekends in September, where a local historian is on hand to provide visitors with the history of the church, in either Welsh or English.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfaglan">Mae Llanfaglan yn bentref yng Ngwynedd, ar y ffordd gefn rhwng Caernarfon a Llandwrog ac ychydig i'r gogledd o Afon Gwyrfai. Mae'r enw yn dod o enw sant: Baglan ap Dingad mab Dingad ap Nudd Hael (545). Preswyliai gydai frodyr yn Llancafarn ac aeth ar bererindod i Ynys Enlli gyda Sant Dyfrig. Mae yna sawl un yn drysu rhwng y Sant Baglan yma a Sant Baglan Ithel Hael.
Saif Eglwys Sant Baglan gryn bellter o'r pentref presennol, bron 2 km i'r gorllewin ger glan y môr ym mae'r Foryd, ac heb unrhyw adeilad arall yn agos ati. Mae'r rhan hynaf o'r adeilad presennol yn dyddio o'r 13/14 ganrif, a'r capel deheuol yn dyddio o'r 16 ganrif, ac yn ystod 1801-04, fe estynwyd y rhan gorllweinol fel ac y mae heddiw. Mae nifer o gerrig diddorol wedi eu gosod yn y muriau. Uwchlaw'r drws gogleddol mae carreg fedd o ddiwedd y bumed neu ddechrau'r chweched ganrif, a'r arysgrif FILI LOVERNII ANATEMORI neu "(Carreg) Anatemorus fab Loverinus". Ond yn gywir Anatemoori Fili Lovernii yw'r ffordd mae'r ysgrifen ar y garreg yn gywir, gan ei bod ar ei ochr yn y safle presennol. Yma hefyd mae dwy garreg fedd o'r 13eg ganrif ond heb enwau arnynt. Mae llun llong ar un, felly efallai ei bod wedi nodi bedd llongwr.
Yn y cae nesaf i'r gogledd, sef cae ffynnon, wrth waelod y bryn ble mae'r coed, mae safle Ffynnon Faglan, fe chwalwyd unig olion o'r ffynnon tua 2011. Ar un adeg ystyrid y ffynnon yma yn un oedd yn medru iachau anhwylderau.
Mae'r eglwys yn agored fel rheol ar benwythnos cyntaf mis Medi fel rhan o weithgareddau Drysau Agored Treftadaeth Ewrop, a bydd rhywun yno i'ch tywysu o gwmpas, yn Gymraeg. Os ydych angen ymweld ar eglwys hanesyddol hon unrhywdro arall, cysylltwch a'r perchnogion, y Friends of Friendless Churches drwy eu gwefan, neu cysylltwch ag Ifor Williams yn lleol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfair">
            <name>Llanfair</name>
            <lat>52.841288</lat>
            <lon>-4.116563</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfair">Llanfair (Welsh for "St. Mary's Parish") may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfair">Gall Llanfair gyfeirio at:
Llanfair, pentref yn ne Gwynedd, gerllaw Harlech
Llanfair, pentref ym Mro Morgannwg
Llanfair-ar-y-bryn, ger Llanymddyfri yn Sir Gaerfyrddin
Llanfair Caereinion, ym Mhowys
Llanfair Clydogau, yn sir Ceredigion
Llanfair Dyffryn Clwyd, yn Sir Ddinbych
Llanfair-is-gaer, eglwys yn Arfon, Gwynedd
Llanfairfechan, yng Ngwynedd
Llanfair Pwllgwyngyll, ar Ynys Môn
Llanfair Talhaearn, yn Sir Ddinbych
Llanfair ym Muallt, ym Mhowys
Llanfair-yng-Nghornwy, ar Ynys Môn
Llanfair-yn-Neubwll, ar Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfihangel-y-pennant">
            <name>Llanfihangel-y-pennant</name>
            <lat>52.6589747</lat>
            <lon>-3.9357027</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfihangel-y-pennant">This is a redirect from a title with another method of capitalisation. It leads to the title in accordance with the Wikipedia naming conventions for capitalisation, or it leads to a title that is associated in some way with the conventional capitalisation of this redirect title. This may help writing, searching and international language issues. For more information follow the category link.
If this redirect is an incorrect capitalization (a typo), then it is made available to aid searches, so pages that use this link should be updated to link directly to the target.
Use this rcat to tag only mainspace redirects; when other capitalisations are in different namespaces, use {{R from modification}} instead.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfihangel-y-pennant">Mae dau bentref o'r enw Llanfihangel-y-pennant yng Ngwynedd:
Llanfihangel-y-pennant yng Nghwm Pennant
Llanfihangel-y-pennant ger Abergynolwyn, yn enwog fel cartref Mary Jones a gerddodd i'r Bala i gael Beibl gan Thomas Charles</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfihangel-y-traethau">
            <name>Llanfihangel-y-traethau</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfihangel-y-traethau">Pentref bychan a phlwyf yn ardal Ardudwy, de Gwynedd, yw Llanfihangel-y-traethau (cyfeiriad grid SH594353). Mae'r pentref ei hun yn cael ei nodi ar rai mapiau fel "Ynys" yn hytrach na Llanfihangel-y-traethau.
Saif y pentref, sy'n gymuned wasgaredig, ar ochr dwyreiniol y bryniau isel i'r gogledd o wastadedd Morfa Harlech, ar lan y Traeth Bach ac aber Afon Dwyryd, tua tair milltir a hanner i'r gogledd o Harlech. Rhed ffordd yr A496 trwy'r pentref ac mae gorsaf aros ar Reilffordd Arfordir Cymru Tŷ Gwyn (Glan-y-wern) tua chwarter milltir i ffwrdd.
Yn yr Oesoedd Canol Diweddar roedd plwyf Llanfihangel-y-traethau yn rhan o gwmwd Ardudwy Uwch Artro ac yn cynnwys Y Lasynys, cartref Ellis Wynne, awdur Gweledigaethau'r Bardd Cwsg, yn yr 17eg ganrif. Mae'n ymestyn o lan Bae Ceredigion i fyny i ragfryniau'r Rhinogau.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfor">
            <name>Llanfor</name>
            <lat>52.916932</lat>
            <lon>-3.583672</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfor">Llanfor is a village in Gwynedd, Wales near the town of Bala, and Snowdonia.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfor">Pentref ym Meirionnydd, Gwynedd ydy Llanfor, sy'n gorwedd llai na milltir o'r Bala i gyfeiriad Corwen. Yn hanesyddol bu'n ran o Sir Feirionnydd. Llanfawr oedd enw'r pentref yn wreiddiol. Roedd hefyd Frongoch Whiskey Distillery gerllaw ym mhentref Frongoch.
↑ Llanfawr ar genuki.org.uk</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanfrothen">
            <name>Llanfrothen</name>
            <lat>52.951762</lat>
            <lon>-4.051456</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfrothen">Llanfrothen is a community in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, and is 108.1 miles (174.0km) from Cardiff and 193.6 miles (311.6km) from London. In 2011 the population of Llanfrothen was 422 with 70.1% of them able to speak Welsh.
Parc, a Grade II* Listed Building is within the community.
The church at Llanfrothen is dedicated to St Brothen and is a Grade 1 listed building and is in the care of the Friends of Friendless Churches</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfrothen">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Llanfrothen, a leolir ychydig i'r gogledd o dref Penrhyndeudraeth. Saif lle mae'r ffordd B4410 yn croesi'r briffordd A4085.
Gelwir y rhan hynaf o'r pentref yn Garreg, Llanfrothen, ac mae rhannau eraill o'r pentref ar wasgar i'r dwyrain a'r de-ddwyrain i Garreg, ar y ffordd fechan sy'n arwain i bentref Rhyd. Mae yno dafarn adnabyddus, y "Brondanw Arms" ("Y Ring" i bobl leol) ac ysgol gynradd. Ar y ffordd sy'n arwain i gyfeiriad Croesor mae Plas Brondanw, gynt yn gatref i'r pensaer Clough Williams-Ellis.
Gwasanaethodd yr emynydd Richard Jones (Cymro Gwyllt) (1772-1833) fel gweinidog gyda'r Methodistiaid Calfinaidd yn Llanfrothen, lle treuliodd y rhan helaeth o'i oes (roedd yn frodor o blwyf Llanystumdwy, Eifionydd).
Cysegrwyd yr eglwys i Sant Brothen, a oedd yn un o feibion Helig ap Glannog yn ôl traddodiad. Dywedir y claddwyd y sant yno. Ceir Ffynnon Frothen (neu'r Hen Ffynnon) ar bwys yr eglwys. Ceir nifer o nodweddion pensaernïol yn yr eglwys yn cynnwys ffenestr o'r 13eg ganrif. Yn 1888 bu helynt enwog ynghylch hawl i gladdu ym mynwent yr eglwys, a'r achos hwn a ddaeth â David Lloyd George i amlygrwydd am y tro cyntaf. Mae bedd Mary Jones o Minffordd, a lofruddiwyd gan yr Hwntw Mawr yma.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llangelynnin">
            <name>Llangelynnin</name>
            <lat>53.2555488</lat>
            <lon>-3.8451156</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangelynnin">For the village and ancient church of the same name near Fairbourne in the neighbouring county of Gwynedd, see Llangelynnin, Gwynedd.
Llangelynnin (Welsh for The church of Celynnin) is a former parish in the Conwy valley, in Conwy county borough, north Wales. Today the name exists only in connection with the church, a school in the nearby village of Henryd, and the nearby mountain ridge, Craig Celynnin.

Llangelynnin Church (Welsh: Eglwys Llangelynnin) is possibly one of the remotest churches in Wales (53.2458°N 3.8730°W﻿ / 53.2458; -3.8730﻿ (Llangelynnin Church)), and is amongst the oldest; that at Llanrhychwyn, further up the valley, is a little older. The church is dedicated to Saint Celynin, who lived in the 6th century and probably established the first religious settlement here. It lies at a height of just over 900 feet above the village of Henryd in the Conwy valley, in the shelter of Tal y Fan (610m), the hill to the south-west.
A small and simple building, it probably dates from the 12th century (although some sources cite the 13th century), and was probably pre-dated by an earlier church of timber, or wattle and daub construction. Llangelynnin is also the name of the former parish, the primary school in nearby Henryd (Ysgol Llangelynnin). Celynnin's name is also carried by Craig Celynnin, a mountain ridge adjacient to the church.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangelynnin">Gallai Llangelynnin gyfeirio at un o sawl lle:
Llangelynnin, Conwy, pentref bychan a phlwyf yn Nyffryn Conwy
Hen eglwys Llangelynnin, eglwys hanesyddol yn y plwyf uchod
Llangelynnin, Gwynedd, pentref ar arfordir de Gwynedd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llangian">
            <name>Llangian</name>
            <lat>52.831033</lat>
            <lon>-4.533437</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangian">Llangian is a small village and former civil parish on the Llŷn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It is located 1 mile (1.6 km) north west of Abersoch, in the community of Llanengan. The parish was abolished in 1934 and divided between Llanengan and Botwnnog.
The village's church of Saint Cian is connected to the Edwards family of Nanhoron.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llangower">
            <name>Llangower</name>
            <lat>52.8761269</lat>
            <lon>-3.628159</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangower">LLangower is small hamlet on the south end of Bala Lake, Gwynedd, north Wales. It has a closed church and grave yard, a village hall which hosts the annual Sioe Llangywer, a miniature narrow gauge railway holt, and the most beautiful natural spit of land out-crop into Bala Lake, forming a public foreshore and mobile caravan/camping site.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llangwnnadl">
            <name>Llangwnnadl</name>
            <lat>52.866985</lat>
            <lon>-4.669581</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwnnadl">Llangwnnadl is a village and former civil parish in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. The parish was abolished in 1934, and incorporated into Tudweiliog.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwnnadl">Pentref bach ym mhen gorllewinol Llŷn yw Llangwnnadl (neu Llangwnadl), yng Ngwynedd, gogledd-orllewin Cymru.
Lleolir y pentref tua milltir o'r môr rhwng Aberdaron a Nefyn ar ochr ogleddol pen eithaf penrhyn Llŷn. O'r pentref mae lôn gul yn arwain i lawr i Borth Golman ar lan bae agored Porth Sgadan a'i draethau tywod braf.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llangybi">
            <name>Llangybi</name>
            <lat>51.665196</lat>
            <lon>-2.907844</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangybi">Llangybi can refer to one of several villages named after Saint Cybi, their reputed founder.
In Wales
Llangybi, Ceredigion
Llangybi, Gwynedd
Llangybi, Monmouthshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangybi">Ceir mwy nag un enghraifft o'r enw lle Llangybi:
Llangybi, Gwynedd
Llangybi, Ceredigion
Llangybi, Sir Fynwy
Gweler hefyd:
Caergybi, Môn
a'r sant Cybi.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llaniestyn">
            <name>Llaniestyn</name>
            <lat>52.874559</lat>
            <lon>-4.5725749</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaniestyn">Llaniestyn may refer to:
Llaniestyn, Anglesey, Wales
Llaniestyn, Gwynedd, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llaniestyn">Ceir mwy nag un enghraifft o'r enw lle Llaniestyn:
Llaniestyn (Môn) - pentref ar Ynys Môn
Llaniestyn (Gwynedd) - pentref yng Ngwynedd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanllechid">
            <name>Llanllechid</name>
            <lat>53.196424</lat>
            <lon>-4.061664</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanllechid">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf yng Ngwynedd yw Llanllechid. Saif y pentref rhyw bedair milltir i'r de-ddwyrain o ddinas Bangor, rhwng Bangor a Bethesda ac ychydig i'r dwyrain o'r briffordd A5, wrth droed y Carneddau.
Cysegrir eglwys y plwyf i'r Santes Llechid. Bu Evan Evans (Ieuan Fardd) yn gurad yno am gyfnod yn y 18fed ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanllyfni">
            <name>Llanllyfni</name>
            <lat>53.0431696</lat>
            <lon>-4.2829389</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanllyfni">Llanllyfni is a small village and a community in Gwynedd, Wales. The community consists of the villages of Drws-y-coed, Nantlle, Nasareth, Nebo, Penygroes, Talysarn and the village of Llanllyfni itself. As a community the 2011 census recorded a population of 4135. It is a largely Welsh speaking village; 85% of the villagers speak Welsh as their first language.
The river Afon Llyfni (sometimes spelt Afon Llyfnwy), runs through the village. Llanllyfni existed before the slate quarries opened but grew bigger and bigger during the slate quarrying period. In the 2001 census, there were about 650 people living in the village of Llanllyfni.
Llanllyfni is seven miles away from the well-known town of Caernarfon.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanllyfni">Pentref a chymuned yn Nyffryn Nantlle ychydig i'r de o Benygroes yw Llanllyfni. Erbyn hyn mae Penygroes a Llanllyfni bron yn cyffwrdd ei gilydd, gydag Afon Llyfni yn eu gwahanu. Hyd yn ddiweddar yr oedd y briffordd A487 rhwng Caernarfon a Phorthmadog yn rhedeg trwy ganol y pentref, ond yn awr mae ffordd osgoi newydd wedi lleihau'r drafnidiaeth.
Yr adeilad mwyaf diddorol yn y pentref yw Eglwys Sant Rhedyw. Dywedir i'r eglwys gyntaf ar y safle gael ei sefydlu yn y bedwaredd ganrif. Mae traddodiad i Rhedyw (Lladin Redicus) gael ei eni yn Arfon a dod yn swyddog pwysig yn eglwys Augustodunum (Autun heddiw) yng Ngâl. Ei ŵyl Mabsant yw'r 6 Gorffennaf, pan gynheli Gŵyl Rhedyw yn Llanllyfni bob blwyddyn.
Ymysg enwogion Llanllyfni a'r cylch mae Robert Roberts (Silyn), bardd ac arloeswr Cymdeithas Addysg y Gweithwyr, Mathonwy Hughes, bardd a newyddiadurwr, nai Silyn, ac R. Alun Roberts, ysgolhaig ac arbenigwr ar dyfu gweiriau a bridio anifeiliaid. Claddwyd y Parchedig John Jones, Talysarn ym mynwent yr eglwys.
Yn fwy diweddar, mae enwogion fel Cefin Roberts, sefydlwr yr ysgol berfformio 'Glanaethwy', a Bryn Fôn, y canwr ac actor enwog yn dod o Lanllyfni; a mynychodd Bryn Terfel, y canwr opera byd-enwog, Ysgol Gynradd Llanllyfni cyn mynd ymlaen i Ysgol Dyffryn Nantlle.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llannor">
            <name>Llannor</name>
            <lat>52.907855</lat>
            <lon>-4.449218</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llannor">Llannor is a village. parish and community located on the Llŷn Peninsula (Welsh: Penrhyn Llŷn) in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies 1.7 miles (2.8 km) north of Pwllheli and 18.0 miles (29.0 km) south west of Caernarfon. The community includes the villages of Abererch, Efailnewydd and Rhos-fawr, and has a population of 2,244, reducing slightly to 2,145 at the 2011 Census.

The medieval church of the Holy Cross was rebuilt by Henry Kennedy in 1855. Later alterations were made by Harold Hughes in 1905.
It is a grade II* listed building.

^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015. 
^ Office for National Statistics : Census 2001 : Parish Headcounts : Gwynedd Retrieved 13 January 2010
^ "Church of the Holy Cross, Llannor". British Listed Buildings. Retrieved 16 December 2013.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llannor">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Llannor. Saif ar ffordd gefn ychydig i'r gogledd o dref Pwllheli.
Ceir carreg arysgifiedig yma, sy'n coffhau person o'r enw VENDESETI, sy'n cael ei uniaethu a'r sant Gwynhoedl. Cafwyd hyd i ddau faen o wenithfaen a ffurfiai ochrau bedd dir Tir Gwyn; mae'r rhain yn awr i'w gweld yn Oriel Plas Glyn y Weddw.
Ychydig i'r gorllewin mae plasdy Bodfel, a arferai fod yn gartref teulu dylanwadol Wyniaid Bodfel.
Mae Cymuned Llannor yn cynnwys pentrefi Abererch a Rhos-fawr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanrug">
            <name>Llanrug</name>
            <lat>53.147852</lat>
            <lon>-4.194649</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrug">Llanrug (or Llanfihangel-yn-y-grug) is a large village in Gwynedd, north-west Wales. It lies about 4 miles to the east of Caernarfon, 7 miles south of Bangor and 3 miles northwest of Llanberis. It is the largest populated village in the Arfon area of Gwynedd, Wales. The old name term of the village was initially Llanfihangel-y-Rug, derived from Eglwys Sant Mihangel situated about half a mile west of the village. It has a Welsh-speaking community of 81% and a population of 2,911. The busy A4086 road from Llanberis Pass to Caernarfon runs through the village.
^ "Welsh language skills and community population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrug">Pentref gweddol fawr a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Llanrug. Saif 4 milltir i'r gorllewin o dref Caernarfon, 7 milltir i'r de o Fangor ar y briffordd A4086 rhwng Caernarfon a Llanberis sydd 3 milltir i'r gogledd orllewin.
Llifa Afon Rhythallt heibio'r pentref, gan newid ei henw i Afon Seiont ar ôl llifo dan Bont Rhythallt. Mae ysgol uwchradd Ysgol Brynrefail yma. Yn fras, saif tua hanner ffordd rhwng Afon Menai a'r Wyddfa. I'r dde o'r pentref gwelir ucheldir Cefn Du; i'r de-ddwyrain cwyd yr Wyddfa a'i chriw, ac i'r dwyrain y ddwy Elidir gyda thomennydd y chwarel llechi.
Llanrug yw'r pentref mwyaf yn ardal Arfon yn sir Gwynedd gyda'r canran uchaf (81%) o siaradwyr Cymraeg a phoblogaeth o tua 2,500. Enw gwreiddiol y pentref oedd Llanfihangel-yn-y-Grug a enwyd ar ôl yr eglwys Sant Mihangel sydd tua hanner milltir i'r gorllewin o'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanuwchllyn">
            <name>Llanuwchllyn</name>
            <lat>52.8550757</lat>
            <lon>-3.6682978</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanuwchllyn">Llanuwchllyn is a village and community in Gwynedd, Wales, near the southern end of Bala Lake (Llyn Tegid). Its population according to the United Kingdom Census 2001 was 834, of whom about 81% were Welsh-speaking. The figures for the 2011 census were:population 617:welsh speakers 82%.
The parish church of St Deiniol is a grade II* listed building. 
Llanuwchllyn railway station is the headquarters of the narrow gauge Bala Lake Railway, centred on the former Great Western Railway station on the standard-gauge line from Ruabon to Barmouth.
The village was the birthplace of Welsh language author and educationalist Owen Morgan Edwards.
Caer gai, a Roman fort near Llanuwchllyn, was traditionally known as the home of Cei, the character in the Arthurian legend known in English as Sir Kay. Poets of the 15th century recorded a story, ultimately deriving from the Prose Merlin included in the Lancelot-Grail and the Post-Vulgate Cycle, that King Arthur and Cei were brought up at Caer-gai as foster brothers. Caer gai is also grade II* listed. 

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanuwchllyn">Pentref a chymuned tua dwy filltir i'r de o ben deheuol Llyn Tegid ym Meirionnydd, Gwynedd yw Llanuwchllyn. Mae'n sefyll oddi ar yr A494, 5 milltir i'r de-orllewin o'r Bala, yn rhimyn hir ar hyd y B4403. Adnabyddir y pen gogleddol fel 'Y Llan' a'r pen deheuol fel 'Y Pandy'. Mae'r gofgolofn i O.M. Edwards a'i fab Ifan yn sefyll wrth y briffordd. Yr ysgol gymunedol leol yw Ysgol O. M. Edwards, a enwir ar ôl yr addysgwr enwog.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanwnda">
            <name>Llanwnda</name>
            <lat>53.101171</lat>
            <lon>-4.276897</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanwnda">Llanwnda may refer to:
Llanwnda, Gwynedd
Llanwnda, Pembrokeshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanwnda">Gall Llanwnda gyfeirio at:
Llanwnda, pentref yng Ngwynedd
Llanwnda, pentref yn Sir Benfro</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanycil">
            <name>Llanycil</name>
            <lat>52.9006423</lat>
            <lon>-3.6157727</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanycil">Llanycil is a community in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, and is 99.9 miles (160.7km) from Cardiff and 176.2 miles (283.6km) from London. In 2011 the population of Llanycil was 404 with 80.4% of them able to speak Welsh.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanycil">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf yng Ngwynedd ydy Llanycil, sydd wedi ei leoli tua 12 milltir i'r de orllewin o Gorwen a 15 milltir i'r gogledd ddwyrain o Dolgellau. Hyd 1974 bu'n ran o Sir Feirionnydd.
Cysgegrir eglwys y plwyf i sant Beuno.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanymawddwy">
            <name>Llanymawddwy</name>
            <lat>52.759817</lat>
            <lon>-3.636243</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanymawddwy">Llanymawddwy is a village in Gwynedd, Wales, which is to the north of the larger village of Dinas Mawddwy, on the minor road which connects Dinas Mawddwy to Llanuwchllyn over Bwlch y Groes. The most notable building is St. Tydecho parish church, where the tradition of singing Matins endures.

Alfred George Edwards, the first Archbishop of the disestablished Church in Wales, was born in Llanymawddwy in 1848.
According to local tradition, Bryn Hall was once haunted by a headless horseman. The haunting is said to have ceased after a grave belonging to the Lord's illegitimate child was found near the hall.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanymawddwy">Mae Llanymawddwy yn bentref yng Ngwynedd sydd ychydig i'r gogledd o bentref mwy Dinas Mawddwy, ar y ffordd fechan sy'n cysylltu Dinas Mawddwy a Llanuwchllyn tros Fwlch y Groes. Mae Afon Dyfi, sy'n tarddu ar Aran Fawddwy gerllaw, yn llifo heibio'r pentref. Daw'r enw o gwmwd Mawddwy. Yr adeilad mwyaf nodedig yw Eglwys Sant Tydecho, lle mae traddodiad canu'r Plygain yn parhau.

Yn Llanymawddwy y ganed Alfred George Edwards, a ddaeth yn Archesgob cyntaf Cymru, a bu'r llenor a geiriadurwr Daniel Silvan Evans yn rheithor yma.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llanystumdwy">
            <name>Llanystumdwy</name>
            <lat>52.9224699</lat>
            <lon>-4.270503</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanystumdwy">Llanystumdwy is a village and community on the Llŷn Peninsula of Gwynedd in Wales, although it is not regarded as being part of Llŷn, but belonging instead to the local region of Eifionydd.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanystumdwy">Pentref a chymuned yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd, gogledd Cymru yw Llanystumdwy. Saif ar yr A497 rhwng Cricieth a Pwllheli, ar lannau Afon Dwyfor. Ystyr yr enw yw "yr eglwys wrth y tro ar Afon Dwy".
Mae'n enwog am ei chysylltiadau â Lloyd George. Treuliodd y 'Dewin Cymreig' ei blentyndod yn y pentref tan oedd yn 15eg oed, yng ngofal ei ewythr Richard Lloyd, crydd wrth ei grefft a gweinidog cynorthwyol yn y capel lleol: Capel Moreia. Cafodd Lloyd George ei gladdu yn Llanystumdwy.
Mae'n bentref deniadol lle gwelir nifer o fythynnod a thai sy'n dyddio o'r 17eg ganrif a'r 18fed ganrif, wedi'u hadeiladu o gerrig tywyll lleol. Mae pont ddwy fwa sy'n dyddio o'r 17eg ganrif ar Afon Dwyfawr ar gyrion Llanystumdwy.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llecheiddior">
            <name>Llecheiddior</name>
            <lat>52.968912</lat>
            <lon>-4.271393</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llechfraith">
            <name>Llechfraith</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#lleyn peninsula (penrhyn llyn)">
            <name>Lleyn Peninsula (Penrhyn Llyn)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llidiardau">
            <name>Llidiardau</name>
            <lat>52.929397</lat>
            <lon>-3.677604</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llithfaen">
            <name>Llithfaen</name>
            <lat>52.960504</lat>
            <lon>-4.447881</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llithfaen">Llithfaen is a small village on the Llŷn Peninsula in Gwynedd, Wales. It is located around 4 miles north-east of Nefyn and lies just south-west of Yr Eifl mountains, on the B4417 road from Llanaelhaearn to Nefyn. Formerly in the parish of Nant Gwrtheyrn, it is now in the Pistyll community.
Two businesses in the village are run by the community - the Tafarn Y Fic pub, and Siop Pen-y-Groes - the village shop.
There used to be three quarries close to the village, the last of which (Chwarel Carreg y Llam) closed in 1963. The population grew at the opening of a quarry granite on Yr Eifl in the 19th century. Many houses were built and the census in 1881 shows a large number of immigrants from other areas of the peninsula, Penmaenmawr and as far as Scotland. In the first half of the 19th century, before the opening of the granite quarries in Nant Gwrtheyrn, many smallholders supplemented their incomes by taking heather cut from the slopes of Tre'r Ceiri to be sold as kindling in Pwllheli for sixpence a bundle.
As of 2002, musician Ian Brown had a holiday home in the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llithfaen">Mae Llithfaen yn bentref ar arfordir gogleddol penrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd (cyfeiriad grid SH356431). Saif ger llechweddau deheuol Yr Eifl ar y ffordd B4417 o Lanaelhaearn i Nefyn.

Tyfodd y boblogaeth pan agorwyd nifer o chwareli gwenithfaen ar yr Eifl yn y 19eg ganrif. Adeiladwyd llawer o dai newydd ac mae cyfrifiad 1881 yn dangos nifer fawr o fewnfudwyr o ardaloedd eraill yn Llŷn ei hun, o Benmaenmawr a chyn belled â'r Alban. Yn hanner cyntaf y 19eg ganrif, cyn agor chwareli llithfaen lleol fel yr un yn Nant Gwrtheyrn, arferai nifer o dyddynwyr y plwyf ychwanegu at eu hincwm trwy dorri grug ar lethrau Tre'r Ceiri a'i gludo ar eu cefnau yn feichiau mawr i'w werthu fel tanwydd ym marchnad Pwllheli am 6 cheiniog y baich.
Mae yno siop sydd yn gael ei redeg gan y gymuned a Thafarn Y Fic, sydd hefyd yn cael ei rhedeg gan gwmni cydweithredol.
O bentref Llithfaen mae modd cyrraedd Nant Gwrtheyrn ar hyd lôn sy'n arwain tua'r gogledd i gyfeiriad y môr. Yma y sefydlwyd y Ganolfan Iaith Genedlaethol. Ar un o dri chopa'r Eifl mae bryngaer enwog Tre'r Ceiri.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#lliw">
            <name>Lliw</name>
            <lat>51.7499472</lat>
            <lon>-3.9432855</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lliw">Nodwedd sy'n deillio o'r goleuni gweladwy y mae gwrthrychau'n ei daflu, ei drosglwyddo, neu ei gynhyrchu, yw lliw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llwyndyrys">
            <name>Llwyndyrys</name>
            <lat>52.941755</lat>
            <lon>-4.420597</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#llwyngwril">
            <name>Llwyngwril</name>
            <lat>52.6662869</lat>
            <lon>-4.0843239</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llwyngwril">Llwyngwril is a coastal village and post town, 2 miles north of Llangelynnin and 4 miles south of Barmouth, in the county of Gwynedd, Wales.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llwyngwril">Pentref yn ne Gwynedd yw Llwyngwril. Fe'i lleolir ar arfordir Bae Ceredigion dwy filltir i'r gogledd o Langelynnin a phedair milltir i'r de o Abermaw.
Ceir gorsaf reilfordd ger y pentref ar lein Rheilffordd Arfordir Cymru.

Yn y bryniau hanner milltir i'r de o Lwyngwril ceir bryngaer Castell y Gaer.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#lon">
            <name>Lon</name>
            <lat>51.5042858</lat>
            <lon>-0.1259551</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lon">Lon or LON may refer to:
Launch on Need, a Space Shuttle rescue mission which would have been mounted to rescue the crew of a Space Shuttle if needed
League of Nations, the first permanent international organization for maintaining world peace, predecessor of the United Nations
Legends of Norrath, an online trading-card game by Sony Online Entertainment
Local oxidation nanolithography, a nanofabrication technique
LonTalk, protocol for electronic automation networks
LonWorks, a control network protocol
LON, the IATA airport code covering all airports within the London area of the United Kingdom, see Airports of London
Lon protease family
Longitude</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#machroes">
            <name>Machroes</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#maentwrog">
            <name>Maentwrog</name>
            <lat>52.9441739</lat>
            <lon>-3.988467</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maentwrog">Maentwrog is a village and community in the Welsh county of Gwynedd, lying in the Vale of Ffestiniog just below Blaenau Ffestiniog, within the Snowdonia National Park. The River Dwyryd runs alongside the village. It has a population of 585, increasing to 631 at the 2011 Census.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maentwrog">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Maentwrog, a leolir lle mae'r ffordd A496 o Harlech i Flaenau Ffestiniog yn croesi'r A487 o Borthmadog. Saif ar Afon Dwyryd ac mae'r Moelwyn Bach i'r gogledd a Llyn Trawsfynydd i'r de. Maentwrog oedd y lle uchaf y gellid ei gyrraedd ar hyd Afon Dwyryd mewn cychod o faint sylweddol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#maesgeirchen">
            <name>Maesgeirchen</name>
            <lat>53.2231995</lat>
            <lon>-4.1172318</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maesgeirchen">Maesgeirchen is a large housing estate on the edge of the city of Bangor in Gwynedd, north-west Wales, with roughly 4,000 inhabitants.
It was originally constructed in the late 1930s, with more homes being added after World War II and in recent years. In 2003, the local council-owned pre-war homes on the estate underwent an expansive home-improvement scheme funded by the council, which saw them all fitted with double-glazing and central heating, as well as maintenance and modernisation work to both the interior and exterior of the buildings. It is the third largest single housing estate in Wales behind Gurnos, Merthyr Tydfil, the second largest and Caia Park in Wrexham, which is the largest with nearly 12,000 inhabitants.
The estate is located away from the main spread of the city of Bangor, being separated by Bangor Mountain. The name of the estate is often shortened to a simpler "Maes-G" in casual use, by residents of both the estate and the city. Maesgeirchen was named after the farm Maes-y-geirchen which was situated near Queens Avenue.

The estate has only one road entrance and exit, via "Maes-G Hill" (official road name: Penrhyn Avenue), which gives the residents of Maesgeirchen a strong sense of community. There are also numerous un-made footpaths leading to and from the estate; one called Lôn Felin Esgob (meaning "Bishop's mill lane"), is an old highway with some of the paving still in place, north it goes over Bangor Mountain towards the city and south is goes towards and through the nearby Llandegai industrial estate. Recently there have been major environmental works throughout the river area including walkways, paths, and picnic areas designed for use by pedestrians and wheelchair users.
The estate also boasts its own residents' organisation and communities first division which is being run by locals. The estate was fitted, in 2002, with CCTV which covers the majority of streets. It has a social club, a community centre (Ty Cegin - built with National Lottery funding as a Healthy Living Centre and later taken over by the local Communities First Partnership following cessation of five years of Lottery funding), a newsagent, a post office, a hairdresser, a chip shop, a Chinese take-away, a laundrette, a church and a primary school named Ysgol Glan Cegin. Bus services into the estate until 2006 were provided exclusively by Arriva Buses Wales, but now there is competition from Padarn Bus following a request by residents unhappy with Arriva's service.
Maesgeirchen is designated a 'Communities First' area by the Welsh Assembly Government.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#mallwyd">
            <name>Mallwyd</name>
            <lat>52.696534</lat>
            <lon>-3.683317</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mallwyd">Mallwyd is a small village at the most southern end of the county of Gwynedd, Wales in the valley of the River Dyfi. It lies on the A470 approximately half-way between Dolgellau and Machynlleth, and forms the junction of the A458 towards Welshpool. The nearest village is Dinas Mawddwy, two miles to the north, and Aberangell to the south. The River Dugoed flows into the River Dyfi near the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mallwyd">Pentref bychan a phlwyf yn ne-ddwyrain Gwynedd yw Mallwyd. Fe'i lleolir yn nyffryn Afon Dyfi ar lôn priffordd yr A470 tua hanner ffordd rhwng Dolgellau a Machynlleth. Ar bwys y pentref mae cyffordd yr A458 o gyfeiriad Y Trallwng. Y pentrefi agosach yw Dinas Mawddwy, tua dwy filltir i'r gogledd, ac Aberangell i'r de. Mae Afon Dugoed yn aberu yn Afon Dyfi ger y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#marian-y-de (south beach)">
            <name>Marian-y-de (South Beach)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#marian-y-mor (west end)">
            <name>Marian-y-mor (West End)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#mawddach">
            <name>Mawddach</name>
            <lat>52.8285651</lat>
            <lon>-3.8231311</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#minffordd">
            <name>Minffordd</name>
            <lat>52.924667</lat>
            <lon>-4.0904049</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minffordd">Minffordd (roadside in Welsh) is a village within the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It is situated on the A487 road between Porthmadog and Penrhyndeudraeth.
The village has two adjacent railway stations, which are served both by Cambrian Line mainline train services and the narrow gauge Ffestiniog Railway. In the 1992 the Ffestiniog Railway built a hostel to house volunteers working on the line.
The stations are approximately quarter of a mile from the start of the mile-long drive to the Italianate hotel-village of Portmeirion.
Nearby are the minor remains of a medieval castle (known variously as Castell Deudraeth, Castell Gwain Goch and Castell Aber Iau). The castle was first recorded by Giraldus Cambrensis (Gerald of Wales) in 1188.
Garth Quarry was opened in 1870 to produce granite setts for transport to developing towns and cities by the newly opened Cambrian Railways. The quarry now produces roadstone and railway ballast.
Ysbyty Bron y Garth was built as the Ffestiniog Union Workhouse in 1839 at a cost of £3,200 and was intended to house 150 inmates. In recent years the buildings were used as a community hospital operated by North West Wales NHS Trust. In 2009 the hospital was replaced by Ysbyty Alltwen at Tremadog. Part of the site houses over 400 lesser horseshoe bats.
Minffordd is a thriving Welsh speaking village, where the language is used everyday.
^ John Dobson and Roy Woods, Ffestiniog Railway Traveller's Guide, Festiniog Railway Company, Porthmadog, 2004
^ Cyngor Gwynedd : Meirionnydd Area Committee : 14 January 2008</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minffordd">Gall Minffordd gyfeirio at un o nifer o bentrefi yng Nghymru;
Minffordd rhwng Porthmadog a Penrhyndeudraeth.
Minffordd ger Tal-y-Llyn, gerllaw Cader Idris.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#minllyn">
            <name>Minllyn</name>
            <lat>52.713685</lat>
            <lon>-3.691511</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minllyn">Pentref bychan yn ne Gwynedd, gogledd Cymru yw Minllyn. Mae'n gorwedd ar lan orllewinol Afon Dyfi ar y ffordd A470 rhwng Dinas Mawddwy i'r gogledd a Mallwyd i'r de.
Roedd Rheilffordd Mawddwy yn gwasanaethu'r chwareli llechi ym Minllyn ac Aberangell.
Mae Pont Minllyn ar afon Dyfi yn adeilad cofrestredig sydd yng ngofal Cadw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#moel tryfan">
            <name>Moel Tryfan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moel Tryfan">Moel Tryfan (429 m / 1407 ft) is a small mountain near the villages of Rhosgadfan, Y Fron and Betws Garmon, in northern Gwynedd. The higher and more famous peak of Tryfan above Dyffryn Ogwen has also sometimes been referred to as "Moel Tryfan" in the past.
Moel Tryfan could be regarded as the westerly outlier of the larger Mynydd Mawr. The southern and eastern flanks of the mountain were heavily quarried in the past, particularly at Moel Tryfran Quarry and Cilgwyn quarry.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moel Tryfan">Mynydd bychan yn Eryri ger pentrefi Rhosgadfan, Y Fron a Betws Garmon yng ngogledd Gwynedd yw Moel Tryfan (1400' / 427m). Ni ddylid ei gymysgu a'r mynydd adnabyddus Tryfan, ger Llyn Ogwen (cyfeirir at y mynydd hwnnw mewn ambell hen lyfr fel "Moel Tryfan").
Gellid ystyried Moel Tryfan fel parhad gorllewinol o'r Mynydd Mawr, a wahanir oddi wrtho gan fwlch llydan. Ar lethrau deheuol a dwyreiniol y mynydd ceir olion sylweddol o'r chwareli llechi a fu mor brysur yno yn y gorffennol, yn cynnwys Chwarel Moel Tryfan a Chwarel Alexandra (Cors y Bryniau).
Mae Kate Roberts yn sôn am y mynydd a'r ardal yn ei chyfrol hunangofiannol Y Lôn Wen. Cafodd yr awdur Dic Tryfan ei lysenw o'r mynydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#morfa">
            <name>Morfa</name>
            <lat>52.1484521</lat>
            <lon>-4.4774035</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa">Morfa may refer to:
Conwy Morfa, North Wales, United Kingdom
Morfa, Swansea, South Wales, United Kingdom
Morfa (drug), a highly potent opiate analgesic drug</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa">Erthygl am y tirffurff yw hon. weler hefyd Morfa (gwahaniaethu).
Darn o wastatir isel, gan amlaf ar lan y môr ac yn enwedig ger aber afon, a orchuddir gan ddŵr o dro i dro, yw morfa. Mae'r defnydd o'r gair yn amrywio a gellir ei gymhwyso i ddisgrifio unrhyw gorstir neu gors, neu ros gwlyb neu weundir ar lan aber. Y term agosaf yn Saesneg yw salt-marsh neu sea marsh (er bod y term geiriadurol 'morfa hallt' wedi cael ei fachu am hynny).
Er ei fod yn dir diffrwyth ar un olwg, mae morfeydd yn gynefin bwysig i fywyd gwyllt, yn enwedig planhigion ac adar.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#morfa bychan">
            <name>Morfa Bychan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa Bychan">Morfa Bychan is a village located in Gwynedd, North Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa Bychan">Pentref arfordirol yng Ngwynedd yw Morfa Bychan. Saif i'r de-orllewin o dref Porthmadog ac i'r dwyrain o Gricieth, ar ochr ogleddol aber Afon Glaslyn lle mae'n cyrraedd Bae Tremadog.
Mae'n lle poblogaidd iawn gan dwristiaid yn yr haf, yn enwedig oherwydd traeth Morfa Bychan, Black Rock Sands yn Saesneg, sy'n ymestyn o'r pentref i gyfeiriad Cricieth. Caniateir gyrru ceir ar y traeth yma. Ceir nifer o siopau a thafarnau yma ynghyd â sawl gwersyll carafanau.
Gerllaw mae gwarchodfa natur Morfa Bychan, yn perthyn i Ymddiriedolaeth Natur Gogledd Cymru, ac heb fod ymhell o'r pentref mae'r Garreg Wen, cartref y cerddor Dafydd y Garreg Wen. Y tu ôl i'r pentref ceir bryn Moel y Gest.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#morfa nefyn">
            <name>Morfa Nefyn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa Nefyn">Morfa Nefyn is a small village located on the northern coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. Historically, it is part of Caernarfonshire.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morfa Nefyn">Mae Morfa Nefyn yn bentref bychan rhyw filltir i'r gorllewin o dref Nefyn ar y B4417 ar arfordir gogleddol Penrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd. Saif ar fae Porth Dinllaen sydd rhwng Trwyn Porth Dinllaen a Phenrhyn Nefyn.
Pentref bychan yw Morfa Nefyn, gydag un dafarn a bad achub. Roedd yma waith brics o 1868 hyd 1906, ac ar un adeg roedd yn borthladd eithaf prysur. Mae'n le poblogaidd i dwristaid oherwydd y cwrs golff a chyfleusterau hwylio.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#myndd llandegai">
            <name>Myndd Llandegai</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#mynydd gilan">
            <name>Mynydd Gilan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#mynytho">
            <name>Mynytho</name>
            <lat>52.85201</lat>
            <lon>-4.5147389</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynytho">Mynytho is a small village in the parish of Llangian near the southern coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in north-west Wales. It consists of only a few houses, beautiful scenery and some farmland. There are also campsites scattered around the village's outskirts.
Mynytho's memorial hall  occupies a significant place in the history of the struggle for the recognition of Welsh culture and the Welsh language.
The following englyn by the poet R. Williams Parry appears on a plaque mounted on the wall of the hall.
Adeiladwyd gan dlodi, — nid cerrig

Ond cariad yw'r meini;

Cydernes yw'r coed arni,
Cyd-ddyheu a'i cododd hi.

In English this means
It is built of poverty, not stones

But love is its masonry,

Shared aspirations are its timber,
And shared commitment is what raised it up.

Another notable Welsh poet, Richard Goodman Jones (aka Dic Goodman) is a resident of the village.
Mynytho is also the site of a small yet highly visible tower that stands on a hill (Foel Tŵr) overlooking the area. The tower, which is popularly known to English residents as the "Jampot", is an old windmill but was never a success due to crosswinds on the hill, it is identified on maps as being an old mill. The land (Foel Tŵr) on which it stands is owned by the National Trust.
The community supports its own large chapel called Horeb, which stands close to the common land and a spring  said to have healing properties. Of historical interest is the older (18th century) but disused chapel (Capel Newydd) which stands on the left hand side of the road to Nanhoron.
Neighbouring villages and settlements include Llanbedrog, Abersoch, Llangian, Nanhoron, Rhydyclafdy and Botwnnog.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynytho">Pentref bychan ym Mhen Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Mynytho. Fe'i lleolir tua 2 filltir i'r gorllewin o Lanbedrog a tua'r un pellter i'r gogledd o Abersoch yn ne-orllewin Llŷn.
Anfarwolwyd y Neuadd Goffa yn yr englyn canlynol gan y bardd R. Williams Parry sydd i'w weld ar furiau'r neuadd:
Adeiladwyd gan dlodi, — nid cerrig
Ond cariad yw'r meini;
Cydernes yw'r coed arni,
Cyd-ddyheu a'i cododd hi.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nannau">
            <name>Nannau</name>
            <lat>52.7704218</lat>
            <lon>-3.8648358</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nannau">Nannau is a historic summer estate house in Bar Harbor, Maine. Located between Maine State Route 3 and overlooking Compass Harbor, this 1904 Shingle style house was built for David R. Ogden, a New York City lawyer, to designs by the Boston firm Andrews, Jaques and Rantoul. The house was characterized in 1906 as "an excellent example of shingle work"; it was listed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1984.
^ a b "National Register Information System". National Register of Historic Places. National Park Service. 2010-07-09.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nannau">Plasdy hynafol ac ystâd ym mhlwyf Llanfachreth, Meirionnydd, ac enw'r teulu a drigai yno yw Nannau.
Roedd teulu Nannau yn ddisgynyddion o dywysogion Powys trwy ei hynafiad Ynyr Hen (yn fyw ar ddechrau'r 13eg ganrif). Roedd y teulu yn ewnog fel noddwyr beirdd y cyfnod a dethlir y plasdy mewn sawl cerdd o'r 14eg ganrif ymlaen. Roedd y bardd Llywelyn Goch ap Meurig Hen yn perthyn i'r teulu. Ystyrir Siôn Dafydd Las (bu farw 1694), bardd teulu Nannau, yn un o'r olaf o'r beirdd teulu traddodiadol yng Nghymru.
Unwyd ystadau Nannau a Hengwrt ar ddechrau'r 18fed ganrif pan briododd Robert Vaughan, gorwyr yr hynafiaethydd enwog Robert Vaughan o Hengwrt, ac un o wyresau Huw Nannau, yntau'n noddwr a hynafiaethydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nant peris">
            <name>Nant Peris</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nant Peris">Pentref bychan y Eryri yw Nant Peris. Saif ychydig i'r de-ddwyrain o Lyn Peris a phentref Llanberis, ac mae Bwlch Llanberis yn arwain ymlaen i'r de-ddwyrain o'r pentref.
Cysegrwyd yr eglwys i Sant Peris; hwn yw'r sefydliad gwreiddiol yn hytrach na Llanberis. Heb fod ymhell o'r eglwys mae Ffynnon Peris. Yn ôl traddodiad roedd dau frithyll yn arfer byw yn y ffynnon, ac os byddai'r sawl fyddai'n ymweld â'r ffynnon i geisio iachad yn gweld y brithyll, byddai ei gais yn llwyddiannus.
Mae'r pentref yn ganolfan boblogaidd gan ddringwyr, ac mae maes gwersylla yno; ceir hefyd un dafarn, Y Vaynol Arms. Gellir parcio yma a chymeryd bws "Sherpa'r Wyddfa" i Ben-y-pas ar gyfer dringo'r Wyddfa.
Mae "Nant Peris" neu "Afon Nant Peris" hefyd yn enw ar yr afon sy'n llifo i lawr Bwlch Llanberis a heibio'r pentref; a defnyddir "Nant Peris" fel enw arall ar Fwlch Llanberis ei hun hefyd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nant peris (old llanberis)">
            <name>Nant Peris (Old Llanberis)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nantlle">
            <name>Nantlle</name>
            <lat>53.057533</lat>
            <lon>-4.2228009</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nantlle">Nantlle is a small village in the slate quarrying Nantlle Valley in Gwynedd, Wales. It lies on the north shore of Llyn Nantlle Uchaf and is part of the community of Llanllyfni.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nantlle">Pentref yn Nyffryn Nantlle, Gwynedd yw Nantlle. Saif ar y ffordd B4418 rhwng Talysarn a Rhyd Ddu.
Tyfodd pentref Nantlle fel pentref i'r gweithwyr yn y chwareli llechi cyfagos, ac mae olion y chwareli hynny i'w gweld ymhobman o gwmpas y pentref, yn enwedig i'r gogledd. I'r de o'r pentref mae Llyn Nantlle Uchaf, sydd ag Afon Drws-y-coed yn llifo i mewn iddo ac Afon Llyfni yn tarddu ohono.

Cyfeirir at nifer o leoedd yn ardal Nantlle ym mhedwaredd gainc y Mabinogi, chwedl Math fab Mathonwy. Dywedir fod y gair "Nantlle" ei hun yn dod o "Nant Lleu".
Ar un adeg roedd dau lyn yma, fel y gwelir yn yr enw "Baladeulyn". Gyda datblygiad y chwareli fe wacawyd y dŵr o'r llyn arall, Llyn Nantlle Isaf, a newidiwyd cwrs Afon Llyfni. Yn ffermdy Talymignedd Uchaf gerllaw'r pentref y ganwyd Margaret Evans, "Marged Fwyn Uch Ifan" (ferch Ifan), sy'n cael ei choffáu yn y pennill:
Mae gan Marged fwyn Uch Ifan
Delyn fawr a thelyn fechan;
Un i ganu'n nhre Caernarfon
A'r llall i gadw'r gŵr yn fodlon.
Lleolir Ysgol Baladeulyn yn y pentref. Mae papur bro Lleu yn gwasanaethu Nantlle.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nantmor">
            <name>Nantmor</name>
            <lat>52.991046</lat>
            <lon>-4.081446</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nantmor">Nantmor is a hamlet which lies about 1½ miles to the south of the village of Beddgelert in Gwynedd, Wales.
The current spelling of the name Nantmor is more modern – most old documents [1] from the 16th to the 18th century record the name as Nanmor.
It lies close to the scenic Aberglaslyn Pass and the Welsh Highland Railway. Nantmor station has re-opened, following a 2007 vote in its favour by local residents.
A car park run by the National Trust is a popular starting point for walks up Cwm Bychan or along the Aberglaslyn.
The village is perhaps most famous for being the home of Dafydd Nanmor, a renowned 15th century bard (died c. 1490), who took his name from the hamlet, as did Rhys Nanmor after him. Dafydd Nanmor himself was possibly a bardic student of Rhys Goch, who lived at neighbouring Hafod Garegog.
Filmed in Nantmor in 1957 the Inn of the Sixth Happiness is a 1958 American 20th Century Fox film based on the true story of Gladys Aylward, a tenacious British maid, who became a missionary in China during the tumultuous years leading up to World War II.
Carneddi, a nearby hill farm, was the home of Ruth Janette Ruck, who published a trilogy of books about her experiences in the 1950s, '60s and '70s, namely Place of Stones, Hill Farm Story and Along Came a Llama. In 1980 she featured in the HTV About Britain series in an episode called "The Lady and the Llama", which featured a year on the farm. [2]

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nantmor">Pentref bychan yng Ngwynedd yw Nantmor (hefyd Nanmor, efallai yn wreiddiol Nanmor Deudraeth). Saif ynghanol Eryri, ychydig i'r de o bentref Beddgelert, ar ffordd gefn fymryn i'r dwyrain o'r briffordd A4085, rhwng Aberglaslyn a Garreg, Llanfrothen. I'r gogledd-ddwyrain o'r pentref mae Blaen Nanmor.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nantygwryd">
            <name>Nantygwryd</name>
            <lat>53.0891434</lat>
            <lon>-3.9662675</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nasareth">
            <name>Nasareth</name>
            <lat>53.026188</lat>
            <lon>-4.281727</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nasareth">Nasareth (named for the biblical Nazareth), is a hamlet in the Nantlle Valley in Gwynedd, north Wales.
The Councillor for Nasareth is Owen Penant Huws, which covers Llanllyfni and surrounding villages.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nasareth">Ceir mwy nag un lle o'r enw Nasareth neu Nazareth:
Nasareth - tref yng Ngalilea
Nasareth - pentref yng Ngwynedd
Nazareth - tref yn nhalaith Pennsylvania, yr Unol Daleithiau</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nebo">
            <name>Nebo</name>
            <lat>53.0300719</lat>
            <lon>-4.269537</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebo">Nebo may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nebo">Ceir mwy nag un enghraifft o'r enw Nebo:
Nebo - Duw Babilonaidd
Y Dwyrain Canol
Nebo - dinas Feiblaidd, yn Iwda
Nebo - dinas Feiblaidd, ym Moab
Cymru
Nebo - pentref yn Nyffryn Aeron, Ceredigion
Nebo - pentref yn Sir Conwy
Nebo - pentref yng Ngwynedd
Nebo - pentref ar Ynys Môn
Awstralia
Nebo - tref yn Queensland
Swydd Nebo
Yr Unol Daleithiau
Nebo, Illinois
Nebo, Kentucky
Nebo, Gogledd Carolina
Nebo Center, Califfornia
Ardal Ysgol Nebo, ardal ysgol yn Swydd Utah, Utah
Mynyddoedd
Enwir sawl mynydd gyda'r enw hwn, gweler dudalen gwahaniaethu Mynydd Nebo</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#nefyn">
            <name>Nefyn</name>
            <lat>52.9356549</lat>
            <lon>-4.520111</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nefyn">Nefyn (Welsh pronunciation: [ˈneːvɨn]) is a small town and community on the north west coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in Gwynedd, Wales. Historically in Caernarfonshire, it has a population of 2,602.
Welsh is the first language of almost 73% of its inhabitants. The A497 road terminates in the town centre. The community includes Edern.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nefyn">Tref fechan a chymuned ar arfordir gogleddol Penrhyn Llŷn yng Ngwynedd yw Nefyn, gyda phoblogaeth o tua 2,500. Filltir i lawr y ffordd i'r gorllewin mae Morfa Nefyn a Phortin-llaen, ar lan Bae Caernarfon. I'r dwyrain o Nefyn ar y ffordd i gyfeiriad Gaernarfon mae pentref Pistyll a bryniau Yr Eifl. Heblaw Nefyn ei hun, mae cymuned Nefyn yn cynnwys pentrefi Morfa Nefyn ac Edern.
Er bod Nefyn yn boblogaidd gydag ymwelwyr oherwydd bod yma draeth tywodlyd, mae'n un o gadarnleoedd yr iaith Gymraeg gyda bron 95% o'r trigolion yn ei medru. Mae'r ffordd A497 yn gorffen ynghanol y dref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#ogwen">
            <name>Ogwen</name>
            <lat>52.9815702</lat>
            <lon>-3.0597434</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogwen">Ogwen may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogwen">Gallai Ogwen (neu Ogwan) gyfeirio at:
Lleoedd
Afon Ogwen, Gwynedd
Dyffryn Ogwen, Gwynedd
Llyn Ogwen, Gwynedd/Conwy
Ysgol
Ysgol Dyffryn Ogwen, Bethesda, Gwynedd
Pobl
John Ogwen, actor adnabyddus
Arall
Llais Ogwan ('Llais Ogwen'), papur bro
Gweler hefyd
Tarddiad yr enw Ogwen/Ogwan</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#old llanberis (nant peris)">
            <name>Old Llanberis (Nant Peris)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pandy">
            <name>Pandy</name>
            <lat>51.897364</lat>
            <lon>-2.966638</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pandy">A pandy is another name (in Wales) for a fulling mill.

Pandy may also refer to several places in Wales:
Pandy, Monmouthshire, a village near Abergavenny
Pandy, Wrexham, a village in the Ceiriog Valley
Pandy, Powys, a village in Powys
Pandy Tudur, a village in Conwy
Pandy, an electoral ward near Llanfairfechan, Conwy</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pandy">Gallai Pandy gyfeirio at:
Pandy, adeilad a ddefnyddid ar gyfer pannu
Nifer o bentrefi yng Nghymru, yn cynnwys:
Pandy, Powys
Y Pandy, Sir Fynwy
Y Pandy, Wrecsam
Pandy Tudur, sir Conwy
Pandy'r Capel, sir Ddinbych</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pant">
            <name>Pant</name>
            <lat>51.7726429</lat>
            <lon>-3.3571127</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pant">Pant may refer to:
Underpants, an item of men's underwear
Trousers, an article of clothing worn on the lower half of the body
To breathe quickly, spasmodically, or in a labored manner
Panting is used by many furry animals as a means of thermoregulation

Pant (surname), a North Indian and Nepalese surname
Public Drinking Fountain
Places
Pant (meaning "a hollow" in Welsh) is a common Welsh place name element
Places named Pant include:
Pant, Denbighshire, Wales
Pant, Merthyr Tydfil, Wales
Pant, Shropshire, England
Pant, Wrexham, Wales
PANT is an ICAO code for Annette Island Airport</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pant glas">
            <name>Pant Glas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pant Glas">Pant Glas (Welsh for Green Hollow - in Welsh, as in other Celtic languages, "glas" may mean both 'green' and 'blue') is a hamlet on the A487 road in Gwynedd, Wales. Historically in Caernarfonshire, it is located approximately 10 miles (16 km) south of Caernarfon, 9 miles (14 km) miles north-west of Porthmadog, and 10 miles (16 km) north-east of Pwllheli. Nearby is the former Pant Glas railway station, which was closed as well as the Carnarvonshire Railway in 1964. The railway has since been replaced with the Lôn Eifion cycle track. Also nearby is the Arfon transmitting station, the tallest structure in Wales.
Welsh opera singer Bryn Terfel was brought up at Fferm Nant Cyll Ucha, located just outside the hamlet.
In February 2005, the speed limit for the A487 in Pant Glas was reduced from 50 mph (80 km/h) to 40 mph (64 km/h).
^ "Bryn Terfel; One of the world's most renowned opera stars.". BBC - North West Wales Arts. BBC. Retrieved 13 August 2009. 
^ "The A487 Trunk Road (Pant Glas, Gwynedd) (40 MPH Speed Limit) Order 2005.". Welsh Assembly Government. Retrieved 13 August 2009.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pant Glas">Pentref ydy Pant Glas (weithiau Pantglas) sy'n gorwedd ar yr hen A487 yn Nyffryn Nantlle, Gwynedd. Llifa Afon Dwyfach heibio i'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pantperthog">
            <name>Pantperthog</name>
            <lat>52.621646</lat>
            <lon>-3.850123</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pantperthog">Pantperthog is a hamlet in southern Gwynedd in Wales, 2 miles north of Machynlleth and 14 miles southeast of Dolgellau. Nearby is the former Llwyngwern quarry, which is now the Centre for Alternative Technology. The Afon Dulas, which here forms the border between Gwynedd and Powys, runs past the hamlet.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#parc">
            <name>Parc</name>
            <lat>52.891936</lat>
            <lon>-3.669819</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc">This is a redirect from a title with another method of capitalisation. It leads to the title in accordance with the Wikipedia naming conventions for capitalisation, or it leads to a title that is associated in some way with the conventional capitalisation of this redirect title. This may help writing, searching and international language issues. For more information follow the category link.
Use this rcat to tag only mainspace redirects; when other capitalisations are in different namespaces, use {{R from modification}} instead.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pen-gilfach">
            <name>Pen-gilfach</name>
            <lat>51.6145936</lat>
            <lon>-3.4520334</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pen-y-bont">
            <name>Pen-y-bont</name>
            <lat>51.917762</lat>
            <lon>-4.464583</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-bont">Gallai Pen-y-bont neu Penybont gyfeirio at:
Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr, neu 'Pen-y-bont', tref yn ne Cymru (gweler hefyd Pen-y-bont ar Ogwr (gwahaniaethu)
Pen-y-bont, Maldwyn, pentref ym Mhowys
Penybont, Powys, pentref a chymuned ym Mhowys
Penybont, Ceredigion, pentrefan yng Ngheredigion
Pen-y-bont, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Pen-y-bont, ger Caerfyrddin
Pen-y-bont, ger Llanymddyfri

Pen-y-bont-fawr, pentref ym Mhowys</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pen-y-bryn">
            <name>Pen-y-bryn</name>
            <lat>52.053908</lat>
            <lon>-4.659392</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-bryn">Gallai Pen-y-bryn neu Penybryn (weithiau hefyd Pen y Bryn) gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Pentrefi
Pen-y-bryn, Caerffili
Pen-y-bryn, Gwynedd
Pen-y-bryn, Sir Benfro
Pen-y-bryn, Wrecsam
Pen-y-bryn, Abergwyngregyn sef yr enw cyfoes am "Garth Celyn"
Ysgol
Ysgol Penybryn, Tywyn
Chwarel
Chwarel Pen y Bryn, Dyffryn Nantlle, Gwynedd
Nofel
Gŵr Pen y Bryn (1923), gan E. Tegla Davies</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pen-y-graig">
            <name>Pen-y-graig</name>
            <lat>52.867807</lat>
            <lon>-4.672957</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-y-graig">Pentref a chymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Rhondda Cynon Taf, de Cymru, yw Pen-y-graig (hefyd Penygraig). Heblaw pentref Pen-y-graig ei hun, mae'r gymuned yn cynnwys Dinas Rhondda, Edmondstown, Penpisgah a Threwiliam. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 5,877.
Saif Pen-y-graig yn ne-orllewin y Rhondda. Arferai'r diwydiant glo fod yn bwysig yma, gyda Glofa'r Naval yn y gymuned. Ceir prif swyddfeydd bwrdeisdref sirol Rhondda Cynon Taf yma.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pen-y-groeslon">
            <name>Pen-y-groeslon</name>
            <lat>53.073051</lat>
            <lon>-4.2709333</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penbodlas">
            <name>Penbodlas</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pencaenewydd">
            <name>Pencaenewydd</name>
            <lat>52.94581</lat>
            <lon>-4.376505</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pendre">
            <name>Pendre</name>
            <lat>51.518982</lat>
            <lon>-3.573769</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pendre">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanbadarn Fawr, Ceredigion, Cymru yw Pendre, sydd 73.9 milltir (118.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 178.1 milltir (286.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pendre yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Mark Williams (Y Democratiaid Rhyddfrydol).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penhelig">
            <name>Penhelig</name>
            <lat>52.5457</lat>
            <lon>-4.03503</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penllech">
            <name>Penllech</name>
            <lat>52.878381</lat>
            <lon>-4.646227</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penllech">Penllech is a village and former civil parish in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. The parish was abolished in 1934, and incorporated into Tudweiliog.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penmaenpool">
            <name>Penmaenpool</name>
            <lat>52.746422</lat>
            <lon>-3.937928</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmaenpool">Penmaenpool (Welsh: Pwll Penmaen) is a hamlet on the south side of estuary of the River Mawddach in Wales, near Dolgellau.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penmorfa">
            <name>Penmorfa</name>
            <lat>52.943079</lat>
            <lon>-4.163572</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmorfa">Penmorfa is a small village in the community of Penbryn, Ceredigion, Wales, which is 71.9 miles (115.7km) from Cardiff and 190.7 miles (306.8km) from London. Penmorfa is represented in the National Assembly for Wales by Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) and the Member of Parliament is Mark Williams (Liberal Democrats).

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmorfa">Pentref bychan yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd, yw Penmorfa. Mae'n gorwedd tua milltir i'r gorllewin o Dremadog ar bwys yr A487.
Fe'i gelwir yn Benmorfa am ei fod yn gorwedd ar ben gorllewinol morfa Tremadog, sy'n rhan o'r Traeth Mawr; buasai'r tir hwn yn wlypach o lawer cyn i William Madocks godi morglawdd dros geg y Traeth Mawr.
Eglwys Beuno Sant yw eglwys Penmorfa. Mae wedi cau ers rhai blynyddoedd.
Ar ochr arall yr Alltwen i'r gogledd o'r pentref ceir hen blasdy'r Gesail Gyfarch gyda phlasdy'r Clenennau yn ei wynebu dros y cwm.
Ar wahân i'r A487, mae lonydd bychain dros y morfa yn cysylltu'r pentref â Pentrefelin a Cricieth i'r de-orllewin a Penamser a Phorthmadog i'r de-ddwyrain.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pennal">
            <name>Pennal</name>
            <lat>52.58512</lat>
            <lon>-3.921579</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennal">Pennal is a village on the A493 road in southern Gwynedd, Wales, on the north bank of the Afon Dyfi/River Dovey, near Machynlleth.
It lies in the historic county of Merionethshire/Sir Feirionnydd and is within the Snowdonia National Park.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 14 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennal">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Gwynedd yw Pennal. Saif ar y briffordd A493 rhwng Tywyn a Machynlleth, ac ar lan ogleddol Afon Dyfi. Mae gan Pennal nifer o gysylltiadau hanesyddol gan gynnwys eglwys gron, sy'n deillio nôl i eglwys gynharach, Geltaidd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrallt">
            <name>Penrallt</name>
            <lat>53.2571645</lat>
            <lon>-4.3184426</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrhos">
            <name>Penrhos</name>
            <lat>53.300496</lat>
            <lon>-4.600263</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhos">Penrhos may refer to:
Penrhos, Anglesey, Wales
home of Penrhos Country Park

Penrhos, Gwynedd, Wales
RAF Penrhos, Gwynedd, Wales

Penrhos, Herefordshire, England
Penrhos, Monmouthshire, Wales
Penrhos, Powys, Wales
Penrhos College, Perth, an independent school for girls in Western Australia</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhos">Gallai Penrhos neu Pen-rhos gyfeirio at un o sawl lle yng Nghymru:
Penrhos, Gwynedd
Penrhos, Powys
Penrhos, Sir Fynwy
Gweler hefyd
Penrhosgarnedd, Gwynedd
Penrhosllugwy, Ynys Môn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrhos-garnedd">
            <name>Penrhos-garnedd</name>
            <lat>53.211588</lat>
            <lon>-4.159899</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrhyn llyn (lleyn peninsula)">
            <name>Penrhyn Llyn (Lleyn Peninsula)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrhyn mawr">
            <name>Penrhyn Mawr</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penrhyndeudraeth">
            <name>Penrhyndeudraeth</name>
            <lat>52.92924</lat>
            <lon>-4.067134</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhyndeudraeth">Penrhyndeudraeth (English: Peninsula with Two Beaches) is a village and community in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It is located between Traeth Mawr (English: Big Beach), the now largely reclaimed estuary of the Afon Glaslyn, and Traeth Bach (English: Little Beach), the estuary of the River Dwyryd. The village is close to the mouth of the River Dwyryd on the A487 from Porthmadog, and has a population of 2,031, increasing to 2,150 at the 2011 Census. The holiday village of Portmeirion, best known as the filming location for the 1960s TV series, The Prisoner, is located within Penrhyndeudraeth.
^ Office for National Statistics : Census 2001 : Parish Headcounts : Gwynedd
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 17 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhyndeudraeth">Pentref a chymuned ar arfordir gogledd eithaf Meirionnydd, Gwynedd yw Penrhyndeudraeth, gyda'r Traeth Mawr a'r Traeth Bach ar y naill ochr iddo gydag Afon Glaslyn yn ei wahanu oddi wrth Eifionydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pentir">
            <name>Pentir</name>
            <lat>53.180847</lat>
            <lon>-4.139788</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentir">Pentir is a community in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, and is 124.2 miles (199.9 km) from Cardiff and 204.7 miles (329.4 km) from London. In 2011 the population of Pentir was 2366 with 58.7% of them able to speak Welsh.
The Faenol Hall (Vaenol Estate) is a Grade II* Listed Building within the community, as well as a number of other buildings on the estate e.g. Chapel of St. Mary.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentir">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Pentir. Saif y pentref gerllaw y briffordd A4244 i'r de o ddinas Bangor. Llifa Afon Cegin gerllaw.
Ffurfiwyd y gymuned o'r rhan hwnnw o blwyf sifil Bangor oedd tu allan i ddinas Bangor ei hun. Heblaw pentref Pentir ei hun, mae'n cynnwys Penrhosgarnedd. Saif plasdy Y Faenol, Ysbyty Gwynedd a Phont Britannia o fewn y gymuned. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2,403 yn 2001.
Ganed y mathemategydd John William Thomas (Arfonwyson) yn y pentref yn 1805.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pentre gwynfryn">
            <name>Pentre Gwynfryn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentre Gwynfryn">Pentre Gwynfryn is a village in the Ardudwy area of Gwynedd, Wales about 1 mile (1.6 km) east of Llanbedr. The village is at the confluence of the river Artro and the river Cwmnantcol.
The inside of Capel Salem at Pentre Gwynfryn was made famous by the painter Sydney Curnow Vosper who painted the 1908 Salem featuring a member of the congregation, Siân Owen, in traditional Welsh costume. The folds around the left arm of her richly embroidered cloak are said to form the face of the devil who has taken over this proud woman, although this can be difficult to see. A far more obvious devil's face may be seen peering in through the window, which may be the origin of the claim that the devil's face is in the picture. The Salem painting hangs in the Lady Lever Art Gallery at Port Sunlight on the Wirral.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentre Gwynfryn">Pentref bychan yn ardal Ardudwy, Gwynedd yw Pentre Gwynfryn. Fe'i lleolir tua milltir i'r dwyrain o Lanbedr wrth gymer Afon Artro ac Afon Cwmnantcol.
Saif y pentref gwledig ar ffordd sy'n dringo o Lanbedr i gyfeiriad Cwm Nantcol a bryniau'r Rhinogau.
Daeth Capel Salem ym Mhentre Gwynfryn yn enwog diolch i'r paentiad adnabyddus gan Sydney Curnow Vosper o Siân Owen yn eistedd yn y capel yn ei siôl Gymreig. Cred rhai eu bod yn medru gweld llun y Diafol ym mhlygiadau'r siôl. Mae paentiad Capel Salem i'w gweld heddiw yn Oriel Gelf yr Arglwyddes Lever (Lady Lever Art Gallery) yn Port Sunlight, Cilgwri, Lloegr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pentrefelin">
            <name>Pentrefelin</name>
            <lat>52.934281</lat>
            <lon>-4.193056</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentrefelin">Mae Pentrefelin yn enw ar sawl lle yng Nghymru:
Pentrefelin, Ceredigion
Pentrefelin, Conwy
Pentrefelin, Gwynedd
Pentrefelin, Powys
Pentrefelin, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Pentrefelin, Ynys Môn, ar gyrion Amlwch
Gweler hefyd:
Pentre'r Felin (gwahaniaethu)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pentreuchaf">
            <name>Pentreuchaf</name>
            <lat>52.9234373</lat>
            <lon>-4.4467753</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentreuchaf">Pentref bychan sy'n gorwedd tair milltir a hanner i'r gogledd o dref Pwllheli yn Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Pentreuchaf.
Ceir yno ysgol gynradd, Ysgol Pentreuchaf, a adeiladwyd yn wreiddiol yn y flwyddyn 1908.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penycaerau">
            <name>Penycaerau</name>
            <lat>51.471266</lat>
            <lon>-3.2576602</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penyffridd">
            <name>Penyffridd</name>
            <lat>53.088457</lat>
            <lon>-4.2341179</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#penygroes">
            <name>Penygroes</name>
            <lat>53.05459</lat>
            <lon>-4.283645</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygroes">Penygroes or Pen-y-groes may refer to any of several places in Wales:
Penygroes, Gwynedd
Penygroes railway station, a former station in the town

Penygroes, Pembrokeshire
Pen-y-groes, Carmarthenshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygroes">Am y pentref bychan yn Sir Gaerfyrddin, gweler Pen-y-groes, Sir Gaerfyrddin.

Pentref mawr yng Ngwynedd yw Penygroes (hefyd: Pen-y-groes). Fe'i lleolir yn Nyffryn Nantlle, ger pentrefi Llanllyfni, Carmel a Groeslon.
Lleolir Ysgol Dyffryn Nantlle yn y pentref, ynghyd â ffatri papur toiled a chlwb peldroed enwog Nantlle Vale. Dyma ganolfan fasnachol ac economaidd y dyffryn, bellach wedi edwino rhyw gymaint ers agor ffordd osgoi heibio pentrefi'r cwm. Yno hefyd mae meddygfeydd, llyfrgell, canolfan dechnoleg, canolfan hamdden Plas Silyn, fferyllydd a stad ddiwydiannol. Cydnabyddir fel un o'r cymunedau Cymreiciaf yn y byd, gyda mwy na 90% yn gallu'r Gymraeg yno.
Mae bysiau sy'n rhedeg i Gaernarfon yn gwasanaethu'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pistyll">
            <name>Pistyll</name>
            <lat>52.948972</lat>
            <lon>-4.492473</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pistyll">Pistyll is a village and community in the Welsh county of Gwynedd, located on the Llŷn Peninsula. The community includes the village of Llithfaen, and has a population of 492,increasing to 566 at the 2011 Census. The actor Rupert Davies best known for playing the title character in Maigret, is buried here,being located within the community, in Llithfaen.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pistyll">Pentref bychan, plwyf eglwysig a chymuned yn Llŷn, Gwynedd, yw Pistyll. Gorwedd ar arfodir gogleddol penrhyn Llŷn, ar y ffordd B4417, ychydig i'r dwyrain o Nefyn.
Mae eglwys Pistyll, a gysegrir i Sant Beuno, yn sefydliad hynafol, gyda bedyddfaen or 12fed ganrif ynddi.
Heblaw pentref Pistyll, mae cymuned a phlwyf Pistyll yn cynnwys pentref mwy Llithfaen a phentref Nant Gwrtheyrn, sydd yn awr yn ganolfan ar gyfer dysgu Cymraeg.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pont-rhythallt">
            <name>Pont-Rhythallt</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pont-rug">
            <name>Pont-rug</name>
            <lat>53.1454949</lat>
            <lon>-4.222269</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pontllyfni">
            <name>Pontllyfni</name>
            <lat>53.047479</lat>
            <lon>-4.336862</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontllyfni">Mae Pontllyfni yn bentref bychan ar arfordir gogleddol Gwynedd, ar briffordd yr A499 rhwng Caernarfon a Phwllheli. Saif lle mae Afon Llyfni yn cyrraedd y môr, ychydig i'r gorllewin o Benygroes a Llanllyfni. Ystyrir yr ardal yn rhan o Ddyffryn Nantlle.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#port dinorwig (y felinheli)">
            <name>Port Dinorwig (Y Felinheli)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#porth colmon">
            <name>Porth Colmon</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#porthmadog">
            <name>Porthmadog</name>
            <lat>52.927842</lat>
            <lon>-4.133384</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porthmadog">Porthmadog (/pɔrθˈmædɒɡ/; Welsh pronunciation: [pɔrθˈmadoɡ]), known locally as "Port", and since 1974, rendered into Welsh from its former Anglicised form, Portmadoc, is a small coastal town and community in the Eifionydd area of Gwynedd, in Wales. Prior to the Local Government Act 1972 it was in the administrative county of Caernarfonshire. The town lies 5 miles (8 km) east of Criccieth, 11 miles (18 km) south west of Blaenau Ffestiniog, 25 miles (40 km) north of Dolgellau and 20 miles (32 km) south of Caernarfon. The community had a population of 4,185 (2011 census).
The town developed in the 19th century as a port exporting slate to England and around the world. Since the decline of the slate industry it has become an important shopping centre for the surrounding area and a popular tourist destination. It has easy access to the Snowdonia National Park and is the terminus of the Ffestiniog Railway. In 1987 the National Eisteddfod was held in Porthmadog.
The community includes the nearby villages of Borth-y-Gest, Morfa Bychan and Tremadog.
^ "British Broadcasting Corporation : What's in a Name : Porthmadog". Bbc.co.uk. Retrieved 2013-04-17. 
^ Neighbourhood Statistics. "Census 2011". Neighbourhood.statistics.gov.uk. Retrieved 2013-04-17. 
^ Whispernet (2008-02-14). "Gateway to Snowdonia". Porthmadog. Retrieved 2013-04-17. 
^ "Eisteddfod Genedlaethol Cymru : Eisteddfod Locations". Eisteddfod.org.uk. Retrieved 2013-04-17. 
^ "Ordnance Survey : Election Maps : Gwynedd". Election-maps.co.uk. Retrieved 2013-04-17.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porthmadog">Tref yng Ngwynedd yw Porthmadog neu Port ar lafar, sydd wedi'i leoli ar aber Afon Glaslyn yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd. Saif oddeutu 8 km (5 milltir) o Gricieth. Mae Caerdydd 173.4 km i ffwrdd o Borthmadog ac mae Llundain yn 316.6 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 33 km i ffwrdd.
Mae dros 65% o'r boblogaeth yn siarad Cymraeg. Cyn adleoli 1972 arferai fod yn Sir Gaernarfon. Yn 2001 roedd y boblogaeth yn 4,187.
↑ British Broadcasting Corporation : What's in a Name : Porthmadog</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#portmeirion">
            <name>Portmeirion</name>
            <lat>52.9144986</lat>
            <lon>-4.0973316</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portmeirion">Portmeirion is a tourist village in Gwynedd, North Wales. It was designed and built by Sir Clough Williams-Ellis between 1925 and 1975 in the style of an Italian village, and is now owned by a charitable trust.
The village is located in the community of Penrhyndeudraeth, on the estuary of the River Dwyryd, 2 miles (3.2 km) south east of Porthmadog, and 1 mile (1.6 km) from the railway station at Minffordd, which is served by both the narrow gauge Ffestiniog Railway and Arriva Trains Wales (Cambrian Line).
Portmeirion has served as the location for numerous films and television shows, and was "The Village" in the 1960s television show The Prisoner.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portmeirion">Arbrawf ar arfordir Eryri ac ymgais i greu datblygu cynaladwy sy'n gydnaws a'i amgylchfyd o ran tirwedd a diwylliant yw Portmeirion. Lleolir ym Meirionnydd, a roes iddo'i enw, ynghyd â'r rhagddodiad Port i gyfleu naws Port arall, sef Portofino yn Yr Eidal, ar lannau Afon Dwyryd, ger Bae Tremadog. Mae'r fynedfa iddo hanner ffordd rhwng Penrhyndeudraeth a Phorthmadog, ar yr A487. Mae yna dai a siopau, bwytai a gwestai yn y pentref, rai ohonyn nhw'n adeiladau gwreiddiol ac eraill wedi eu cynllunio gan Clough Williams-Ellis a'i codi ganddo ar benrhyn Aber Iâ a brynodd yn 1925 a'i agor fel Gwesty dros y Pasg, 1926. Adeiladwyd y pentref gan y pensaer a'r cadwriaethwr Syr Clough Williams-Ellis er mwyn dangos bod modd datblygu lle hardd heb ei ddinistrio ac y gellid, o arddel disgyblaeth lem, ychwanegu at yr harddwch naturiol. Ar dir y gwesty gellir ymweld ag adfeilion Castell Deudraeth, a godwyd gan feibion Cynan ab Owain Gwynedd tua chanol y 12fed ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#prenteg">
            <name>Prenteg</name>
            <lat>52.94972</lat>
            <lon>-4.105678</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prenteg">Prenteg is a hamlet that lies 3 miles (4.8 km) from Porthmadog, Wales, between Tremadog and Beddgelert.
Prenteg is where the entertainer and rugby player Ioan Gwilym was born and raised.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prenteg">Pentref bychan yng Ngwynedd yw Prenteg a leolir ar y ffordd A498 tua 2 filltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Dremadog. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Dolbenmaen.
Gorwedd y pentref ar groesffordd ar lan orllewinol Afon Glaslyn. Yn ogystal â'r A498 mae ffordd wledig yn ei gysylltu â Golan i'r gorllewin ac mae'r B4410 yn croesi'r afon Glaslyn i'w gysylltu â Garreg a Maentwrog.
I'r de o'r pentref ceir Y Traeth Mawr. I'r gogledd mae'r bryniau yn codi i gyfeiriad Moel Hebog.
Yno ganwyd a magwyd y diddanwr a chwaraewr rygbi Ioan Gwilym.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#prysor">
            <name>Prysor</name>
            <lat>52.97562</lat>
            <lon>-3.94496</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#pwllheli">
            <name>Pwllheli</name>
            <lat>52.888816</lat>
            <lon>-4.4176339</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pwllheli">Pwllheli (Welsh pronunciation: [pʊɬˈhɛlɪ]) is a community and the main market town of the Llŷn Peninsula (Welsh: Penrhyn Llŷn) in Gwynedd, north-western Wales. It had a population of 4,076 in 2011 of which a large proportion, 81 per cent, are Welsh speaking. Pwllheli is the place where Plaid Cymru was founded. It is the birthplace of the Welsh poet Sir Albert Evans-Jones (bardic name Cynan).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pwllheli">Tref hynafol yw Pwllheli ar arfordir deheuol Llŷn yng Ngwynedd, sy'n dyddio'n ôl i'r canol oesoedd. Bu'r porthladd yn bwysig i'r dref ar hyd y canrifoedd. Roedd yno ddiwydiant adeiladu llongau llewyrchus yn y bedwaredd ganrif ar bymtheg. Tyfodd i fod yn dref marchnad i Lŷn gyfan, fel y tystia'r safle a adwaenir fel 'Y Maes' lle y cynhelid y ffeiriau, a 'Stryd Moch'. Mae Caerdydd 178.4 km i ffwrdd o Pwllheli ac mae Llundain yn 331.8 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 41.1 km i ffwrdd.
Yn ôl Cyfrifiad 2001 mae Pwllheli yn un o gadarnleoedd yr iaith Gymraeg, gyda 80% o'r boblogaeth yn medru'r iaith. Yn yr oedrannau 10-14 mae'r canran uchaf o bobol sydd yn gwybod yr iaith, sef 94%.
Daeth y rheilffordd i Bwllheli yn 1867 gan ei chysylltu ag Aberystwyth a Chaernarfon. Ger Pwllheli, ym mhlwyf Penrhos, mae Penyberth, safle'r ysgol fomio a losgwyd mewn protest yn erbyn militariaeth gan Saunders Lewis, D.J. Williams a Lewis Valentine yn 1936.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rachub">
            <name>Rachub</name>
            <lat>53.1914114</lat>
            <lon>-4.0614792</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rachub">Rachub is a small village of about 900 people in Dyffryn Ogwen (Ogwen Valley), Gwynedd, Wales, about half a mile away from the nearby, larger village of Bethesda. It forms part of Bethesda community.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rachub">Pentref bychan o tua 900[angen ffynhonnell] o bobl yn Nyffryn Ogwen, Gwynedd, yw Rachub, tua hanner milltir i ffwrdd o bentref Bethesda. Gorwedd ar lethrau'r Carneddau. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Bethesda.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhaeadr-fawr">
            <name>Rhaeadr-fawr</name>
            <lat>53.2264517</lat>
            <lon>-4.0113982</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhiw">
            <name>Rhiw</name>
            <lat>52.819499</lat>
            <lon>-4.633336</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhiw">Rhiw may refer to:
Rhiw, Conwy - an electoral ward in the county borough of Conwy, Wales, United Kingdom
Rhiw, Gwynedd - a village in the county of Gwynedd, Wales, United Kingdom
Rhiw, Powys - a place in the county of Powys, Wales, United Kingdom</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhiwbryfdir">
            <name>Rhiwbryfdir</name>
            <lat>53.0047349</lat>
            <lon>-3.944537</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhiwbryfdir">Ardal ar begwn gogleddol tref Blaenau Ffestiniog, wrth droed Bwlch Gorddinan ydy Rhiwbryfdir. Dyma leoliad Clwb Rygbi Bro Ffestiniog, Stad Ddiwydiannol Llwyn y Gell a Thafarn y King's Head. Roedd yr ardal hon yn arfer cael ei gwasanaethu gan Ysgol Glan-y-Pwll.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhiwen">
            <name>Rhiwen</name>
            <lat>52.819499</lat>
            <lon>-4.633336</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhiwlas">
            <name>Rhiwlas</name>
            <lat>53.172148</lat>
            <lon>-4.133393</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhiwlas">Rhiwlas may refer to:
Rhiwlas, Llanddeiniolen, Gwynedd, Wales, United Kingdom
Rhiwlas, Llandderfel, Gwynedd, Wales, United Kingdom
Rhiwlas, Powys, Wales, United Kingdom</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhiwlas">Pentref yng Ngwynedd yw Rhiwlas a leolir tua 4 milltir i'r de o Fangor yn ardal Arfon.
Y pentrefi agosaf yw Pentir a Rhyd-y-groes i'r gogledd, Deiniolen i'r de, Waun a Penisa'r Waun i'r de-orllewin, a Llanddeiniolen i'r gorllewin. I'r de a'r dwyrain o'r pentref cyfyd rhagfryniau Eryri yn cynnwys Moel-y-ci (410m) a Moel Rhiwen (391m).
Ceir bryngaer gynhanesyddol a elwir yn 'Castell' hanner milltir i'r dwyrain o Riwlas ger y B4547.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhos isaf">
            <name>Rhos Isaf</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhos-ddu">
            <name>Rhos-ddu</name>
            <lat>53.05441</lat>
            <lon>-2.992112</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhos-ddu">Cymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Wrecsam a rhan o dref Wrecsam yw Rhos-ddu. Saif i'r gogledd-orllewin o ganol Wrecsam. Ceir yno ysgol gynradd a thafarn.
Ffurfiwyd plwyf Rhos-ddu ym 1886, o ran o blwyf Wrecsam. Daeth yn rhan o blwyf Wrecsam unwaith eto yn 1972. Adeiladwyd yr eglwys, a gysegrwyd i Sant Iago, rhwng 1874 a 1876, er na chafodd ei chysegru hyd 1886.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhos-fawr">
            <name>Rhos-fawr</name>
            <lat>52.2671111</lat>
            <lon>-3.1998611</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhos-fawr">Pentref bychan yng Ngwynedd yw Rhos-fawr a leolir ar y ffordd B4354 tua milltir i'r gorllewin o'r Ffôr a thua 3 milltir i'r gogledd o dref Pwllheli, yn ardal Eifionydd.
Mae'r pentref yn rhan o gymuned Llannor.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhos-y-gwaliau">
            <name>Rhos-y-gwaliau</name>
            <lat>52.898815</lat>
            <lon>-3.571486</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhos-y-gwaliau">is a small hamlet in the North of Wales and to the South-East of Bala, in Gwynedd, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhos-y-gwaliau">Pentref bychan yn ardal Meirionnydd, Gwynedd yw Rhos-y-gwaliau, a leolir tua milltir a hanner i'r de-ddwyrain o'r Bala. Tu ôl i'r pentref cyfyd bryniau'r Berwyn. Mae ffrwd Hirnant yn llifo o grib y Berwyn i lawr i ymuno yn Afon Dyfrdwy gan ffurfio Cwm Hirnant; saif y pentref yn rhan isaf y cwm cul hwnnw.
Ceir capel Methodistaidd Rhos-y-gwaliau yn y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhos-y-llan">
            <name>Rhos-y-llan</name>
            <lat>52.9079864</lat>
            <lon>-4.6227473</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhosdylluan">
            <name>Rhosdylluan</name>
            <lat>53.031159</lat>
            <lon>-3.027841</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhosgadfan">
            <name>Rhosgadfan</name>
            <lat>53.090636</lat>
            <lon>-4.231281</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosgadfan">Rhosgadfan is a Welsh village in the county of Gwynedd. It is notable as the birthplace of Kate Roberts, the greatest Welsh writer of the 20th century. The Welsh TV programme C'mon Midffild was filmed in the village hall, prior to its destruction. The hall was destroyed in a blaze believed to have been caused by arson . Nobody has been brought to justice. During March and April 2010 filming of SNOWDONIA 1890, a new television series to be shown on BBC1 Wales in the autumn of 2010,took place at various locations in the area.
The view is of Anglesey, Yr Eifl and by walking around you can reach common land called Comin Uwch Gwyrfai and Y Lon Wen. Nearby villages include Y Fron and Rhostryfan. Rhosgadfan is on the border of Snowdonia National Park. The nearest town is Caernarfon and the nearest city is Bangor. There are no shops in Rhosgadfan even with a population of almost 2,000. But the football club, Mountain Rangeres, is very well attended and is the focal point of the village.
The closest mountain is Moel Tryfan  and people from the school walk up often to collect money for educational things. Charles Darwin visited the mountain and recognised evidence of glaciation there .</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosgadfan">Mae Rhosgadfan yn bentref bach ddistaw, rhyw bum milltir i'r dwyrain o Gaernarfon - i fyny at y mynyddoedd. Y mae ysgol gynradd yna, a thafarn i'r clwb pêl-droed, "Mountain Rangers." Mae'r pentref i gyd ar lethrau bryncyn Moel Tryfan, sy'n un o droedfryniau Eryri.
Ar y ffordd i fewn i'r pentref, o Gaernarfon, trwy bentref Rhostryfan, i lawr tri-chwarter milltir o allt, mae hen gartref Kate Roberts - "Cae'r Gors". Mae hi yn un o awduron pennaf Cymru; "Brenhines y stori fer, yn ôl rhai". Mae yna sôn am adnewyddu "Cae'r Gors" yn ganolfan ymwelwyr i ddysgu amdani. Llenor arall a aned yn Rhosgadfan yw Richard Hughes Williams (tua 1878–1919), sef Dic Tryfan.
Uwchben y pentref a thu ôl i'r bryn, mae hen chwarel Rhosgadfan. Ond mae'n anodd iawn ei chyrraedd mewn car - haws yw cerdded ar hyd y llwybr o'r domen lechi i ogledd y bryn. Ceir golygfeydd gwych o gopa'r bryn: Bae Caernarfon, a goleuadau cychod Iwerddon–Caergybi, yr ochr draw i Ynys Môn - sydd i'w weld yn glîr i lawr i'r gorllewin, dros Afon Menai, a thref Caernarfon.
Yn y rhaglen ar S4C "Cymru a'r Chwyldro Diwydiannol," mae golygfeydd o chwarel Rhosgadfan, y rhan lle mae'r 'trac' i fewn i'r chwarel yn dechrau.
Mae clwb pêl-droed Mountain Rangers, sy'n chwarae yng Nghyngrair Caernarfon a'r Cylch, yn chwarae yn y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhosgyll">
            <name>Rhosgyll</name>
            <lat>52.9393076</lat>
            <lon>-4.3110935</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhoshirwaun">
            <name>Rhoshirwaun</name>
            <lat>52.831398</lat>
            <lon>-4.680314</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoshirwaun">Pentref bychan ym mhen Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Rhoshirwaun. Fe'i lleolir ar y ffordd B4413 tua 3 milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Aberdaron a thua 9 milltir i'r de-orllewin o Nefyn.
Dwy filltir i'r dwyrain cyfyd Mynydd Rhiw. Sefydlwyd Capel Saron yn y pentref gan y Methodistiaid Calfinaidd; fe drowyd yn dŷ yn 2000.
Ceir Ysgol Llidiardau ger y pentref, ysgol gynradd gyfrwng Gymraeg sydd yn nhalgylch Ysgol Botwnnog.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhoslan">
            <name>Rhoslan</name>
            <lat>52.945291</lat>
            <lon>-4.261553</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoslan">Pentref bychan yn Eifionydd, Gwynedd yw Rhoslan. Saif ar y ffordd B4411, rhwng Bryncir a thref Cricieth. Llifa Afon Dwyfor i'r dwyrain o'r pentref, ac Afon Dwyfach i'r gorllewin. Cyfeiria R. Williams Parry ar hyn yn ei linellau "Hen, hen yw murmur llawr man / Sydd rhwng dwy afon yn Rhoslan".</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhoslefain">
            <name>Rhoslefain</name>
            <lat>52.630863</lat>
            <lon>-4.103591</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoslefain">Pentref bychan yn ne Gwynedd yw Rhoslefain. Fe'i lleolir yn ardal Meirionnydd ar y briffordd A493 rhwng Llangelynnin, i'r gorllewin, a Llanegryn i'r dwyrain. Mae'n rhan o Gymuned Llangelynnin.
Mae Bae Ceredigion tua milltir i'r gorllewin o'r pentref. I'r gogledd mae cyfres o fryniau yn codi i gyfeiriaid Cader Idris.
Mae Rhoslefain yn blwyf eglwysig yn Esgobaeth Bangor. Yn yr Oesoedd Canol roedd y plwyf hwnnw'n gorwedd yng nghwmwd Ystumanner.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhostryfan">
            <name>Rhostryfan</name>
            <lat>53.096165</lat>
            <lon>-4.248365</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhostryfan">Pentref bach ar wasgar hyd lethrau Moel Tryfan yw Rhostryfan, tua 4 milltir i'r de o Gaernarfon, Gwynedd, yng ngogledd Cymru.
Fymryn i'r de o'r pentref gwelir gweddillion grŵp o Gytiau Gwyddelod (tai crwn cynhanesyddol).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd">
            <name>Rhyd</name>
            <lat>52.9562</lat>
            <lon>-4.026158</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhyd">Rhyd can refer to:
Rhyd, Ceredigion, Wales
Rhyd, Gwynedd, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhyd">Mae hon yn erthygl ar y nodwedd ddaearyddol. Am ddefnydd arall o'r gair, gweler Rhyd (gwahaniaethu).
Lle bas mewn afon, ffrwd, neu gorff arall o ddŵr, y gellir ei groesi ar droed neu ar geffyl ac ati yw rhyd.

Yn yr amser cyn i bontydd ddod yn gyffredin y rhyd oedd y man croesi arferol ar afonydd, yn arbennig yn achos afonydd llai a ffrydiau (defnyddio cwch i'w croesi oedd y dewis arall). Mewn mannau lle oedd y dŵr yn fwy dyfn ceir cerrig llam weithiau. Mae lleoliad rhydau yn gymorth mawr wrth geisio olrhain hen ffyrdd a llwybrau cynhanesyddol.
Oherwydd eu bod yn fannau strategol pwysig, mae rhydau yn cael eu cysylltu â brywdrau mewn hanes sawl gwlad. Yn llenyddiaeth y gwledydd Celtaidd mae cael arwyr yn ymladd mewn rhyd neu'n agos iddi yn olygfa gyffredin, yn enwedig yn achos llenyddiaeth Wyddeleg. Mae gan rai o rydau Cymru arwyddocád arbennig yn nhraddodiad y canu darogan a'r brudiau fel lleoedd a gysylltir â brwydrau tyngedfennol.
Mae rhyd yn elfen gyffredin mewn enwau lleoedd yng Nghymru, sy'n adlewyrchu ei bwysigrwydd ym mywyd y wlad. Fel enghreifftiau gellid enwi Rhydaman a Rhydcymerau yn y de, Rhyd Ddu yn Eryri, ac ati. Yn aml roedd llwybrau o bentref i bentref yn defnyddio rhydau. Gellir gweld rhai o'r rhydau llai hyn wrth gerdded yn y bryniau.
Gorweddai rhai rhydau ar ffyrdd y porthmyn ac fe'i defnyddid i gael gyrroedd o wartheg dros afon. Ceir enghreifftiau o bentrefi a dyfodd yn ymyl rhydau gyda thafarnau a chyfleusterau eraill ar gyfer y porthmyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-ddu">
            <name>Rhyd-Ddu</name>
            <lat>53.054407</lat>
            <lon>-4.136122</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhyd-Ddu">Pentref yng Ngwynedd yw Rhyd-Ddu (amrywiadau: Rhyd-ddu, Rhyd Ddu), ar lôn yr A4085 rhwng Caernarfon a Beddgelert yn ardal Eryri. Mae wedi ei leoli ar ben uchaf Dyffryn Nantlle, ym Mharc Cenhedlaethol Eryri. Mar'n rhan o gymuned Betws Garmon.
Saif Rhyd-Ddu gerllaw llethrau gorllewinol Yr Wyddfa, ac mae llwybr i gopa'r Wyddfa yn cychwyn o'r pentref. Mae Rheilffordd Ucheldir Cymru wedi ei hail-agor o Gaernarfon cyn belled â Rhyd-Ddu.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-hir">
            <name>Rhyd-hir</name>
            <lat>51.6699244</lat>
            <lon>-3.831622</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-uchaf">
            <name>Rhyd-uchaf</name>
            <lat>52.925637</lat>
            <lon>-3.638261</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-y-clafdy">
            <name>Rhyd-y-clafdy</name>
            <lat>52.886339</lat>
            <lon>-4.48613</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-y-gwystl">
            <name>Rhyd-y-gwystl</name>
            <lat>52.926422</lat>
            <lon>-4.375692</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-y-sarn">
            <name>Rhyd-y-sarn</name>
            <lat>52.959157</lat>
            <lon>-3.950876</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhyd-yr-onnen">
            <name>Rhyd-yr-onnen</name>
            <lat>52.5966639</lat>
            <lon>-4.047601</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhydlios">
            <name>Rhydlios</name>
            <lat>52.8391283</lat>
            <lon>-4.6957767</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#rhydymain">
            <name>Rhydymain</name>
            <lat>52.7811639</lat>
            <lon>-3.777272</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhydymain">Pentref yn ne Gwynedd yw Rhyd-y-main. Saif i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o dref Dolgellau ac i'r dwyrain o bentref Llanfachreth, ar y briffordd A494 ym Meirionnydd. Mae afon Wnion yn llifo heibio'r pentref a bryn uchel Rhobell Fawr i'r gogledd. I'r dwyrain o'r pentref mae copaon Aran Fawddwy ac Aran Benllyn.
Ceir ysgol gynradd, Ysgol Ieuan Gwynedd, yma, wedi ei henwi ar ôl Ieuan Gwynedd (1820 - 1852), oedd yn frodor o'r ardal.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#sarn meyllteyrn">
            <name>Sarn Meyllteyrn</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarn Meyllteyrn">Sarn Meyllteyrn is a village and former civil parish (Known at the time as Mellteyrn) located to the West of the Llŷn Peninsula (Welsh: Penrhyn Llŷn) in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. It lies 8.4 miles (13.5 km) west of Pwllheli and 24.3 miles (39.2 km) south west of Caernarfon. The village is often referred to simply as Sarn. The parish was abolished in 1934, and divided between the communities of Botwnnog and Tudweiliog.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#sarn-bach">
            <name>Sarn-bach</name>
            <lat>52.8102329</lat>
            <lon>-4.517265</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#sarnau">
            <name>Sarnau</name>
            <lat>52.131624</lat>
            <lon>-4.464382</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarnau">Gallai (Y) Sarnau gyfeirio at un o sawl lle:
Sarnau, Gwynedd, pentref ger y Bala
Sarnau, Maldwyn, pentref yng ngogledd Powys
Sarnau, Brycheiniog, pentref arall o'r un enw yn ne Powys
Sarnau, Ceredigion, pentref yn ne Ceredigion
Sarnau, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Gweler hefyd:
Sarn (gwahaniaethu)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#saron">
            <name>Saron</name>
            <lat>52.017731</lat>
            <lon>-4.370707</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saron">Saron may refer to:
Saron, Western Cape, a town in South Africa
Saron, Thiruvannamalai,a township in the Indian district of Thiruvannamalai
Saron (Cantabria, Spain) a village of Santa Maria de Cayón Municipalitie
Saron, a mythical king who gave his name to the Saronic Gulf
A Biblical name also written as Sharon
Saron Läänmäe (born 1996), Estonian footballer

Saron (instrument), an instrument in the Indonesian gamelan ensemble
Saron, Carmarthenshire, a small mining village in West Wales near Ammanford
Saron, a small village in Denbighshire, Wales
Saron, Gwynedd, a hamlet near Caernarfon (grid reference SH4659)
Saron Gas, original name of hard rock band Seether
Bedehuset Saron, a Gospel Hall in Bryne, Norway
SARON, Swiss Average Rate Overnight, an interest rate statistic
Saron, a genus of shrimp</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saron">Gall Saron (o'r Hebraeg: שָׁרוֹ, Šaron) gyfeirio at:
Gwastadedd Saron yn Israel.
Saron, pentref yn Sir Ddinbych
Saron, pentref yn Sir Gaerfyrddin gerllaw Rhydaman
Saron, pentref yn Sir Gaerfyrddin gerllaw Castell Newydd Emlyn
Saron, pentref yng Ngwynedd i'r de o Gaernarfon
Saron, pentref yng Ngwynedd gerllaw Bethel
Hefyd:
Rhosyn Saron (Hypericum calycinum), planhigyn</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#seion">
            <name>Seion</name>
            <lat>53.179266</lat>
            <lon>-4.175786</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seion">This is a redirect from a person's given name. It is used because Wikipedia has only one biographical article of a person by this given name, or because one individual is ubiquitously known by this given name (other persons who share this name might be listed at a primary topic disambiguation page). For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seion">Gair a ddefnyddir i ddynodi gwlad Israel neu ddinas Jeriwsalem yw Seion (Hebraeg: צִיּוֹן, tziyyon). Ceir llawer cyfeiriad at Seion yn y Beibl; yn aml maen cyfeirio at Mynydd Seion, bryn gerllaw Jeriwsalem lle roedd caer yn perthyn i'r Jebiwsiaid, a gipiwyd gan y brenin Dafydd.
Daeth "Seion" i olygu'r rhan o'r ddinas lle safai'r gaer, ac yn ddiweddarach i olygu Teml Solomon, y ddinas neu Wlad yr Addewid yn gyffredinol. Rhoddodd Seion ei enw i Seioniaeth, mudiad i greu a chynnal gwladwriaeth i'r Iddewon yn Israel. Sefydlwyd y mudiad Seionaidd yn Awst 1897 yn y Gyngres Seionaidd Ryngwladol gyntaf yn Basel yn y Swistir.
Ceir cyfeiriad yn anthem genedlaethol Israel, yr Hatikva:
A hyd ymylon y Dwyrain, ymlaen,
Mae llygad yn gwylio i Seion ...
Gobaith dwy fil o flynyddoedd,
I fod yn genedl rydd yn ein gwlad ein hunan,
Y wlad Seion a Jeriwsalem.
Yng Nghymru, daeth Seion, neu weithiau Mynydd Seion, yn boblogaidd iawn fel enw ar gapeli Anghydffurfiol. Trwy hyn daeth yn enw ar nifer o bentrefi bychain, er enghraifft Capel Seion yn Sir Gaerfyrddin; ceir hefyd bentref bychan Seion gerllaw Bangor.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#seiont">
            <name>Seiont</name>
            <lat>53.1327561</lat>
            <lon>-4.2596186</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#snowdon">
            <name>Snowdon</name>
            <lat>53.068504</lat>
            <lon>-4.0762766</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowdon">Snowdon (Welsh: Yr Wyddfa, pronounced [əɾ ˈwɨ̞ðva]) is the highest mountain in Wales, at an elevation of 1,085 metres (3,560 ft) above sea level, and the highest point in the British Isles outside the Scottish Highlands. It is located in Snowdonia National Park (Parc Cenedlaethol Eryri) in Gwynedd, and has been described as "probably the busiest mountain in Britain". It is designated as a national nature reserve for its rare flora and fauna.
The rocks that form Snowdon were produced by volcanoes in the Ordovician period, and the massif has been extensively sculpted by glaciation, forming the pyramidal peak of Snowdon and the arêtes of Crib Goch and Y Lliwedd. The cliff faces on Snowdon, including Clogwyn Du'r Arddu, are significant for rock climbing, and the mountain was used by Edmund Hillary in training for the 1953 ascent of Mount Everest.
Snowdon offers some of the best views in Britain. The summit can be reached by a number of well-known paths, and by the Snowdon Mountain Railway, a rack and pinion railway opened in 1896 which carries passengers the 4.7 miles (7.6 km) from Llanberis to the summit station. The summit also houses a cafe called Hafod Eryri, open only when the railway is operating and built in 2006 to replace one built in the 1930s. The railway generally operates to the summit station from Whitsun to October. The daily running schedule depends on weather and customer demand.
The name Snowdon is from the Old English for "snow hill", while the Welsh name – Yr Wyddfa – means "the tumulus", which may refer to the cairn thrown over the legendary giant Rhitta Gawr after his defeat by King Arthur. As well as other figures from Arthurian legend, the mountain is linked to a legendary afanc (water monster) and the Tylwyth Teg (fairies).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowdon">Gallai Snowdon gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#soar">
            <name>Soar</name>
            <lat>51.537778</lat>
            <lon>-3.302269</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soar">Soar may refer to:
160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (Airborne), a US Army regiment
The Special Operations Assault Rifle, primary assault rifle for the special forces unit of the Philippine National Police
Soar (cognitive architecture), a symbolic cognitive architecture
"Soar", a song by Christina Aguilera from the album Stripped (2002)
Soar (album), the second album (released 1991) by the American band Samiam
Hank Soar (1914–2001), American football player, baseball umpire and basketball coach
Safe operating area, typically used to describe power limitations of electronic components
Southern Astrophysical Research Telescope, a modern 4.1-meter-aperture optical and near-infrared telescope located on Cerro Pachón, Chile
SOAR Student Orientation And Registration
Surgical Outcomes Analysis and Research, a research collaborative in the department of surgery the Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center
An increased growth in the height of a mountain
Soaring, a mode of flight
Soar, a fictional airline in Flight Simulator X
Situation, Obstacles, Actions, Results
Any of several places in England:
The River Soar, a river in the East Midlands
Soar, Nottinghamshire
Soar, Devon
Old Soar Manor, an English Heritage property

Any of several places in Wales:
Soar, Anglesey
Soar, Gwynedd
Soar, Powys</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soar">Gallai Soar gyfeirio at:
Soar, dinas y cyfeirir ati yn llyfr Genesis yn yr Hen Destament
neu un o sawl lle yng Nghymru;
Soar, Ynys Môn
Soar, Gwynedd
Soar, Powys
Soar, Sir Gaerfyrddin
neu Loegr;
Afon Soar
Soar, Dyfnaint
Soar, Swydd Nottingham</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#soch">
            <name>Soch</name>
            <lat>52.85807</lat>
            <lon>-4.60195</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soch">Soch is a 2002 Hindi language film starring Sanjay Kapoor, Raveena Tandon, Arbaaz Khan, Danny Denzongpa and Aditi Govitrikar among others. Soch is a remake of Alfred Hitchcock's 1951 film Strangers on a Train.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#south beach (marian-y-de)">
            <name>South Beach (Marian-y-de)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tabor">
            <name>Tabor</name>
            <lat>51.7497537</lat>
            <lon>-4.3401809</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabor">Tabor may refer to:
Tabor (formation), a type of a camp or military formation
Tabor (Morocco), a type of a military unit in Morocco
Tabor (instrument), a snare drum
Tarrant Tabor, a very large aircraft of the early 20th century</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tai-morfa">
            <name>Tai-morfa</name>
            <lat>51.5776467</lat>
            <lon>-3.7620508</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tal-y-bont">
            <name>Tal-y-bont</name>
            <lat>52.485205</lat>
            <lon>-3.986391</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tal-y-bont">Mae Tal-y-bont (neu Talybont) yn enw lle cyffredin yng Nghymru:
Tal-y-bont, un o ddau gwmwd hen gantref Meirionnydd, de Gwynedd
Enw ar bentrefi:
Tal-y-bont, Ceredigion
Tal-y-bont, Conwy,
Talybont, Bangor, Gwynedd
Talybont, Abermaw, Gwynedd
Talybont-ar-Wysg, Powys
Tal-y-bont, Maldwyn, Powys
Enghreifftiau eraill:
Argae Talybont
Neuadd Breswyl Llys Talybont, Maendy, Caerdydd</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tal-y-llyn">
            <name>Tal-y-llyn</name>
            <lat>52.665836</lat>
            <lon>-3.909282</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tal-y-waenydd">
            <name>Tal-y-waenydd</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#talardd">
            <name>Talardd</name>
            <lat>52.8296979</lat>
            <lon>-3.6426466</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#talsarnau">
            <name>Talsarnau</name>
            <lat>52.904127</lat>
            <lon>-4.062969</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talsarnau">Talsarnau or Talsamau is a village and community in the Ardudwy area of Gwynedd in Wales. It has a population of 525, increasing to 550 at the 2011 Census.
The village of Talsarnau is situated on the A496 coastal road between Maentwrog and Harlech, close to the hamlets of Eisingrug and Llandecwyn.
It has one primary school and one pub, "The Ship Aground".
Talsarnau railway station on the Cambrian Line serves the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talsarnau">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Talsarnau. Saif ar y briffordd A496 rhwng Penrhyndeudraeth a Harlech.
Mae gan y pentref orsaf ar Reilffordd y Cambrian. Ychydig i'r gorllewin mae Traeth Bach, aber Afon Dwyryd, ac Ynys Gifftan. I'r de o'r pentref, i gyfeiriad Harlech, mae ffermdy Y Lasynys Fawr, lle ganed Ellis Wynne (1671-1734), awdur Gweledigaethau y Bardd Cwsc.
Un arall o Dalsarnau oedd y nofelydd Annie Harriet Hughes (Gwyneth Vaughan), awdures Plant y Gorthrwm, a aned yno yn 1852 yn ferch i felinydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#talysarn">
            <name>Talysarn</name>
            <lat>53.053408</lat>
            <lon>-4.25606</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talysarn">Talysarn is a village in the slate quarrying Nantlle Valley in Gwynedd, Wales. It is part of the community of Llanllyfni and includes some of Llandwrog. The ward had a population of 1,930 at the 2011 census.
The Welsh language poet Robert Williams Parry was born in 37, Station Road, Talysarn, where a plaque designed by R.L. Gapper commemorates the connection. Other persons connected with the village were Annant, quarryman, preacher and bard, Gwilym R. Jones, bard and journalist, and Idwal Jones author of the Welsh-language radio series SOS, Galw Gari Tryfan.
The 19th century methodist preacher John Jones, Talysarn, is also connected with the village, not by birth but because he settled here, becoming a shopkeeper and quarry owner as a sideline to his main vocation.
The song "Ciosg Talysarn" by the Welsh folk singer Dafydd Iwan was written after two secret agents were found bugging a public telephone in Talysarn in 1982.
Talysarn is covered by a Neighbourhood Policing Team based in the nearby village of Penygroes.
^ Davies, John; Jenkins, Nigel; Menna, Baines; Lynch, Peredur I., eds. (2008). The Welsh Academy Encyclopaedia of Wales. Cardiff: University of Wales Press. p. 502. ISBN 978-0-7083-1953-6.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talysarn">Pentref yn Nyffryn Nantlle, Gwynedd, yw Talysarn heb fod ymhell o Ben-y-groes. Tyfodd y pentref yn gyflym yn ystod y 19eg ganrif pan oedd nifer o chwareli llechi yn yr ardal, megis Chwarel Dorothea.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tan-lan">
            <name>Tan-lan</name>
            <lat>52.963216</lat>
            <lon>-4.052349</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tan-y-bwlch">
            <name>Tan-y-bwlch</name>
            <lat>52.974065</lat>
            <lon>-3.96837</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tan-y-mynydd">
            <name>Tan-y-mynydd</name>
            <lat>53.2256669</lat>
            <lon>-4.1167055</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tanat">
            <name>Tanat</name>
            <lat>53.0445589</lat>
            <lon>-2.9682384</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tanygrisiau">
            <name>Tanygrisiau</name>
            <lat>52.987119</lat>
            <lon>-3.958979</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanygrisiau">Tanygrisiau is a village and area within Blaenau Ffestiniog in the upper end of the Vale of Ffestiniog in the county of Gwynedd, north-west Wales (52°59′12″N 3°57′25″W). It can be found along the southern side of the Moelwyn mountain range and dates to around 1750. It joins onto the semi-urban area of Blaenau Ffestiniog, and is in the community of Ffestiniog; located between 650 feet (200 m) and 750 feet (230 m) above sea level.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tanysgafell">
            <name>Tanysgafell</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#teigl">
            <name>Teigl</name>
            <lat>52.9716086</lat>
            <lon>-3.9211937</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#terfyn">
            <name>Terfyn</name>
            <lat>53.2553365</lat>
            <lon>-3.4479021</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#the bar">
            <name>The Bar</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#trawsfynydd">
            <name>Trawsfynydd</name>
            <lat>52.903732</lat>
            <lon>-3.927315</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trawsfynydd">Trawsfynydd (Welsh pronunciation: [trausˈvənɨ̞ð]; Welsh for "across [the] mountain") is a village in Gwynedd, Wales, adjacent to the A470 north of Bronaber and Dolgellau near Blaenau Ffestiniog.
The total parish area is 12,830 hectares with a population of just under 1000, measured at 973 in the 2011 Census – the area is sparsely populated with each hectare inhabited by an average 0.07 persons. The village is typical of many Welsh villages. There is one grocery shop, one public house, a newsagent, a chemist, garage, petrol service station, and a branch of a large agricultural merchants.

^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 18 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trawsfynydd">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Gwynedd yw Trawsfynydd, sy'n gorwedd ar lan ddwyreiniol Llyn Trawsfynydd ar ochr cefnffordd de-gogledd yr A470. Mae'n adnabyddus fel man geni y bardd Hedd Wyn. Mae 81.7% o'r pentrefwyr yn medru'r Gymraeg. Cyfanswm arwynebedd y plwyf yw 12,830 hectar gyda phoblogaeth o 1000 o bobl.
Adeiladwyd Atomfa Trawsfynydd ar lannau'r llyn yn y chwedegau a ddaeth â llawer o waith i'r ardal. Mae hi bellach yn cael ei dadgomisiynu ers cael ei chau ym 1992. O safbwynt gwleidyddol, mae'r Pentref yn rhan o ward ehangach Trawsfynydd ac yn cael ei gynrychioli ar Gyngor Gwynedd gan y Cynghorydd Thomas Ellis (Annibynnol). Mae ysgol gynradd yn y pentref o'r enw Ysgol Bro Hedd Wyn, sy'n rhan o ddalgylch Ysgol y Moelwyn, Blaenau Ffestiniog. Mae dwy dafarn yn y pentref o'r enw'r Cross Foxes a Rhiw Goch. Mae nifer o siopau ar gael yn y pentref gan gynnwys Swyddfa Bost, Siop Bapur, Fferyllfa a Chigydd. Mae dwy garej yn y pentref hefyd. Mae hefyd ganolfan treftadaeth, sy'n cynnwys hostel yn yr un adeilad.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#trefaes">
            <name>Trefaes</name>
            <lat>52.868366</lat>
            <lon>-4.595418</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#trefor">
            <name>Trefor</name>
            <lat>52.992992</lat>
            <lon>-4.427481</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefor">Trefor is a village on the north coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in Gwynedd, Wales. Its population, with nearby Llanaelhaearn is 1,560.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefor">Erthygl am y pentref yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Gweler hefyd Trefor (gwahaniaethu).

.
Pentref gerllaw Yr Eifl ar arfordir gogleddol Llŷn yng Ngwynedd yw Trefor. Saif ychydig oddi ar y briffordd A499 o Gaernarfon i Bwllheli, rhwng Clynnog Fawr a Llanaelhaearn, lle maer'r briffordd yn gadael yr arfordir ac yn troi tua'r de. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanaelhaearn. Mae yno harbwr bychan, pier a thraeth. Llifa Afon Tal i'r môr yn y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tregath">
            <name>Tregath</name>
            <lat>53.2298036</lat>
            <lon>-4.1239534</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tremadog">
            <name>Tremadog</name>
            <lat>52.939532</lat>
            <lon>-4.141671</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tremadog">Tremadog (formerly Tremadoc) is a village in the community of Porthmadog, in Gwynedd, north west Wales. It was a planned settlement, founded by William Madocks, who bought the land in 1798. The centre of Tremadog was complete by 1811 and remains substantially unaltered.

It hosted an unofficial National Eisteddfod event in 1872.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tremadog">Pentref ar gyrion Porthmadog, Gwynedd, yw Tremadog.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#trwyn cilan">
            <name>Trwyn Cilan</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#trwyn y gorlech">
            <name>Trwyn y Gorlech</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tryweryn">
            <name>Tryweryn</name>
            <lat>52.912362</lat>
            <lon>-3.595478</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tryweryn">Gall Tryweryn gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Afon Tryweryn: yr afon ei hun
Cwm Tryweryn: sef yr ardal o gwmpas Capel Celyn a foddwyd dan gronfa ddŵr
Tri Tryweryn: Y tri wnaeth osod ffrwydron adeg codi argae Cwm Tryweryn yn Chwefror 1963
Gweler hefyd:
Boddi Capel Celyn: y pentref a foddwyd a'r protestio yn erbyn boddi'r cwm</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tudweiliog">
            <name>Tudweiliog</name>
            <lat>52.899919</lat>
            <lon>-4.621257</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudweiliog">Tudweiliog is a small, predominantly Welsh-speaking village and community on the northern coast of the Llŷn Peninsula in the Welsh county of Gwynedd. The population has risen from 801 in 2001 to 970 in 2011.
Agriculture is the main industry in Tudweiliog, with numerous farms both pastoral and arable.
^ "Enwau Cymru - Chwilio". E-gymraeg.com. Retrieved 2013-09-25. 
^ Cymuned Tudweiliog Community website 
^ "Tudweiliog Information on Llyn.info - Gwybodaeth Tudweiliog ar". Llyn.info. Retrieved 2013-09-25. 
^ "Community/Ward population 2011". Retrieved 18 May 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudweiliog">Pentref bychan a chymuned ar arfordir ogleddol Penrhyn Llŷn, Gwynedd yw Tudweiliog.
Mae'r mwyafrif o'r boblogaeth yn Gymraeg-gyntaf eu hiaith. Mae amaethyddiaeth yn rhan hanfodol o fywyd dyddiol y gymuned gyda thwristiaeth yn bwysig drwy'r haf. Mae i'r pentref un siop/Swyddfa'r Post, canolfan cymuned, tŷ tafarn, gefail, eglwys, capel ac ysgol gynradd (presennol) a ddathlodd ei chanmlwyddiant yn 2007. Mae gwasanaeth bws lleol yn gludiant cyhoeddus (pob 2 awr) rhwng Tudweiliog (a phentrefi eraill ar hyd y ffordd) a Phwllheli, sef cymuned mwyaf poblog Llŷn tua 10 milltir i ffwrdd. Mae Tudweiliog yn gyngor cymuned o fewn sir Gwynedd, ac o fewn dalgylch y gymuned mae atyniadau megis Coetan Arthur (cromlech) ar Mynydd Cefnamwlch, olion cymuned o Oes yr Haearn ar gopa fynydd Carn Fadryn, traethau tywodlyd Tywyn a Phenllech a phorthladdoedd hanesyddol Porth Ysgaden, Porth Colmon yn Llangwnnadl (hefyd Llangwnadl), a Phorth Gwylan sydd dan ofalaeth yr Ymddiriedolaeth Genedlaethol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#twrch">
            <name>Twrch</name>
            <lat>51.7774596</lat>
            <lon>-3.7886002</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twrch">Gall Twrch gyfeirio at:
Baedd Gwyllt (Sus scrofa)
Twrch Trwyth, baedd gwyllt yn chwedl Culhwch ac Olwen
Twrch Daear (Talpa europaea)
Afon Twrch, enw ar nifer o afonydd yng Nghymru</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tyn-lon">
            <name>Tyn-lon</name>
            <lat>53.087541</lat>
            <lon>-4.294747</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#tywyn">
            <name>Tywyn</name>
            <lat>52.587006</lat>
            <lon>-4.087249</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tywyn">Tywyn (/ˈtaʊ.ɪn/; Welsh: [ˈtəʊ.ᵻn]), formerly Towyn, is a town and seaside resort on the Cardigan Bay coast of southern Gwynedd, Wales. It was previously in the historic county of Merionethshire. It is famous as the location of the Cadfan Stone, a stone cross with the earliest known example of written Welsh, and the home of the Talyllyn Railway.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tywyn">Gallai Tywyn gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#upper bangor">
            <name>Upper Bangor</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper Bangor">This is a redirect from a title that potentially could be expanded into a new article or other type of associated Wikipedia page. The topic described by this title is more detailed than what is currently provided on the target page, or section of that page. For more information follow the category link.
When the target page becomes too large, this redirect may be replaced with a page carved out of the target page. See also {{R to section}}, and when appropriate, use both together.
If the topic is not susceptible to a major expansion, then instead of this rcat, tag this redirect with {{R to section}} or {{R to list entry}} as applicable.
Do not replace links to this redirect with a link directly to the target page.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#uwchmynydd">
            <name>Uwchmynydd</name>
            <lat>52.793143</lat>
            <lon>-4.742858</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#vaynol hall">
            <name>Vaynol Hall</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#waen-pentir">
            <name>Waen-pentir</name>
            <lat>53.2818527</lat>
            <lon>-3.7829116</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#waen-wen">
            <name>Waen-wen</name>
            <lat>53.196422</lat>
            <lon>-4.125751</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#waterloo port">
            <name>Waterloo Port</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#waun">
            <name>Waun</name>
            <lat>51.6177773</lat>
            <lon>-3.752255</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#waunfawr">
            <name>Waunfawr</name>
            <lat>53.110485</lat>
            <lon>-4.206658</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waunfawr">Waunfawr (English: large moorland/heathland) is a large village and community on the outskirts of the Snowdonia National Park, Gwynedd, in Wales, south of Llanrug. The community had a population of 1,427 at the 2011 census. The ward had a population of 1,676 at the 2011 census, and includes Caethro near Caernarfon.
Waunfawr railway station on the Welsh Highland Railway between Caernarfon and Porthmadog adjoins the Snowdonia Park Brewpub and Inn at the southern end of the village. The brewpub is a recent winner of the CAMRY award for a number of its beers and voted best pub in the region for 2012.
The name Waunfaur was spelled 'Waenfawr' an anglicized version of the Welsh name, corrected by common consent in 1994 to align with the aims of the Welsh Language Society's aims to maintain the Welsh language in its proper form throughout public signage and usage.
According to the United Kingdom Census 2011, the percentage of Welsh language speakers above age 3 was 79.5%. This was a 1.4% increase since the previous census in 2001.
The Waunfawr landscape certainly reflects the village name and is absolutely stunning with the surrounding mountains Mynydd Mawr and Moel Elio, with views of Snowdon, the highest mountain in Wales possible from some locations. There are a number of tourist locations for camping in Waunfawr and there is the opportunity to enjoy trekking and other Snowdonia National Park activities such as canoeing and mountain climbing.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waunfawr">Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd yw Waunfawr (weithiau Waenfawr). Mae'n bentref sylweddol o faint ar y ffordd A4085 rhwng Caernarfon a Beddgelert, ar lan Afon Gwyrfai. Mae yno orsaf ar Reilffordd Ucheldir Cymru ym mhen deheuol y pentref.
Waunfawr yw cartref Antur Waunfawr, elusen sy'n darparu gwaith bar gyfer yr anabl trwy gynnal nifer o brosiectau, yn cynnwys safle Bryn Pistyll yn Waunfawr ei hun, sy'n cynnwys gerddi, caffi a siop grefftau.
Yn 1914 adeiladodd cwmni Marconi orsaf ddarlledu ger y pentref, oedd yn gyrru negeseuon i orsaf dderbyn ger Tywyn. Mae'r adeilad yn awr yn ganolfan fynydda.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#wenallt">
            <name>Wenallt</name>
            <lat>52.9656086</lat>
            <lon>-3.5112606</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenallt">Wenallt is a hamlet in the community of Trawsgoed, Ceredigion, Wales, which is 67.2 miles (108.1km) from Cardiff and 172.2 miles (277.2km) from London. Wenallt is represented in the National Assembly for Wales by Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) and the Member of Parliament is Mark Williams (Liberal Democrats).

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#wern">
            <name>Wern</name>
            <lat>52.716432</lat>
            <lon>-3.106802</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wern">Wern is a river of Bavaria, Germany.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#west end (marian-y-mor)">
            <name>West End (Marian-y-mor)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#wnion">
            <name>Wnion</name>
            <lat>42.047858</lat>
            <lon>-72.2117694</lon>
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#y felinheli (port dinorwig)">
            <name>Y Felinheli (Port Dinorwig)</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia />
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
        <town id="gwynedd#y ffor">
            <name>Y Ffor</name>
            <lat />
            <lon />
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Y Ffor">This is a redirect from a page name that does not have diacritical marks (accents, umlauts, etc.) to essentially the same page name with diacritical marks. For more information follow the category link.
Apply this redirect (without piping) when the subject page concerns language translation or foreign language equivalents. Other pages that use this redirect should be updated with a direct link to the redirect target (again, without piping).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia />
        </town>
    </towns>
</county>