<?xml version="1.0"?>
<county id="Pembrokeshire">
    <postcodes>
        <postcode>SA34</postcode>
        <postcode>SA35</postcode>
        <postcode>SA36</postcode>
        <postcode>SA37</postcode>
        <postcode>SA41</postcode>
        <postcode>SA42</postcode>
        <postcode>SA43</postcode>
        <postcode>SA61</postcode>
        <postcode>SA62</postcode>
        <postcode>SA63</postcode>
        <postcode>SA64</postcode>
        <postcode>SA65</postcode>
        <postcode>SA66</postcode>
        <postcode>SA67</postcode>
        <postcode>SA68</postcode>
        <postcode>SA69</postcode>
        <postcode>SA70</postcode>
        <postcode>SA71</postcode>
        <postcode>SA72</postcode>
        <postcode>SA73</postcode>
    </postcodes>
    <towns>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#abercastle">
            <name>Abercastle</name>
            <lat>51.958919</lat>
            <lon>-5.125257</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abercastle">Abercastle (Welsh: Abercastell) is a village in the Welsh language speaking area of Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales. Abercastle has a working harbour which is managed by Abercastle Boat Owners Association. The harbour was the landing site of the first single handed atlantic sailing west to east in 1876 starting from Gloucester, Massachusetts by the Danish born fisherman, Alfred "Centennial" Johnson.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#abercych">
            <name>Abercych</name>
            <lat>52.0403499</lat>
            <lon>-4.557244</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abercych">Abercych (or Abercuch, Welsh pronunciation: [&#x251;b&#x259;rki&#x2D0;x]) is a small village in the community of Manordeifi, northeast Pembrokeshire in South West Wales. The village developed from a number of small settlements along the west bank of Afon Cych, which flows into the River Teifi nearby, giving the village its name, meaning "mouth of the Cych".
The village has two pubs, one of which brews its own beer, two chapels and a post office.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#aberdaughleddau (milford haven)">
            <name>Aberdaughleddau (Milford Haven)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#abereiddy">
            <name>Abereiddy</name>
            <lat>51.934295</lat>
            <lon>-5.2056829</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abereiddy">Abereiddy (usual Welsh spelling: Abereiddi) is a hamlet in the county of Pembrokeshire, in south-west Wales.
It has a small beach which was awarded the Blue flag rural beach award in 2005. A large car park adjoins the beach, where in the summer an ice cream van can usually be found. The beach also has public toilets which are open from Easter to October half-term. The Pembrokeshire Coast Path gives fine walking in both directions. The Common which runs inland behind the beach lies within the Manor of Llanrhian.
Following the coast path north leads to Porthgain. Abereiddi to Porthgain is roughly a forty-minute walk.
The coastal path taken in the other direction to the south east goes around St Davids Head and on to Whitesands Bay.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#abergwaun (fishguard)">
            <name>Abergwaun (Fishguard)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#albert town">
            <name>Albert Town</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert Town">Albert Town may refer to:
Albert Town, Bahamas on Long Cay
Albert Town, Jamaica, see Roads in Jamaica
Albert Town, Malta near the Malta Shipyards in Marsa
Albert Town, New Zealand
Albert Town, Pembrokeshire, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#albro castle">
            <name>Albro Castle</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ambleston">
            <name>Ambleston</name>
            <lat>51.89485</lat>
            <lon>-4.9067109</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambleston">Ambleston (Welsh: Treamlod) is a village, parish and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated in the centre of the county, 11 km north of Haverfordwest. In addition to Ambleston village, the parish includes the hamlets of Wallis 51&#xB0;53&#x2032;44&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;53&#x2032;21&#x2033;W and Woodstock (Welsh: Wstog) 51&#xB0;53&#x2032;40&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;52&#x2032;36&#x2033;W. The community had a population of 367 in 2001 increasing to 382 at the 2011 Census. With the communities of Spittal and Wiston, it makes up the Pembrokeshire electoral ward of Wiston.
The placenames, both English and Welsh placenames, mean "Amlot's farm", Amlot being a Norman-French name. The northern border of the parish is an ancient trackway leading towards St David's, with a Roman fortlet called "Castell Fflemish". This line is also the northern boundary of the cantref of Daugleddau, and was described by George Owen in 1602 as the language frontier, placing Ambleston in Little England beyond Wales. Ambleston was one of the parishes Owen described as bilingual, and in modern times it was predominantly Welsh-speaking.
In 1934, a small part of the parish was transferred to the parish of St. Dogwells. The pre-1934 parish had an area of 1558 Ha. Its census populations were: 421 (1801): 598 (1851): 386 (1901): 358 (1951): 309 (1981).
The percentage of Welsh speakers was 86 (1891): 79 (1931): 57 (1971).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#amroth">
            <name>Amroth</name>
            <lat>51.740576</lat>
            <lon>-4.662146</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amroth">Amroth may refer to:
Amroth, Pembrokeshire
Amroth (Middle-earth), a character from J. R. R. Tolkien's Middle-earth</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amroth">Pentref glan-m&#xF4;r a chymuned ar Fae Caerfyrddin yn ne-ddwyrain Sir Benfro yw Amroth neu Llanrhath. Fe'i lleolir 4 milltir i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o Saundersfoot a 2 filltir i'r dwyrain o bentref Stepaside. Mae'r pentref bron iawn ar y ffin &#xE2; Sir Gaerfyrddin.
Yn y 19eg ganrif pentref ar gyfer teuluoedd glowyr lleol a weithiai ym mhyllau glo carreg (anthracite) yr ardal oedd Amroth. Mae'r tai yn wynebu'r m&#xF4;r ac yn agored iddo, felly ceir nifer o dorrwyr d&#x175;r ar y traeth llydan i'w amddiffyn rhag y llanw uchel.
Pan fo'r m&#xF4;r allan gellir gweld olion hen goedwig a foddwyd gan y m&#xF4;r rhai miloedd o flynyddoedd yn &#xF4;l (tua 5000 CC yn &#xF4;l profion carbon radio). Mae esgyrn anifeiliaid sydd wedi darfod o'r tir yn cael eu darganfod ar y traeth weithiau o bryd i'w gilydd, ynghyd ag offer carreg cynhanesyddol.
Erbyn heddiw mae Amroth yn cael ei foddi gan dwristiaid yn yr haf a cheir nifer o barciau carafanau a chalets ar eu cyfer. Mae Llwybr Arfordir Penfro yn rhedeg trwy'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#angle">
            <name>Angle</name>
            <lat>51.6848737</lat>
            <lon>-5.0958467</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angle">In planar geometry, an angle is the figure formed by two rays, called the sides of the angle, sharing a common endpoint, called the vertex of the angle. Angles formed by two rays lie in a plane, but this plane does not have to be a Euclidean plane. Angles are also formed by the intersection of two planes in Euclidean and other spaces. These are called dihedral angles. Angles formed by the intersection of two curves in a plane are defined as the angle determined by the tangent rays at the point of intersection. Similar statements hold in space, for example, the spherical angle formed by two great circles on a sphere is the dihedral angle between the planes determined by the great circles.
Angle is also used to designate the measure of an angle or of a rotation. This measure is the ratio of the length of a circular arc to its radius. In the case of a geometric angle, the arc is centered at the vertex and delimited by the sides. In the case of a rotation, the arc is centered at the center of the rotation and delimited by any other point and its image by the rotation.
The word angle comes from the Latin word angulus, meaning "corner"; cognate words are the Greek &#x1F00;&#x3B3;&#x3BA;&#x3CD;&#x3BB;&#x3BF;&#x3C2; (ankyl&#x3BF;s), meaning "crooked, curved," and the English word "ankle". Both are connected with the Proto-Indo-European root *ank-, meaning "to bend" or "bow".
Euclid defines a plane angle as the inclination to each other, in a plane, of two lines which meet each other, and do not lie straight with respect to each other. According to Proclus an angle must be either a quality or a quantity, or a relationship. The first concept was used by Eudemus, who regarded an angle as a deviation from a straight line; the second by Carpus of Antioch, who regarded it as the interval or space between the intersecting lines; Euclid adopted the third concept, although his definitions of right, acute, and obtuse angles are certainly quantitative.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angle">Pentref a chymuned yn ne-orllewin Sir Benfro yw Angle. Mae yn y rhanbarth Saesneg ei hiaith, ac nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg ar y pentref.
Saif Angle ar ochr ddeheuol Afon Cleddau, gyferbyn ag Aberdaugleddau ac i'r gorllewin o dref Doc Penfro.
Ceir gorsaf bad achub yma, dwy dafarn, ysgol gynradd, swyddfa'r post ac eglwys, ac mae Llwybr Arfordir Sir Benfro yn mynd heibio'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#arberth (narberth)">
            <name>Arberth (Narberth)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#begelly">
            <name>Begelly</name>
            <lat>51.735307</lat>
            <lon>-4.726873</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Begelly">Begelly (Welsh: Begeli) is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated in the south of the county, 7 km north of Tenby. In addition to the village, the parish includes the hamlet of Thomas Chapel 51&#xB0;44&#x2032;36&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;44&#x2032;42&#x2033;W. It has a web of small settlements associated with the 19th century anthracite mining industry. The parish, together with the parish of Reynalton and part (Kilgetty) of St. Issells, constitutes the community and ward of Kilgetty-Begelly, which had a population of 2011 in 2001, with 11% Welsh speakers.
The placename appears to be Welsh, meaning "Bugail's territory". Part of Little England beyond Wales, it has been essentially English-speaking for 900 years.
The parish had an area of 1021 ha (3.94 mi&#xB2;). Its census populations were: 354 (1801): 779 (1851): 445 (1901): 346 (1951): 500 (1981).
The percentage of Welsh speakers was 3.5 (1891): 5.0 (1931): 4.5 (1971).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bengal">
            <name>Bengal</name>
            <lat>51.9562539</lat>
            <lon>-4.9790241</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengal">Bengal /b&#x25B;&#x14B;&#x2C8;&#x261;&#x254;&#x2D0;l/ (Bengali: &#x9AC;&#x9BE;&#x982;&#x9B2;&#x9BE;  Bangla  /ba&#x14B;la/ or &#x9AC;&#x999;&#x9CD;&#x997; B&#xF4;nggo /b&#x254;&#x14B;&#x261;o/) is a geographical and ethno-linguistic region in the north-eastern part of South Asia, at the apex of the Bay of Bengal and dominated by the fertile Ganges delta. The region was politically divided in the 1947 Partition of Bengal based on religion: predominantly Hindu West Bengal became a province (now a state) of India, while predominantly Muslim East Bengal became a province of Pakistan and later gained independence as Bangladesh. Some regions of the historical kingdoms of Bengal are now part of the neighbouring Indian states of Assam, Tripura, Bihar, Jharkhand, and Odisha. The Bengali people (&#x9AC;&#x9BE;&#x999;&#x9BE;&#x9B2;&#x9BF; Bangali), who speak the Bengali language (&#x9AC;&#x9BE;&#x982;&#x9B2;&#x9BE; Bangla), which is Indo-Aryan, natively inhabit the region, alongside dozens of indigenous ethnic groups who speak minority languages of the Tibeto-Burman, Austroasiatic, and Dravidian families.
Bengal is one of the most densely populated regions on Earth, with an estimated population of more than 250 million people and a population density exceeding 900 people per square kilometre. Most of the Bengal region lies in the low-lying Ganges Delta, the world's largest river delta. In the southern part of the delta lies the Sundarbans, the world's largest mangrove forest and home of the Bengal tiger. In the coastal southeast lies Cox's Bazar, the world's longest beach with a length of 120 km (75 mi). While most of region is rural and agrarian, it includes two megacities: Kolkata (previously Calcutta) and Dhaka (previously Dacca).
The Bengal region has a rich literary and cultural heritage and immensely influenced South Asian history through the Bengal Renaissance during the 19th and early 20th centuries and the Bengali Language Movement in the mid-20th century. The Bengal was the seat of western science education and a major industrial hub in pre and post independent India and reshaped the modern Indian culture and the Bengali people made important contributions to the revolutionary movement for Indian independence and the overall Indian independence movement, and successfully prosecuted the Bangladesh Liberation War.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengal">Rhanbarth yn is-gyfandir India yn ne Asia yw Bengal. Mae'n ymestyn rhwng Bangladesh yn y dwyrain a thalaith Gorllewin Bengal yn y gorllewin, yn India.
Gorwedd Bengal ar lan Bae Bengal yng ngogledd-ddwyrain yr is-gyfandir. Y prif afonydd yw Afon Ganges ac Afon Brahmaputra sy'n ffurfio aberoedd anferth, gyda'r gyntaf gyntaf yn gorwedd yn India a'r ail yn llifo trwy Fangladesh trwy gwastadir gorlif eang a ffrwythlon.
Bengaleg yw iaith Bengal a cheir llenyddiaeth gyfoethog yn perthyn iddi.
O ran crefydd, Hindwiaid yn bennaf a geir yn y gorllewin tra bod bron pawb ym Mangladesh yn ddilynwyr Islam. Roedd y rhaniad yn bod ers canrifoedd, ond fe ddyfnheuwyd pan ymranwyd yr hen dalaith yn ddwy ran yn 1947, gyda'r gorllewin yn aros yn India a'r dwyrain, dan yr enw Dwyrain Pacistan, yn mynd yn rhan o'r wlad newydd honno.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bentlass">
            <name>Bentlass</name>
            <lat>51.6821361</lat>
            <lon>-4.947699</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bentlass">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Hundleton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Bentlass, sydd 77.4 milltir (124.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.3 milltir (333.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Bentlass yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#berry hill">
            <name>Berry Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berry Hill">Berry Hill may refer to:
In England:
Berry Hill, Gloucestershire
Berry Hill High School and Sports College, a secondary school in Staffordshire
In the United States:
Berry Hill (Glenview, Kentucky), a National Register of Historic Places listing in Jefferson County, Kentucky
Berry Hill (Taconic Mountains), a peak in western Massachusetts
Berry Hill, Tennessee
Berry Hill (Orange, Virginia), a National Register of Historic Places listing in Orange County, Virginia
Berry Hill Plantation in South Boston, Virginia
Berry Hill Elementary School, as part of the Syosset Central School District</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bethesda">
            <name>Bethesda</name>
            <lat>53.178927</lat>
            <lon>-4.058833</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethesda">Bethesda (Aramaic, &#x5D1;&#x5D9;&#x5EA; &#x5D7;&#x5E1;&#x5D3;&#x5D0;, beth &#x1E25;esda, "House of Mercy"), originally referring to the Pool of Bethesda in Jerusalem (in the New Testament of the Christian Bible), may also refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethesda">Erthygl am y pentref yng Ngwynedd yw hon. Gweler hefyd Bethesda (gwahaniaethu).
Pentref a chymuned yng Ngwynedd, yn Nyffryn Ogwen, a enwyd ar &#xF4;l Capel Bethesda. Y mae ei thrigolion yn aml yn cyfeirio ati fel Pesda. Cyfeirnod OS: SH 62262 66779. Mae Caerdydd 193.8 km i ffwrdd o Bethesda ac mae Llundain yn 334.4 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Bangor sy'n 18.6 km i ffwrdd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bicton">
            <name>Bicton</name>
            <lat>52.7308</lat>
            <lon>-2.8217629</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bicton">Bicton can refer to:
United Kingdom
Bicton, Devon, England
Bicton College
Bicton House, a country house on the campus of Bicton College

Bicton, Herefordshire, England
Bicton, Shrewsbury, Shropshire (a village and parish), England
Bicton, South Shropshire, England
Bicton, Pembrokeshire, Wales
Australia
Bicton, Western Australia</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bicton">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanisan-yn-Rhos, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Bicton, sydd 85.4 milltir (137.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 214.9 milltir (345.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Bicton yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#black tar">
            <name>Black Tar</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#blackpool">
            <name>Blackpool</name>
            <lat>51.792156</lat>
            <lon>-4.815339</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackpool">Blackpool /&#x2C8;bl&#xE6;kpu&#x2D0;l/ is a major seaside resort and borough of Lancashire, North West England. The town is a unitary authority area, noted for its political autonomy, independent of Lancashire County Council. It is situated along England's northwest coast located by the Irish Sea, between the Ribble and Wyre estuaries, 17.5 miles (28.2 km) northwest of Preston, 27 miles (43 km) north of Liverpool, 30 miles (48 km) northwest of Bolton and 40 miles (64 km) northwest of Manchester. It has an estimated population of 142,100,. falling to 142,065 at the 2011 Census. making it the fourth most populated settlement in the North West behind Manchester, Liverpool and Warrington, and a population density that makes it the fourth most densely populated borough of England and Wales outside Greater London.
Throughout the Middle Ages and Early Modern period, Blackpool was a coastal hamlet in Lancashire's Hundred of Amounderness, and remained such until the mid-18th century when it became fashionable in England to travel to the coast during the summer to bathe in sea water to improve well-being. In 1781, visitors attracted to Blackpool's 7-mile (11 km) sandy beach were able to use a newly built private road, built by Thomas Clifton and Sir Henry Hoghton. Stagecoaches began running to Blackpool from Manchester in the same year, and from Halifax in 1782. In the early 19th century, Henry Banks and his son-in-law John Cocker erected new buildings in Blackpool such that its population grew from less than 500 in 1801 to over 2,500 in 1851. St John's Church in Blackpool was consecrated in 1821.
Blackpool rose to prominence as a major centre of tourism in England when a railway was built in the 1840s connecting it to the industrialised regions of Northern England. The railway made it much easier and cheaper for visitors to reach Blackpool, triggering an influx of settlers, such that in 1876 Blackpool was incorporated as a borough, governed by its own town council and aldermen. In 1881 Blackpool was a booming resort with a population of 14,000 and a promenade complete with piers, fortune-tellers, public houses, trams, donkey rides, fish-and-chip shops and theatres. By 1901 the population of Blackpool was 47,000, by which time its place was cemented as "the archetypal British seaside resort". By 1951 it had grown to 147,000.
Shifts in tastes, combined with opportunities for Britons to travel overseas, affected Blackpool's status as a leading resort during the late 20th century. Nevertheless, Blackpool's urban fabric and economy remains relatively undiversified, and firmly rooted in the tourism sector, and the borough's seafront continues to attract millions of visitors every year. In addition to its sandy beaches, Blackpool's major attractions and landmarks include Blackpool Tower, Blackpool Illuminations, the Pleasure Beach, Blackpool Zoo, Sandcastle Water Park, the Winter Gardens, and the UK's only surviving first-generation tramway.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackpool">Tref ger y m&#xF4;r yn Swydd Gaerhirfryn, Lloegr yw Blackpool. Mae ei boblogaeth yn 142,900. Mae'n gorwedd 40 milltir i'r gogledd-gorllewin o Fanceinion, a llai na 30 milltir o Lerpwl. Mae wedi dod yn ganolfan twristiaeth yn ystod yr 19eg ganrif, yn enwedig ar gyfer pobl o drefi melinoedd y gogledd. Mae Caerdydd 260.3 km i ffwrdd o Blackpool ac mae Llundain yn 324 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Preston sy'n 23 km i ffwrdd.
Tyfodd ar &#xF4;l 1864, wedi i'r rheilffyrdd cael eu adeiladu. Yn 1851, roedd y boblogaeth dros 2,500. Cafodd drydan yn y 1870au. Yn 1930, cafodd 7 miliwn o ymwelwyr mewn blwyddyn. Osgodd y dref ddifrod mawr yn ystod yr Ail Ryfel Byd, oherwydd fod Hitler wedi cynllunio i'w ddefnyddio ar &#xF4;l goresgyrn Prydain.
T&#x175;r mawr haearn yw'r Twr Blackpool. Cwblheuwyd y t&#x175;r yn 1894.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#blaenffos">
            <name>Blaenffos</name>
            <lat>52.003215</lat>
            <lon>-4.638387</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blaenffos">Blaenffos is a small village of around 200 inhabitants in the north of Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the community of Boncath. It is located on the boundary between the former parishes of Llanfihangel Penbedw and Castellan Chapelry (part of Penrydd parish).
Lying one mile to the north of Crymych, Blaenffos has an average elevation of 200 metres (660 ft), lying on the western slopes of Y Frenni which at 395m is the most easterly peak in the Preseli Hills. The village straddles the A478 former drovers' road which runs from Cardigan in Ceredigion south to Tenby, is surrounded by farmland, and is in the heart of Welsh-speaking Pembrokeshire with a rich history and associated folklore.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bletherston">
            <name>Bletherston</name>
            <lat>51.856779</lat>
            <lon>-4.802411</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bletherston">Bletherston (Welsh: Trefelen) is a hamlet and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated in the middle of the county, 9 km north of Narberth and 13 km east of Haverfordwest. The parish includes the village of Penffordd 51&#xB0;52&#x2032;0&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;47&#x2032;39&#x2033;W. Together with the parishes of Llys y Fran and New Moat, it constitutes the community of New Moat.
The church of St Mary's in the centre of the village is a grade II* listed building.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#boncath">
            <name>Boncath</name>
            <lat>52.014011</lat>
            <lon>-4.617351</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boncath">Boncath is a village, community and postal district in north Pembrokeshire, Wales, about 5 miles (8.0 km) west of Newcastle Emlyn.
The village stands at a cross-roads linking the nearby settlements of Newchapel (Capelnewydd), Eglwyswrw, Blaenffos and Bwlch-y-groes. Formerly a hamlet around an inn, the village developed after the coming of the railway in 1885.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boncath">Gallai Boncath gyfeiro at:
Bwncath (Boncath, Boda), math o aderyn ysglyfieithus
Boncath, Sir Benfro, pentref yn Sir Benfro, Cymru</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bosherston">
            <name>Bosherston</name>
            <lat>51.615819</lat>
            <lon>-4.94341</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosherston">Bosherston is a small village in South Pembrokeshire, Wales within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. Bosherston has a population of approximately 300.
There is a pub, the St. Govan's Inn and a caf&#xE9; serving light refreshments during the summer.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosherston">Pentref yn Sir Benfro yw Bosherston (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg am y pentref). Mae'n gorwedd yn ne'r sir o fewn ffiniau Parc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Sir Benfro ac mae'n rhan o gymuned Y Stagbwll.
Mae Eglwys Sant Mihangel, ar gwr y pentref, yn dyddio o'r 13eg ganrif.
Gerllaw ceir Llynnoedd Bosherston.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#boulston">
            <name>Boulston</name>
            <lat>51.777534</lat>
            <lon>-4.939391</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulston">Boulston is a village in Pembrokeshire, Wales.
Boulston is part of the community of Uzmaston, Boulston and Slebech</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#brimaston">
            <name>Brimaston</name>
            <lat>51.886537</lat>
            <lon>-5.008237</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brimaston">This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target article. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brimaston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-lai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Brimaston, sydd 83.4 milltir (134.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.6 milltir (338.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Brimaston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#broad haven">
            <name>Broad Haven</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broad Haven">Broad Haven (Welsh translation: Aber Llydan) is a village and seaside resort in the south east corner of St Bride's Bay at the western terminus of the B4341 road in south Pembrokeshire, Wales.
Broad Haven and Little Haven together form the Havens community and division of Pembrokeshire County Council. The 2001 census records a population of 1,328 for the Havens. The only church in Broad Haven is the Baptist church, although there are Anglican churches in nearby Little Haven.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broad Haven">Gallai Broad Haven gyfeirio at:
Aberllydan (Broad Haven): pentref yn Sir Benfro i'r gorllewin i Hwlffordd
Broad Haven: bae ar arfordir de Sir Benfro, i'r de o Benfro</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#broadfield">
            <name>Broadfield</name>
            <lat>51.700688</lat>
            <lon>-4.7066123</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadfield">Broadfield or Broadfields may refer to more than one placename:
Broadfield, Lancashire, England
Broadfield, Leyland, Lancashire, England
Broadfield, Greater Manchester, England
Broadfield, Inverclyde, Scotland
Broadfield, Pembrokeshire, Wales
Broadfield, Crawley, West Sussex, England
Broadfield, New Zealand, New Zealand
Broadfields Estate, London, England</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadfield">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanfair Dinbych-y-pysgod, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Broadfield, sydd 67.5 milltir (108.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.9 milltir (316.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Broadfield yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#broadmoor">
            <name>Broadmoor</name>
            <lat>51.720135</lat>
            <lon>-4.75477</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadmoor">Broadmoor may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadmoor">Pentref yng nghymuned Dwyrain Trewiliam, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Broadmoor, sydd 69.8 milltir (112.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 199 milltir (320.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Broadmoor yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#broadway">
            <name>Broadway</name>
            <lat>51.781075</lat>
            <lon>-5.077684</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway">Broadway may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway">Rhodfa lydan yn Ninas Efrog Newydd yw Broadway. Er bod Broadways eraill yn Efrog Newydd, yng nghyd-destun y ddinas, cyfeiria Broadway fel arfer at Stryd Manhattan. Dyma yw'r prif dramwyfa hynaf o'r gogledd i'r de drwy'r ddinas, ac mae'n dyddio i Setlwyr Amsterdam Newydd. Mae'r enw Broadway yn gyfieithiad Saesneg o'r enw Iseldireg, Breede weg. Mae rhan o Broadway yn enwog fel uchafbwynt y diwydiant theatr Americanaidd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#broom">
            <name>Broom</name>
            <lat>51.741159</lat>
            <lon>-4.735714</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broom">A broom is a cleaning tool consisting of usually stiff fibers (often made of materials such as plastic, hair, or corn husks) attached to, and roughly parallel to, a cylindrical handle, the broomstick. It is thus a variety of brush with a long handle. It is commonly used in combination with a dustpan.
In many Asian countries, however, brooms are not always made of stiff fibers, as there is often a distinction between a "hard broom" and a "soft broom". In Filipino-speaking Philippines, the hard broom is known as the walis-tingting, while the soft broom is known as the walis-tambo.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broom">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cilgeti a Begeli, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Broom, sydd 69.3 milltir (111.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 198.3 milltir (319.1 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Broom yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#bryn-henllan">
            <name>Bryn-henllan</name>
            <lat>52.017533</lat>
            <lon>-4.902072</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn-henllan">Pentref yng nghymuned Dinas, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Bryn-henllan, sydd 82.6 milltir (133 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.1 milltir (333.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Bryn-henllan yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#brynberian">
            <name>Brynberian</name>
            <lat>51.981627</lat>
            <lon>-4.762475</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynberian">Pentre bach yng nghesail bryniau Preseli yn Sir Benfro yw Brynberian. Mae tua un filltir o Bentre Ifan.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#burton">
            <name>Burton</name>
            <lat>51.710955</lat>
            <lon>-4.919328</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton">Burton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton">Gall Burton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#burton ferry">
            <name>Burton Ferry</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton Ferry">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Burton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Burton Ferry, sydd 76.7 milltir (123.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 206.2 milltir (331.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Burton Ferry yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#caer-farchell">
            <name>Caer-Farchell</name>
            <lat>51.8975523</lat>
            <lon>-5.2063647</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#caermeini">
            <name>Caermeini</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caermeini">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Mynachlog-ddu, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Caermeini, sydd 72.6 milltir (116.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 197.7 milltir (318.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Caermeini yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#caldey island">
            <name>Caldey Island</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caldey Island">Caldey (Welsh:Ynys B&#x177;r) is a small island off the SW coast of mainland Wales, near Tenby in Pembrokeshire. With a recorded history going back over 1500 years, it is known as one of Holy Islands of Britain, and a number of traditions inherited from Celtic times are observed by the Cistercian monks who are the chief inhabitants of the island today.
At its closest point, Caldey lies 1 kilometre (0.6 mi) south of the mainland, though the usual access to the island is by small boat from the town of Tenby which is some 4 kilometres (2.5 mi) to the north.
The island's population consists of 40 permanent residents and a varying number of Cistercian monks, known as Trappists, whose predecessors migrated there from Belgium in the early 20th century, taking over from Anglican Benedictines who had bought the island in 1906 and built the extant monastery and abbey but later got into financial difficulties. Today the monks farm the island, chiefly raising dairy cattle, and make a range of items including cheese, shortbread, perfumes and toiletries.
In the spring and summer, visitors are ferried to Caldey, not only to visit the sacred sanctuary but also to view the island's rich wildlife.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#camp hill">
            <name>Camp Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp Hill">Camp Hill may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tredeml, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Camp Hill, sydd 70.3 milltir (113.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 198.6 milltir (319.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Camp Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#camrose">
            <name>Camrose</name>
            <lat>51.840957</lat>
            <lon>-5.010048</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camrose">Camrose may refer to:
People
Viscount Camrose
Places
Camrose, Alberta, Canada
Camrose, Pembrokeshire, Wales
Other
Camrose Trophy, Home International competition in contract bridge</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carew">
            <name>Carew</name>
            <lat>51.697451</lat>
            <lon>-4.827894</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carew">Carew is a Welsh language and Cornish Language habitation type surname; it has also been used as a synonym for the Irish patronymic &#xD3; Corr&#xE1;in. Carey can be a variant.
The Cambro-Norman Carew family sprang from the same stock as the FitzGeralds: viz. from the union of Gerald de Windsor alias Gerald FitzWalter (1070-1136), the Norman Constable of Pembroke, Pembrokeshire and Nest ferch Rhys, Princess of Deheubarth, the 'Helen of Wales'. These Carews descend from Gerald and Nest's oldest son William FitzGerald de Carew. The family home was at Carew, Pembrokeshire, Welsh language 'Caeriw', from a fortified site and later castle, originally a holding of Nest's royal father, Rhys Ap Tewdwr. The usual derivation offered is that the root word is 'caer', Middle Welsh for 'fort'; the second element being possibly 'rhiw' - 'slope', or 'yw' - 'yew' (tree). The Pembrokeshire Coast National Park website has 'Caerau - fort (Locally pron Carey)'.
First, as will be shown below, not all modern Carews are of Carew, Pembrokeshire stock; some bear the name from cognate Cornish origins; and others as an Anglicised form, together with Carey, of the Irish patronymic &#xD3; Corr&#xE1;in/&#xD3; Carr&#xE1;in.
Secondly, some true Carews in Wales may have received their name in the variant form of 'Carey' or 'Cary', which is a traditional local pronunciation of the place Carew (see above), another version being 'Care-ew'. John Marius Wilson's 'Imperial Gazetteer of England and Wales' (1870&#x2013;72) has 'Carew, or Carey, a village and a parish in the district and county of Pembroke'. Bannister (1871) writes that Carew is 'pronounced Car'-ew in Ireland; Car-ew' in Devon; Carey in Cornwall and Wales' (my italics). However, Carey in Britain generally is either from any one of at least six immigrant Gaelic-Irish patronymics Anglicised thus, or is from a Pre-Celtic or Celtic language river/habitation name in Somerset and Devon.
Gerald FitzWalter's second son Maurice FitzGerald, Lord of Lanstephan and grandson Raymond de Carreu, 'le Gros', took part, alongside Richard de Clare, 2nd Earl of Pembroke, or 'Strongbow', in the invasion of Ireland in 1171. The 'invasion' was almost a family affair, with many of the Cambro-Norman protagonists related through the matriarchal and 'polygamous' Nest: among the cousins of the Geraldines were Robert FitzStephen, Robert de Barry et al.
In Ireland, after the invasion, the de Carreus, or Carews, held the barony of Idrone in County Carlow, without relinquishing their holdings in Britain. William de Carreu (d. 1213), held both manors of Carew and Idrone. Maurice de Carreu was in Edward 1's Irish Parliament in 1300. Raymond de Carreu appears in Irish records in 1302. Sir John Carew (d. 1362), who also held the manor of Moulsford in Berkshire, was Justiciar of Ireland.
Another Norman branch, which may or may not be related to the Idrone Carews, said to be descended from Adam Montgomery de Carrew, settled in East Cork, at Garryvoe, on the Waterford border in the 12th century. This family is described in 'British Museum Funeral Certificates', MS. No. 4820. They feature frequently in the 'Fiants' (Tudor records): e.g. John Careue of Garryvoe, 1582; Redmond &amp; Peirse Carewe, 1600. They forfeited Garryvoe, as rebels against Cromwell's 'Commonwealth' in 1656. Paul MacCotter has claimed in 'Irish Roots' (1997) that the rare East Cork Carews survive under the form 'Carey'; although the Garryvoe family definitely died out in the male line in the 1660s (Brit Mus.MS 4820); and Carey in this area is regarded as an Anglicisation of &#xD3; Ciar&#xE1;in.
There is recorded evidence for Carew being used as a synonym of the Munster surname &#xD3; Corr&#xE1;in/&#xD3; Carr&#xE1;in. The 'Court of Claims' in Ireland, 15 July 1663, adjudicates a request for return of lands in and around Mobernan in County Tipperary forfeited by 'Teige Carrue alias O Carron'. Donald O Carrane of Mobernayne, 1586 was his ancestor. By the 17th century the Mobernan O Corrain sept had widely adopted Carew as an Anglicised form of their name: Conor Carew of Mobarnan, was a representative at the Catholic Confederation of Kilkenny, 1642. Thomas Carue (alias O Corrain) of Mobernan appears in the Dictionary of National Biography His brother, Sir Ross Carey, appears on the 1661 memorial of Anne Hyde, his wife, in Westminster Abbey.
Some Carews, according to family legend/family trees, moved from Pembrokeshire to the English West Country, and settled in Crowcombe in Somerset, Haccombe in Devon and Antony House in Cornwall. There the name has occasionally been used interchangeably, in records such as the 'Patent Rolls', with the indigenous Cary of the West Country, causing no little confusion. It has been claimed that 'Carey' is a variant of Carew in Cornwall, (neither name there is numerous). However, this claim seems to be based on the Carew family of Antony being allegedly known by the byname 'Carey' (Hanks &amp; Hodges, op. cit. 1988), whereas this gentry family were usually known as 'Carew' not 'Carey'.
It is also highly likely that the surnames Carew and Carrow in Cornwall are variants of Cornish locative names such as Kerrow, Caroe &amp;c. with derivations from either Celtic 'car/ker'- 'fort' or pre-Celtic 'car'- 'stone/stony'. This would mean that at least some Cornish Carews are indigenous to Cornwall, and therefore have no connection with the Welsh/Norman immigrant Carews of Antony.
In England the family became influential. The Devon Carews became Earls of Totness (1625, extinct 1629). A Devon man, Sir George Carew was President of Munster temp. Elizabeth 1st. Ironically, given the supposed family connection, one of his more formidable tasks was the destruction of the FitzGerald Earls of Desmond.
Cornishman Richard Carew of Antony was a noted late 16th century historian of Cornwall; he wrote the fascinating 'Survey of Cornwall', published in 1602. Another family member, Alexander Carew, 2nd Baronet of Antony, was executed by Parliament for his lackadaisical support of their 'cause' in 1644. His half brother, John Carew, was a keener supporter of Cromwell: he was Commonwealth M.P. for Cornwall, and a signatory to the execution of Charles 1st; thus as a 'regicide' he was hanged, drawn and quartered by the returning royalists in 1660.
The Cambro-Norman Pembrokeshire Carew arms are 'Or, three lioncels passant, sable'.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carew cheriton">
            <name>Carew Cheriton</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carew newton">
            <name>Carew Newton</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carnhedryn">
            <name>Carnhedryn</name>
            <lat>51.905816</lat>
            <lon>-5.198845</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carnhedryn uchaf">
            <name>Carnhedryn Uchaf</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnhedryn Uchaf">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Carnhedryn Uchaf, sydd 91.5 milltir (147.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.8 milltir (352.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Carnhedryn Uchaf yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carreg-wen">
            <name>Carreg-wen</name>
            <lat>52.046393</lat>
            <lon>-4.591023</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carreg-wen">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Maenordeifi, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Carreg-wen, sydd 72 milltir (115.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 194.4 milltir (312.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Carreg-wen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#carregwastad point">
            <name>Carregwastad Point</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#castlebythe">
            <name>Castlebythe</name>
            <lat>51.92509</lat>
            <lon>-4.879542</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castlebythe">Castlebythe (Welsh: Cas-fuwch) is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales, on the southern slopes of the Preseli Hills, 10 km south-east of Fishguard. The northern part of the parish is in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. Together with the parishes of Henry's Moat, Little Newcastle, Morvil and Puncheston, it constitutes the community of Puncheston.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#castlemartin">
            <name>Castlemartin</name>
            <lat>51.644581</lat>
            <lon>-5.014966</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castlemartin">Castlemartin may refer to:
Castlemartin House and Estate, County Kildare, Ireland
Castlemartin, Pembrokeshire, a village in Wales
Castlemartin (hundred), a former administrative unit in Wales named after the village</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#castlemorris">
            <name>Castlemorris</name>
            <lat>51.9420185</lat>
            <lon>-5.0534287</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castlemorris">Castlemorris (also Castle Morris or Castle Maurice) is a small village in the heart of Pembrokeshire, Wales. It has a population of roughly 150 people. The Welsh manor (maenor) of Castle Morris lay within the ancient Cantref of Pebediog (later the Hundred of Dewisland) given in perpetuity to the bishops of St David's by Rhys ap Tewdwr, then Prince of Deheubarth, in 1082. It was then seized by William FitzGerald de Carew (William de Castello) during the Norman-Flemish invasion of Pembrokeshire after 1095. At the same time, his related half-brother Henry FitzRoy, the illegitimate son of King Henry I of England, acquired the interlocking manor of Priskilly. Prior to 1175, both manors were then granted to Maurice FitzGerald, Lord of Lanstephan by his brother David FitzGerald, then the second Norman approved bishop of St David's, as part reward for Maurice's appointment as hereditary steward of the episcopate. Castle Morris is generally considered to have acquired its name (Castell Maurice) from Maurice. But it may be a far more ancient relic of the pre-Norman Welsh name - Castell Marlais - Marlais then being the name of the reach of the Western Cleddau river which flows immediately below the village. Maurice was the progenitor of the FitzGerald dynasty in Ireland. By 1265 Maurice's descendants were defaulting in their hereditary duties. The Bishops recovered seisin against them in the King's Court in Carmarthen and then renegotiated their obligations. But that clearly was also not satisfactory. In 1302 Sir John Wogan, chancellor of St David's and Lord Justiciar of Ireland, bought out the remaining Fitzgerald interests in both Castle Morris and Priskilly and returned them to the Bishopric. And both manors then remained under the direct overlordship of the Bishops until 1886 when the Church Commissioners, by then acting in their name, sold the surface interests off to their sitting tenants. But mineral rights, vested in the University of Wales following disestablishment in the 1920s, were nevertheless reserved. However because of their history a possibly unparalleled record of lands and interests in both manors still survives.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cemaes head">
            <name>Cemaes Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cheriton (stackpole elidor)">
            <name>Cheriton (Stackpole Elidor)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#church hill">
            <name>Church Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church Hill">Church Hill, also known as the St. John's Church Historic District, is an Old and Historic District in Richmond, Virginia. This district encompasses the original land plat of the city of Richmond. Church Hill is the eastern terminus of Broad Street, a major east-west thoroughfare in the Richmond Metropolitan Area]]. The name Church Hill is often used to describe both the specific historic district and the larger general area in the East End encompassing other neighborhoods such as Union Hill, Chimborazo, Fairmount, Peter Paul, Woodville, etc.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tiers Cross, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Church Hill, sydd 82.5 milltir (132.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.4 milltir (340.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Church Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#churchton">
            <name>Churchton</name>
            <lat>38.8026161</lat>
            <lon>-76.5369022</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Churchton">Pentref yng nghymuned Saundersfoot, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Churchton, sydd 67.7 milltir (108.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.9 milltir (316.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Churchton yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cilau">
            <name>Cilau</name>
            <lat>51.8495594</lat>
            <lon>-3.1724184</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cilgerran">
            <name>Cilgerran</name>
            <lat>52.054818</lat>
            <lon>-4.632048</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cilgerran">Cilgerran (previously Kilgerran or Cil-Garon) is a parish, community and formerly incorporated market town situated on the River Teifi in north Pembrokeshire, Wales. The town gives its name to the Hundred of Cilgerran and was previously the headquarters of the commote of Emlyn is Cuch.
Among Cilgerran's attractions are Cilgerran Castle and annual coracle races. Kilgerran Halt was a stop on the former Whitland and Cardigan Railway. There are a number of listed buildings, including the parish church.
Nearby are the hamlets of Llwyncelyn, Rhoshill, Cnwce, Pen-y-bryn and Pontrhydyceirt, and the villages of Llechryd and Boncath.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cilgerran">Mae Cilgerran yn dref fechan ac yn gymuned yng ngogledd Sir Benfro, ger Aberteifi. Saif y dref ar lethrau deheuol Dyffryn Teifi gyferbyn &#xE2; Llechryd. Mae ffyrdd yn ei gysylltu ag Aberteifi a Llechryd i'r gogledd ac Abercuch a Chastell Newydd Emlyn i'r dwyrain.
Mae Cilgerran yn un o wardiau etholaethol Sir Benfro gyda'i chyngor etholedig ei hun.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cilwendeg">
            <name>Cilwendeg</name>
            <lat>52.019174</lat>
            <lon>-4.591889</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cippyn">
            <name>Cippyn</name>
            <lat>52.09861</lat>
            <lon>-4.712973</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cippyn">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llandudoch, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Cippyn, sydd 78.5 milltir (126.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.3 milltir (322.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Cippyn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#clarbeston">
            <name>Clarbeston</name>
            <lat>51.856324</lat>
            <lon>-4.8352769</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarbeston">Clarbeston (Welsh: Treglarbes) is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales, 11 km (6.8 mi) east of Haverfordwest. The parish, together with Wiston and Walton East, constitute the community of Wiston.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#clarbeston road">
            <name>Clarbeston Road</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarbeston Road">Pentref yng nghymuned Cas-wis, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Clarbeston Road, sydd 77.4 milltir (124.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 205 milltir (329.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Clarbeston Road yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#clareston">
            <name>Clareston</name>
            <lat>51.6720633</lat>
            <lon>-4.7054452</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cold blow">
            <name>Cold Blow</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold Blow">Cold Blow (or Coldblow) is a small village about 2 miles (3.2 km) southeast of Narberth in Pembrokeshire, southwest Wales. It lies on the B4315 Princes Gate to Templeton road and is in the community of Templeton.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold Blow">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tredeml, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Cold Blow, sydd 69.5 milltir (111.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 197.9 milltir (318.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Cold Blow yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cold inn">
            <name>Cold Inn</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold Inn">Cold Inn is a small village in the Welsh county of Pembrokeshire and community of East Williamston.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold Inn">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Cold Inn (ymddengys nad oes enw Cymraeg). Fe'i lleolir ger Saundersfoot ac mae'n rhan o gymuned East Williamston. Roedd poblogaeth cymuned East Williamston yn 1,787 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#colston">
            <name>Colston</name>
            <lat>51.5798828</lat>
            <lon>-2.9675746</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colston">Colston is a district in the Scottish city of Glasgow. It is situated north of the River Clyde. Colston is on the northern edge of Glasgow, surrounded by the areas of Milton and Springburn and the town of Bishopbriggs to the north. The main road through Colston is the A803 (Springburn Road), which then becomes Kirkintilloch Road once past Colston to the north through Bishopbriggs.
Colston High School closed in the early 1990s but much of the building remains and has been converted into laboratories which are used by Scottish Water. Most children in the Colston area now attend the re-built Springburn Academy. Stobhill Hospital is the nearest hospital. The nearest shopping centres are Springburn Shopping Centre and Bishopbriggs town centre. However there is a supermarket and several take-away shops within the Colston area.
Most of Colston is in Glasgow City (the area to the South of Newbold Avenue and Stobhill Hospital), with the rest being in East Dunbartonshire and regarded as part of Bishopbriggs.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-mael, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Colston, sydd 80.9 milltir (130.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.5 milltir (333.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Colston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cosheston">
            <name>Cosheston</name>
            <lat>51.696017</lat>
            <lon>-4.889264</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosheston">Cosheston is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated on an inlet of the Daugleddau estuary, 3 km north-east of Pembroke. The northern part of the parish is in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. Together with the parishes of Upton and Nash, it constitutes the community of Cosheston, which had a population of 713 in 2001, increasing to 828 at the 2011 Census. With the community of Lamphey, it makes up the Pembrokeshire ward of Lamphey.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosheston">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Cosheston. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o dref Penfro a ger Cilfach Cosheston neu Cosheston Pill, sy'n arwain i mewn i Afon Cleddau.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Upton a Nash. Ceir rhannau o gastell o'r 13eg ganrif wedi ei ymgorffori ym mhlasdy Upton. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 713 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cresselly">
            <name>Cresselly</name>
            <lat>51.722492</lat>
            <lon>-4.803288</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#crinow">
            <name>Crinow</name>
            <lat>51.7971519</lat>
            <lon>-4.714383</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crinow">Crinow (Welsh: Crynwedd) is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated 2 km east of Narberth. The parish is part of the community of Narberth.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#croes-goch">
            <name>Croes-goch</name>
            <lat>51.928415</lat>
            <lon>-5.159391</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croes-goch">Croes-goch is a village in North Pembrokeshire, West Wales. It is situated on the A487 between Fishguard and St David's. It lies some 5 miles north east of St Davids on the junction of the A487 St Davids to Fishguard road with the B4330 Llanrhian to Haverfordwest. The village, which has a population of about 400, lies within Llanrhian Community Council area and lies 2 miles to the south of the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croes-goch">Pentref yn Sir Benfro yw Croes-goch. Fe'i lleolir yng ngogledd y sir ar y briffordd A487. Mae'n rhan o gymuned a phlwyf eglwysig Llanrhian.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cross hands">
            <name>Cross Hands</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross Hands">Cross Hands is a village in Carmarthenshire, Wales about 12 miles from Carmarthen.
Cross Hands Public Hall is one of only three of its kind in Wales. The Public Hall was erected in 1920 and designed by an unknown Italian Designer in the classic Art Deco Style. Fully restored, the Public Hall has a fully functioning stage and cinema screen and is protected as a Grade 2 listed building.
The continuous built up area which includes the villages of Cross Hands, Gorslas, Cefneithin and Pen-y-groes had a population of 5,717 in 2011.
Cross hands is a growing residential and employment area and includes the established Cross Hands Food Park to the south west of the A48. A new business park - the Cross Hands Business Park is being developed to the northest of the A48 which the local authority hopes will create 1,000 jobs.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross Hands">Pentref yn Nghwm Gwendraeth yn Sir Gaerfyrddin yw Cross Hands. Ni ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo.
Saif Cross Hands gerllaw cyffordd y priffyrdd A48 a'r A476, tua 12 milltir i'r dwyrain o dref Caerfyrddin ac i'r gogledd o Lanelli. Ceir parc busnes ar gyrion y pentref, ynghyd a gwasanaethau ar gyfer teithwyr ar yr A48. Yn &#xF4;l un stori, cafodd y pentref ei enw oherwydd mai yma y byddai swyddogion carchar yn cyfarfod i gyfnewid carcharorion rhwng carchardai Caerfyrddin ac Abertawe.
Yn weinyddol, mae Cross Hands yn rhan o ward Llannon, sydd hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Tymbl a Llannon.
Gerllaw ceir Parc Coetir y Mynydd Mawr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#crosswell">
            <name>Crosswell</name>
            <lat>51.995437</lat>
            <lon>-4.73314</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crosswell">Crosswell (Welsh: Fynnongroes) is a hamlet on the B4329 road in the community of Eglwyswrw, Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the parish of Meline. It is 7 miles (11 km) southwest of Cardigan, 17 miles (27 km) northeast of Haverfordwest and 11 miles (18 km) east of Fishguard.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#crundale">
            <name>Crundale</name>
            <lat>51.825213</lat>
            <lon>-4.947329</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crundale">Crundale may refer to:
Crundale, Kent, a village and civil parish in the Ashford District of Kent, England
Crundale, Pembrokeshire, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crundale">Pentref yng nghymuned Rudbaxton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Crundale, sydd 79.6 milltir (128 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.7 milltir (334.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Crundale yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#crymych">
            <name>Crymych</name>
            <lat>51.974284</lat>
            <lon>-4.646704</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crymych">Crymych is a community, and a village of around 400 inhabitants in the northeast of Pembrokeshire, Wales, situated approximately 800 feet (240 m) above sea level at the eastern end of the Preseli Mountains. It stands astride the old Tenby to Cardigan turnpike road, now the A478.
The village developed around the former Crymmych Arms railway station on the now-closed Whitland to Cardigan Railway, nicknamed Cardi Bach (Little Cardi).
Crymych, which is twinned with Plomelin in Brittany, has its own elected community council. The village has given its name to an electoral ward of Pembrokeshire that encompasses the villages of Crymych itself and Eglwyswrw, as well as to the Megalithic burial mound knowns as Crymych Wayside Barrow.
About 1.8 miles (2.9 km) SSW of Crymych stands a TV mast which, at 235m tall erected on land which itself is some 350m above sea level, can be seen from several counties away on a clear day.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 18 April 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crymych">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Crymych. I'r gogledd saif bryn Y Frenni Fawr (1269 troedfedd). Mae Afon Nyfer yn llifo trwy Grymych ar ddechrau ei thaith i'r m&#xF4;r ym Mae Ceredigion.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentref Eglwyswen.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cuffern">
            <name>Cuffern</name>
            <lat>51.8371969</lat>
            <lon>-5.0619086</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuffern">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Nolton a'r Garn, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Cuffern, sydd 84.7 milltir (136.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.6 milltir (342.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Cuffern yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cuttybridge">
            <name>Cuttybridge</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cwm plysgog">
            <name>Cwm Plysgog</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwm Plysgog">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cilgerran, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Cwm Plysgog, sydd 74.2 milltir (119.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.5 milltir (316.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Cwm Plysgog yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cwmcych">
            <name>Cwmcych</name>
            <lat>51.995655</lat>
            <lon>-4.51157</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cwmorgan">
            <name>Cwmorgan</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#cwmwdig water">
            <name>Cwmwdig Water</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwmwdig Water">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanrhian, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Cwmwdig Water, sydd 91.8 milltir (147.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.7 milltir (352 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Cwmwdig Water yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dale">
            <name>Dale</name>
            <lat>51.706882</lat>
            <lon>-5.171983</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale">Dale or dales may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale">Pentref a chymuned ar arfordir Sir Benfro yw Dale, i'r gogledd-orllewin o Aberdaugleddau. Saif yn y rhan Saesneg o Sir Benfro, ac nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Daw'r enw "Dale" o'r Hen Norwyeg Dalr ("dyffryn"). Gerllaw mae Llwybr Arfordir Sir Benfro.
Ceir caer o'r cyfnod Fictoraidd yn y pentref, sy'n awr yn ganolfan astudiaethau maes bioleg y m&#xF4;r, daeareg a phynciau tebyg. Effeithiwyd ar yr ardal pan gollwyd 72,000 tunnell o olew i'r m&#xF4;r wedi i'r llong Sea Empress fynd ar y creigiau gerllaw ar 15 Chwefror 1996.
Gerllaw Dale, ym Mill Bay, y glaniodd Harri Tudur yn 1485 i ddechrau'r ymgyrch a arweiniodd at fuddugoliaeth Brwydr Bosworth a'i goroni fel Harri VII.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#deerland">
            <name>Deerland</name>
            <lat>51.7556536</lat>
            <lon>-4.9209537</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deerland">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llangwm, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Deerland, sydd 77.3 milltir (124.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 206.2 milltir (331.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Deerland yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dinas cross">
            <name>Dinas Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas Cross">Dinas Cross (Welsh: Dinas) is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is situated between Fishguard and Newport in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park and is a popular holiday destination on the A487. The village has its own elected community council and gives its name to an electoral ward of Pembrokeshire County Council. The electoral ward of Dinas Cross covers the communities of Dinas Cross, Cwm Gwaun and Puncheston.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dinas head">
            <name>Dinas Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dinbych-y-pysgod (tenby)">
            <name>Dinbych-y-pysgod (Tenby)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#doc penfro (pembroke dock)">
            <name>Doc Penfro (Pembroke Dock)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dreenhill">
            <name>Dreenhill</name>
            <lat>51.788716</lat>
            <lon>-5.014879</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreenhill">Pentref yng nghymuned Tiers Cross, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Dreenhill, sydd 81.7 milltir (131.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.3 milltir (338.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Dreenhill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#druidston">
            <name>Druidston</name>
            <lat>51.807118</lat>
            <lon>-5.092092</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Druidston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Nolton a'r Garn, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Druidston, sydd 85.2 milltir (137.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 213.7 milltir (343.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dudwells">
            <name>Dudwells</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dudwells">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Dudwells, sydd 83.8 milltir (134.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.6 milltir (340.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Dudwells yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#dyffryn">
            <name>Dyffryn</name>
            <lat>51.439704</lat>
            <lon>-3.304778</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn">Dyffryn or Duffryn may refer to one of these places in Wales:
Duffryn housing estate in Newport
Dyffryn, Bridgend
Dyffryn Cennen, Carmarthenshire
Dyffryn, Ceredigion
Dyffryn Cellwen, Neath Port Talbot
Dyffryn Clydach, Neath Port Talbot
Dyffryn, Pembrokeshire
Dyffryn, Vale of Glamorgan
Dyffryn Gardens</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyffryn">Am y pentref yn Ynys M&#xF4;n, gweler Y Fali; am yr ystad yng Nghasnewydd gweler Dyffryn, Casnewydd: gweler hefyd Cwm.

Tirffurf yw dyffryn, sef ardal o dir sydd yn is na thir cyfagos, ac yn amrywio o ran arwynebedd o ychydig filltiroedd sgw&#xE2;r i gannoedd o filltiroedd sgw&#xE2;r. Mae'n arferol, er nad yn angenrheidiol, i ddyffryn gynnwys afon yn llifo trwyddo, a'r afon yn rhoi enw i'r dyffryn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#east trewent">
            <name>East Trewent</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/East Trewent">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Castellmartin a Stackpole, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw East Trewent, sydd 74 milltir (119.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 204.2 milltir (328.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir East Trewent yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#east williamston">
            <name>East Williamston</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East Williamston">East Williamston is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the south of the county, 4 km west of Saundersfoot. The parish includes the villages of Cold Inn 51&#xB0;42&#x2032;57&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;44&#x2032;55&#x2033;W and Broadmoor 51&#xB0;43&#x2032;12&#x2033;N 4&#xB0;45&#x2032;16&#x2033;W. The community had a population of 1,787 in 2001, increasing to 1,844 at the 2011 Census. With the community of Jeffreyston, it makes up the Pembrokeshire electoral ward of East Williamston, which had a population of 2,327 in 2001, with 11% Welsh speakers.The ward population had increased to 2,418 at the 2011 Census.
It was originally a chapelry of the parish of Begelly. Part of Little England beyond Wales, it has been essentially English-speaking for 900 years.
The parish had an area of 588 Ha. Its census populations were: 341 (1801): 551 (1851): 397 (1901): 387 (1951): 473 (1981).
The percentage of Welsh speakers was 5 (1891): 12 (1931): 3 (1971).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/East Williamston">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw East Williamston. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Dinbych-y-pysgod, fymryn i'r de o'r briffordd A477.
Mae cymuned East Williamston hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Cold Inn a Broadmoor Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 1,787 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#eastern cleddau">
            <name>Eastern Cleddau</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#eglwyswen">
            <name>Eglwyswen</name>
            <lat>53.2685922</lat>
            <lon>-3.4976522</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eglwyswen">Eglwyswen (sometimes called Whitechurch or Whitchurch-by-Cardigan) is a hamlet and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is on the north slopes of the Preseli Hills, 2.5 miles (4.0 km) northwest of Crymych. The south-western part of the parish is in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. The parish is part of the community of Crymych.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eglwyswen">Pentref a phlwyf yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Eglwyswen. Saif i'r de o dref Aberteifi ac i'r dwyrain o Abergwaun, ar lethrau gogleddol Mynydd Preseli. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Crymych; mae pentref Crymych rhyw bedair milltir i'r de-ddwyrain.
Ar un adeg defnyddid Whitchurch-by-Cardigan fel enw Saesneg ar y pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#eglwyswrw">
            <name>Eglwyswrw</name>
            <lat>52.013981</lat>
            <lon>-4.709128</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eglwyswrw">Eglwyswrw is a village, community and parish in the Hundred of Cemais, Pembrokeshire, Wales. The village lies between Newport and Cardigan at the junction of the A487 road and the B4332.
The parish is in the heart of the Welsh-speaking area of Pembrokeshire.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eglwyswrw">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Eglwyswrw. Fe'i lleolir ar y ffordd A487 tua 6 milltir i'r de o Aberteifi.
Llifa Afon Gafren, ffrwd sy'n llifo i Afon Nyfer gerllaw, drwy'r pentref. Milltir a hanner i'r gorllewin ceir Castell Henllys, bryngaer fechan o Oes yr Haearn. Henllys oedd cartref hanesyddol George Owen. Ar un adeg cynhelid Ffair Feugan yma. Meugan yw sant y cwmwd. Dywed Wade Evans fod Meugan yn debygol o fod yn ddisgybl i Fartin, am fod Ffair Feugan yn cael ei chynnal ar y Llun ar ol Gwyn Fartin.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#felindre farchog">
            <name>Felindre Farchog</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felindre Farchog">Felindre Farchog is a hamlet in the community of Nevern in Pembrokeshire, Wales, located around 7 miles (11 km) south-west of Cardigan, and within the parish of Bayvil. The A487 road from Cardigan to Newport runs through the village.
The hamlet, on the River Nevern, consists of a few houses, a former college and an inn. A number of small mines used to exist to the south-west of the village.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felindre Farchog">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Felindre Farchog. Fe'i lleolir yng ngogledd y sir tua 7 milltir i'r de-orllewin o Aberteifi (Ceredigion).
Mae'n ngorwedd ym mhlwyf eglwysig Y Beifil. Rhed y briffordd A487 trwy'r pentref gan ei gysylltu gyda Trefdraeth, Sir Benfro ac Aberteifi. Ar un adeg bu cloddio am fwyn yn yr ardal a cheir adfeilion sawl mwynglawdd yn y gymdogaeth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ffynnon gron">
            <name>Ffynnon Gron</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ffynnon Gron">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-lai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Ffynnon Gron, sydd 85 milltir (136.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.1 milltir (341.3 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Ffynnon Gron yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#fishguard (abergwaun)">
            <name>Fishguard (Abergwaun)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#folly">
            <name>Folly</name>
            <lat>51.8465295</lat>
            <lon>-5.0103145</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folly">In architecture, a folly is a building constructed primarily for decoration, but either suggesting through its appearance some other purpose, or merely appearing to be so extravagant that it transcends the normal range of garden ornaments or the class of building to which it belongs.
18th century English gardens and French landscape gardening often featured Roman temples, which symbolized classical virtues or ideals. Other 18th-century garden follies represented Chinese temples, Egyptian pyramids, ruined abbeys, or Tatar tents, to represent different continents or historical eras. Sometimes they represented rustic villages, mills and cottages, to symbolize rural virtues. Many follies, particularly during famine, such as the Irish potato famine, were built as a form of poor relief, to provide employment for peasants and unemployed artisans.
In English, the term began as "a popular name for any costly structure considered to have shown folly in the builder", the OED's definition, and were often named after the individual who commissioned or designed the project. The connotations of silliness or madness in this definition is in accord with the general meaning of the French word "folie"; however, another older meaning of this word is "delight" or "favourite abode" This sense included conventional, practical, buildings that were thought unduly large or expensive, such as Beckford's Folly, or Fonthill Abbey, an extremely expensive early Gothic Revival country house that collapsed under the weight of its tower in 1825, 12 years after completion. As a general term "folly" is usually applied to smaller buildings with no practical purpose, or one that appears secondary to a striking and unusual design. But the term is ultimately subjective and a precise definition is probably impossible.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ford">
            <name>Ford</name>
            <lat>51.8975272</lat>
            <lon>-4.972649</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ford">This is a redirect from a trademark to a more common stylisation or to the owner of the trademark. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ford">Pentref yng nghymuned Cas-blaidd, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Ford, sydd 82.1 milltir (132.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.1 milltir (336.5 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Ford yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#freshwater east">
            <name>Freshwater East</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freshwater East">Freshwater East is a village in Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales. The majority of the village is located on the cliff overlooking the bay. It is about 2 miles south of Lamphey and 7 miles from Pembroke by road. In the valley there is a holiday park called Trewent Park (grid reference SS016984).
There are few services in Freshwater East apart from an inn and a twice daily bus service to Pembroke and the surrounding villages.
Its best-known natives are the Welsh indie band Gorky's Zygotic Mynci, whose founder members grew up in the town.
Freshwater East is the site of a Green Coast Award Beach. 

The beach also is host to The Big Draw - art drawn on the beach along with natural items.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freshwater East">Pentref ar arfordir Sir Benfro yw Freshwater East. Lleolir y rhanfwyaf o'r pentref ar glogwyn yn edrych allan drost y bae. Fe'i lleolir tua 2 milltir i'r de o Llandyf&#xE1;i a 7 milltir o dre Penfro.
Ychydig iawn o wasanaethau a chyfleusterau sydd yn Freshwater East, heblaw tafarn "The Freshwater Inn" a gwasanaeth bws dwywaith y dydd mae maes carafan yn y dyffryn gerllaw
Mae'r pentref yn gorwedd o fewn ffin Parc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Sir Benfro a rhed Llywbr Arfordir Sir Benfro heibio iddo, rhwng y pentref a'r traeth.
Brodorion enwocaf y pentref yw sylfaenwyr y band Gorky's Zygotic Mynci.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#freystrop">
            <name>Freystrop</name>
            <lat>51.7631749</lat>
            <lon>-4.960742</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freystrop">Freystrop is a community in Pembrokeshire, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freystrop">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Freystrop. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r de o dref Hwlffordd fymryn i'r gorllewin o lan Afon Cleddau Wen.
Dyddia'r eglwys, sydd wedi ei chysegru i Sant Stinan, o'r 14eg ganrif, ond fe'i hail-adeiladwyd yn 1874. O fewn y gymuned mae olion y lein bach a ddefnyddid i gludo glo carreg o lofa New Hook i'w allforio o Hook Quay.
Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 474.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#gelli">
            <name>Gelli</name>
            <lat>51.6437529</lat>
            <lon>-3.481939</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gelli">Gelli may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#gignog">
            <name>Gignog</name>
            <lat>51.8825812</lat>
            <lon>-5.069566</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#glanafon">
            <name>Glanafon</name>
            <lat>51.8174431</lat>
            <lon>-4.9662682</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glanafon">Ardal yng nghymuned Hwlffordd, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Glanafon, sydd 80.2 milltir (129 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.4 milltir (335.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Glanafon yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#glandwr">
            <name>Glandwr</name>
            <lat>51.927066</lat>
            <lon>-4.631556</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#glanrhyd">
            <name>Glanrhyd</name>
            <lat>52.047204</lat>
            <lon>-4.709708</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glanrhyd">Glanrhyd may refer to -
Glanrhyd Bridge collapse, the collapse of a railway bridge over the River Towy in 1987 which killed four people on a passenger train
Glanrhyd Hospital, Penyfai, Bridgend
SS Glanrhyd, a number of ship with this name</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#glenowen">
            <name>Glenowen</name>
            <lat>51.7161363</lat>
            <lon>-4.9642578</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenowen">Pentref yng nghymuned Neyland, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Glenowen, sydd 78.4 milltir (126.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.9 milltir (334.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Glenowen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#glogue">
            <name>Glogue</name>
            <lat>51.967684</lat>
            <lon>-4.598315</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glogue">Glogue is a hamlet and post town, 1 mile (1.6 km) north of Llanfyrnach, in the community of Crymych in the east of the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales.
It was the site of slate quarrying from the 18th century; the industry employed over 80 men when the railway came to the area in the 19th century and improved distribution.
Quarrying ended in 1926 and the railway closed in 1962.
Glogue Farm is just north of the settlement, in Clydau community.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glogue">Pentref yng nghymuned Crymych, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Glogue, sydd 69.3 milltir (111.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 193.8 milltir (311.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Glogue yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#golden hill">
            <name>Golden Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden Hill">Golden Hill or Golden Hills can refer to:
United States
Golden Hills, California, a census-designated place in Kern County
Golden Hill, San Diego, an urban neighborhood
Golden Hill Historic District (Indianapolis, Indiana), a wealthy historic neighborhood in Indianapolis, Indiana
Golden Hill Paugussett Indian Nation, Connecticut
Golden Hill State Park, in Niagara County, New York
Battle of Golden Hill, 1770 clash between British soldiers and New Yorkers
United Kingdom
Golden Hill, Bristol, a suburb
Golden Hill Fort, on the Isle of Wight
China
Golden Hill, Hong Kong - see List of mountains, peaks and hills in Hong Kong</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden Hill">Ardal yng nghymuned Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Golden Hill, sydd 75.8 milltir (122 km) o Gaerdydd a 205.6 milltir (330.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Golden Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#goodwick (wdig)">
            <name>Goodwick (Wdig)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#granston">
            <name>Granston</name>
            <lat>51.966232</lat>
            <lon>-5.064395</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Granston">Granston is a hamlet and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales. The parish was in the Hundred of Dewisland and includes the settlements of Llangloffan and Tregwynt, with Tregwynt woollen mill. Granston is in the community of Pencaer.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Granston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Pen-caer, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Granston, sydd 87.5 milltir (140.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 213.5 milltir (343.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Granston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#green">
            <name>Green</name>
            <lat>40.8975435</lat>
            <lon>-81.4731264</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green">Green is the color between blue and yellow on the spectrum of visible light. It is evoked by light with a predominant wavelength of roughly 495&#x2013;570 nm. In the subtractive color system, used in painting and color printing, it is created by a combination of yellow and blue, or yellow and cyan; in the RGB color model, used on television and computer screens, it is one of the additive primary colors, along with red and blue, which are mixed in different combinations to create all other colors.
The modern English word green comes from the Middle English and Anglo-Saxon word grene, from the same Germanic root as the words "grass" and "grow". It is the color of living grass and leaves and as a result is the color most associated with springtime, growth and nature. By far the largest contributor to green in nature is chlorophyll, the chemical by which plants photosynthesize and convert sunlight into energy. Many creatures have adapted to their green environments by taking on a green hue themselves as camouflage. Several minerals have a green color, including the emerald, which is colored green by its chromium content.
In surveys made in Europe and the United States, green is the color most commonly associated with nature, youth, spring, hope and envy. In Europe and the U.S. green is sometimes associated with death, sickness, or the devil, but in China its associations are very positive, as the symbol of fertility. Because of its association with youth, it is sometimes used to describe someone who is inexperienced. In the Middle Ages and Renaissance, when the color of clothing showed the owner's social status, green was worn by merchants, bankers and the gentry, while red was the color of the nobility. The Mona Lisa by Leonardo da Vinci wears green, showing she is not from noble family; the benches in the British House of Commons are green, while those in the House of Lords are red. Green is also the traditional color of safety and permission; a green light means go ahead, a green card permits permanent residence in the United States. It is the most important color in Islam. It was the color of the banner of Muhammad, and is found in the flags of nearly all Islamic countries, and represents the lush vegetation of Paradise. It is also often associated with the culture of Gaelic Ireland, and is a color of the flag of Ireland. Because of its association with nature, it is the color of the environmental movement. Political groups advocating environmental protection and social justice describe themselves as part of the Green movement, some naming themselves Green parties. This has led to similar campaigns in advertising, as companies have sold green, or environmentally friendly, products.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#greenway">
            <name>Greenway</name>
            <lat>51.9349816</lat>
            <lon>-4.8192637</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenway">Greenway or Greenways may refer to:
Greenway (landscape)
Another term for bicycle boulevards in some jurisdictions

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#grove">
            <name>Grove</name>
            <lat>51.6699259</lat>
            <lon>-4.916092</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grove">Grove may refer to:
Grove (nature), a small group of trees</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grove">Ardal yng nghymuned Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Grove, sydd 75.6 milltir (121.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 205.5 milltir (330.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Grove yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#guilford">
            <name>Guilford</name>
            <lat>35.966839</lat>
            <lon>-80.040819</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guilford">Ardal yng nghymuned Llangwm, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Guilford, sydd 76.7 milltir (123.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 205.8 milltir (331.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Guilford yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#gumfreston">
            <name>Gumfreston</name>
            <lat>51.677208</lat>
            <lon>-4.736661</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gumfreston">Gumfreston is a small hamlet 1 mile (2km) from St. Florence and 2 miles (4km) from Tenby, South Wales. The B4318 is the main road that passes through Gumfreston. It has a small church and a few houses, including Glebe farm.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gumfreston">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Gumfreston (ymddengys nad oes enw Cymraeg). Fe'i lleolir yn ne Sir Benfro tua 4 milltir o dref Dinbych-y-Pysgod. Mae'n rhan o gymuned St. Florence.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#gwastad">
            <name>Gwastad</name>
            <lat>51.888325</lat>
            <lon>-4.837448</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwastad">Mae Gwastad yn gopa mynydd a geir rhwng Castell-nedd a Chas-gwent; cyfeiriad grid SO234054. Uchder cymharol, neu &#x201D;amlygrwydd&#x201D; y copa, ydy 504 metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
Dosberthir copaon Cymru, a gweddill gwledydd Prydain, yn rhestri arbennig yn &#xF4;l uchder ac yn &#xF4;l amlygrwydd y copa; mae'r copa hwn yn cael ei alw'n Dewey. Mae sawl cymdeithas yn mesur, gwiro a chasglu'r rhestri hyn a d&#xF4;nt yngh&#x177;d ar wefan &#x201C;Database of British and Irish hills&#x201D;. Uchder y copa o lefel y m&#xF4;r ydy 551 metr (1808 tr). Cafodd yr uchder ei fesur a'i gadarnhau ar 10 Mawrth 2007.
&#x2191; &#x201C;Database of British and Irish hills&#x201D;</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hafod grove">
            <name>Hafod Grove</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hakin">
            <name>Hakin</name>
            <lat>51.711667</lat>
            <lon>-5.047022</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hakin">Hakin is a small coastal town in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It belongs to the parish of Hubberston in the historical hundred of Roose. It is located directly to the west of the larger town of Milford Haven, and is often considered a district of the latter. It has a population of 2,313 inhabitants as of 2001. It is mainly residential in nature.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hakin">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Hakin, sydd 81.9 milltir (131.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.5 milltir (340.4 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Hakin yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#harbour village">
            <name>Harbour Village</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harbour Village">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Abergwaun ac Wdig, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Harbour Village, sydd 85.8 milltir (138.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.8 milltir (339.2 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Harbour Village yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#haroldston west">
            <name>Haroldston West</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haroldston West">Haroldston West is a rural coastal parish in west Pembrokeshire, Wales, 5.5 miles (8.9 km) west of Haverfordwest. It is in the community of Merlin's Bridge.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haroldston West">Pentref yng nghymuned Yr Hafanau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Haroldston West, sydd 85.2 milltir (137.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 213.8 milltir (344.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Haroldston West yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#haverfordwest (hwlffordd)">
            <name>Haverfordwest (Hwlffordd)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hayscastle">
            <name>Hayscastle</name>
            <lat>51.889941</lat>
            <lon>-5.0589069</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hayscastle">Hayscastle or Hays-Castle is a village and community of Pembrokeshire in West Wales. Historically it was located in the union of Haverfordwest, in the Hundred of Dewisland. It is located 7&#xBD; miles (N. W. by N.) from Haverfordwest; it had 366 inhabitants in 1841. The principal road is the B4330 road. This rural parish, which is of considerable extent, is recorded as having been for the greater part inclosed and in a good state of cultivation. The largest village is Haycastle Cross; Haycastle itself to the northwest is no larger than a hamlet, the parish also includes the settlements of Brimaston and Ford.
In 1870&#x2013;72, John Marius Wilson's Imperial Gazetteer of England and Wales recorded a parish population of 297 and 62 houses and stated that it covered an area of 4,462 acres.

Hays Castle Motte was a Norman castle located in the area. It lay on a mound, oval in plan and still stands around 20 feet high on one side. Little remains of the castle today. The church is dedicated to St. Mary; and at the small village of Ford, in the parish, is a chapel of ease. St. Mary's is a church of medieval origin, but little remains from that period except the 13th-century font. Repairs were made to the church by D. F. Ingleton in 1927-8. There are places of worship for Independents and Calvinistic Methodists; and two or three Sunday schools which were supported by the dissenters. Noddfa Newton Chapel was built in 1862 and rebuilt in 1924. It is described as having an "old-fashioned stone gable front with a centre arch and arched windows." Several tumuli were formerly discernible, but they have been nearly levelled. RAF Hayscastle Cross Chain Home was situated here during the Second World War.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#haysford">
            <name>Haysford</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haysford">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Haysford, sydd 82.8 milltir (133.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.6 milltir (338.9 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Haysford yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hazelbeach">
            <name>Hazelbeach</name>
            <lat>51.704484</lat>
            <lon>-4.973599</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hazelbeach">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanstadwel, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Hazelbeach, sydd 78.5 milltir (126.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.1 milltir (334.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Hazelbeach yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#herbrandston">
            <name>Herbrandston</name>
            <lat>51.726723</lat>
            <lon>-5.08557</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbrandston">Herbrandston is a large coastal village on the north side of the River Cleddau, in southern Pembrokeshire, Wales, to the west of Milford Haven and Hakin and east of St Ishmael's. The village has a population of 1,523, 15% of which is Welsh-speaking. Before 1960 and the building of the ESSO oil refinery, the village only had a population of 200; as infrastructure grew, so did the population. The size of the village increased within a matter of years, as housing estates associated with the refinery were built.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbrandston">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Herbrandston. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r gorllewin o dref Aberdaugleddau ar lan Afon Cleddau lle mae Sandyhaven Pill yn ymuno a'r brif afon.
Yn yr eglwys, sydd wedi ei chysegru i'r Santes Fair, mae delw o farchog o'r 14eg ganrif.
Ceir purfa olew yn perthyn i Elf Murco gerllaw, gyda glanfa ar gyfer tanceri. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 401.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hermon">
            <name>Hermon</name>
            <lat>51.956106</lat>
            <lon>-4.612589</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermon">Ceir sawl lle o'r enw Hermon, a enwir ar &#xF4;l mynydd sanctaidd yn y Beibl, Mynydd Hermon, gan gynnwys:
Hermon (Sir Gaerfyrddin)
Hermon (Sir Benfro)
Hermon (Ynys M&#xF4;n)</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hill mountain">
            <name>Hill Mountain</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hill Mountain">Hill Mountain (or Herson/Hearson Mountain) is a village in the community and parish (Church in Wales) of Burton, south Pembrokeshire, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hill Mountain">Pentref yng nghymuned Burton, Sir Benfro, Cymru, yw Hill Mountain, sydd 125 km (77 milltir) o Gaerdydd a 333 km (207 milltir) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Hill Mountain yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hillblock">
            <name>Hillblock</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillblock">Pentref yng nghymuned Uzmaston, Boulston a Slebets, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Hillblock, sydd 78.3 milltir (125.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 207 milltir (333 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Hillblock yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hodgeston">
            <name>Hodgeston</name>
            <lat>51.659278</lat>
            <lon>-4.849654</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hodgeston">Hodgeston is a small village and parish a mile southwest of Lamphey, south Pembrokeshire, Wales, and is in the community of Lamphey. It is on the A4139 Pembroke Dock to Tenby road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hodgeston">Pentref yng nghymuned Llandyf&#xE1;i, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Hodgeston, sydd 72.9 milltir (117.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 202.9 milltir (326.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Hodgeston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hook">
            <name>Hook</name>
            <lat>51.765183</lat>
            <lon>-4.9319559</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hook">Hook may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hook">Gallai Hook gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#houghton">
            <name>Houghton</name>
            <lat>51.728149</lat>
            <lon>-4.920743</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houghton">Houghton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houghton">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Burton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Houghton, sydd 76.8 milltir (123.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 206.1 milltir (331.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Houghton yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hubberston">
            <name>Hubberston</name>
            <lat>51.71648</lat>
            <lon>-5.053648</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubberston">Hubberston is a coastal village in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It belongs to the parish of Hubberston in the historical hundred of Roose. It is located directly to the west of the larger town of Milford Haven, and is a district of the community of Milford Haven. It is adjacent to the village of Hakin. It had a population of 2,390 inhabitants in 2001. It is mainly residential in nature.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubberston">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Hubberston, sydd 82.3 milltir (132.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.9 milltir (340.9 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Hubberston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hundleton">
            <name>Hundleton</name>
            <lat>51.667467</lat>
            <lon>-4.950924</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundleton">Hundleton is a village and a community in Pembrokeshire, Wales. The community covers the adjacent settlements of West Orielton, Brownslate, Corston and Pwllcrochan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundleton">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Hundleton. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r gorllewin o dref Penfro gerllaw glan Afon Penfro, sy'n rhan o aber Afon Cleddau.
Heblaw pentref Hundleton ei hun, mae'r gymuned yn cynnwys pentrefi Maiden Wells, Pwllcrochan a Rhoscrowdder. Ceir purfa olew yn perthyn i Texaco yn y gymuned, gydag angorfa ar gyfer tanceri hyd at 280,000 tunnell fetrig. Bu'r naturiaethwr R. M. Lockley yn byw yn Orielton House. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 780.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#hwlffordd (haverfordwest)">
            <name>Hwlffordd (Haverfordwest)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#jameston">
            <name>Jameston</name>
            <lat>51.656292</lat>
            <lon>-4.811667</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jameston">Pentref yng nghymuned Maenorb&#x177;r, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Jameston, sydd 71.3 milltir (114.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 201.3 milltir (324 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Jameston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#jeffreyston">
            <name>Jeffreyston</name>
            <lat>51.724913</lat>
            <lon>-4.7683989</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffreyston">Jeffreyston (also known as Jeffreston) is a village and community in Pembrokeshire.
Jeffreyston lies on the B4586 road about one mile west from the main A477 road; the nearest town is Tenby about six miles (9.7 km) to the south and east. As well as Jeffreyston itself, the community includes the settlements of Cresselly, Cresswell Quay, Loveston, Broadmoor and Yerbeston.
The parish church is dedicated to St Jeffrey and St Oswald and is a grade II* listed building.
Cresselly House in the village of Cresselly is a Georgian country house, seat of the Allen family, which is now a country house hotel and wedding venue.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffreyston">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Jeffreyston. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Dinbych y Pysgod ac i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A477. Awgryma'r fynwent gron o gwmpas yr eglwys, a gysegrwyd i Sant Jeffrey, fod y safle yn gynnar iawn.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Creseli, Loveston a Yerbeston. Ar un adeg, bu mwyngloddio glo carreg yn weddol bwysig yn yr ardal. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 540 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#johnston">
            <name>Johnston</name>
            <lat>51.754691</lat>
            <lon>-4.9973789</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnston">Johnston may refer to Johnston (surname). It may also refer to:

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#jordanston">
            <name>Jordanston</name>
            <lat>51.95277</lat>
            <lon>-5.029736</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordanston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Scleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Jordanston, sydd 85.8 milltir (138.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 212 milltir (341.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Jordanston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#keeston">
            <name>Keeston</name>
            <lat>51.834358</lat>
            <lon>-5.048172</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeston">Pentref yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Keeston, sydd 83.9 milltir (135 km) o Gaerdydd a 212 milltir (341.1 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Keeston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#kete">
            <name>Kete</name>
            <lat>51.6921312</lat>
            <lon>-5.1789315</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kete">Kete may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kete">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Dale, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Kete, sydd 87.2 milltir (140.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.1 milltir (349.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Kete yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#kilgetty">
            <name>Kilgetty</name>
            <lat>51.731792</lat>
            <lon>-4.717631</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilgetty">Kilgetty (Welsh: Cilgeti) is a village immediately north of Saundersfoot in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It lies at the crossing of the A477 road between St. Clears and Pembroke Dock and the A478 road between Tenby and Cardigan. The community of Kilgetty contains the villages of Killgetty itself along with Reynalton and Begelly, with a joint population of 2011 recorded in the 2001 census, updated to 2,262 at the 2011 Census.
The village has local shopping facilities with a supermarket, newsagents, chemists, car and bicycle shop, carpet and bed shop, fish and chip shop, Chinese takeaway and Indian restaurant and takeaway.
The pub, which was previously called the Railway Inn, is now known as the White Horse. There is also a RAOB social club and a local sports club that has a cricket ground.

Kilgetty railway station is on the West Wales Line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lambston">
            <name>Lambston</name>
            <lat>51.8107479</lat>
            <lon>-5.038604</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lambston, sydd 83.1 milltir (133.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.4 milltir (340.3 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Lambston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lampeter velfrey">
            <name>Lampeter Velfrey</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lampeter Velfrey">Lampeter Velfrey (Welsh: Llanbedr Felfre) is a community in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales, and is 68.0 miles (109.4 km) from Cardiff and 196.0 miles (315.4 km) from London. In 2011 the population of Lampeter Velfrey was 1172 with 20.2% of them able to speak Welsh.
The old Medieval spelling was "Velfre"</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lamphey">
            <name>Lamphey</name>
            <lat>51.668477</lat>
            <lon>-4.871848</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lamphey">Lamphey (Welsh: Llandyf&#xE1;i) is a village near the south coast of Pembrokeshire, Wales, two miles east of Pembroke and two miles from the seaside village of Freshwater East.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#landshipping">
            <name>Landshipping</name>
            <lat>51.768415</lat>
            <lon>-4.882113</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landshipping">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Martletwy, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Landshipping, sydd 75.8 milltir (122 km) o Gaerdydd a 204.6 milltir (329.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Landshipping yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#landshipping quay">
            <name>Landshipping Quay</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lane head">
            <name>Lane Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lanesend">
            <name>Lanesend</name>
            <lat>51.7235919</lat>
            <lon>-4.793115</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanesend">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Jeffreyston, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lanesend, sydd 71.3 milltir (114.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.6 milltir (322.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Lanesend yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lawrenny">
            <name>Lawrenny</name>
            <lat>51.725606</lat>
            <lon>-4.871417</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrenny">Lawrenny is a village in the community council ward of Martletwy, in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is on a peninsula of the Cleddau estuary upriver from Milford Haven where it branches off towards the Cresswell and Carew Rivers and is in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrenny">Pentref yng nghymuned Martletwy, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lawrenny, sydd 74.7 milltir (120.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 204 milltir (328.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Lawrenny yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lawrenny quay">
            <name>Lawrenny Quay</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#leonardston">
            <name>Leonardston</name>
            <lat>51.7115694</lat>
            <lon>-4.9663762</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanstadwel, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Leonardston, sydd 78.7 milltir (126.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.2 milltir (335.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Leonardston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#letterston">
            <name>Letterston</name>
            <lat>51.92676</lat>
            <lon>-4.999115</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letterston">Letterston (Welsh: Treletert) is a rapidly growing village and local government community in the north of the county of Pembrokeshire, southwest Wales between Haverfordwest 10 miles (16 km) south and Fishguard 6 1&#x2044;2 miles (10 km) north on the A40 road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#leweston">
            <name>Leweston</name>
            <lat>51.863053</lat>
            <lon>-4.993182</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leweston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Leweston, sydd 82.2 milltir (132.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.8 milltir (337.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Leweston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#liddeston">
            <name>Liddeston</name>
            <lat>51.7210824</lat>
            <lon>-5.0482804</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liddeston">Liddeston is a small coastal village in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It belongs to the Milford North ward of the community of Milford Haven in the historical hundred of Roose. It is located to the north of the town of Milford Haven and the village of Hubberston.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liddeston">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Liddeston, sydd 82.1 milltir (132.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.6 milltir (340.5 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Liddeston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#linney head">
            <name>Linney Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#little haven">
            <name>Little Haven</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little Haven">Little Haven is a village at the south east corner of St Bride's Bay in Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. Together with the larger coastal village of Broad Haven to the north, Little Haven falls within the Havens community for which the 2001 census recorded a population of 1,328.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little Haven">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Little Haven (Saesneg, sef "Harbwr Bach"; dim enw Cymraeg). Mae'n gorwedd ar arfordir Sir Benfro tua 7 milltir i'r gorllewin o Hwlffordd a thua'r un pellter i'r gogledd-orllewin o Aberdaugleddau.
Mae'n rhan o Barc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Sir Benfro ac yn boblogaidd gan ymwelwyr sy'n mwynhau'r traeth llydan yno, ar lan Bae Sain Ffraid.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#little honeyborough">
            <name>Little Honeyborough</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little Honeyborough">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanstadwel, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Little Honeyborough, sydd 78.7 milltir (126.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.2 milltir (335 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Little Honeyborough yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#little milford">
            <name>Little Milford</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little Milford">Pentref yng nghymuned Freystrop, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Little Milford, sydd 78.6 milltir (126.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.4 milltir (333.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Little Milford yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#little newcastle">
            <name>Little Newcastle</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llan-mill">
            <name>Llan-mill</name>
            <lat>51.795641</lat>
            <lon>-4.697828</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llan-mill">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanbedr Felfre, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llan-mill, sydd 68.8 milltir (110.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.8 milltir (316.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llan-mill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanddewi velfrey">
            <name>Llanddewi Velfrey</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddewi Velfrey">Llanddewi Velfrey or Llandewi Velfrey (also Llan-ddewi-vel-vre) is a village and community of Pembrokeshire in West Wales. Historically it was located in the Hundred of Narbeth, and is located in the Lampeter Valley, 2 miles northeast of Narbeth along the A40. In 1831 it had a population of 710 people.
The village is situated in a rich and fertile vale, watered by the river T&#xE2;f, which separates the parish from that of Llangain in the county of Carmarthen. The lands are wholly enclosed and in a good state of cultivation, and the soil is eminently fertile.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llandeloy">
            <name>Llandeloy</name>
            <lat>51.897834</lat>
            <lon>-5.115374</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandeloy">Llandeloy (Welsh: Breudeth) is a small village in Pembrokeshire, South West Wales. Together with the parishes of Brawdy and Llanreithan, it constitutes the community of Brawdy, which had a census population of 611 in 2001.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandeloy">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Breudeth, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llandeloy, sydd 87.9 milltir (141.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 215.1 milltir (346.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llandeloy yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llandilo">
            <name>Llandilo</name>
            <lat>51.908513</lat>
            <lon>-4.758198</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandilo">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Mynachlog-ddu, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llandilo, sydd 73.9 milltir (118.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 200 milltir (321.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llandilo yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llandissilio">
            <name>Llandissilio</name>
            <lat>51.862042</lat>
            <lon>-4.730357</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandissilio">Llandissilio is a village and parish in east Pembrokeshire, Wales on the A478 road between Efailwen to the north and Clunderwen to the south. A largely ribbon development along the main road, the village is surrounded by farmland.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llandruidion">
            <name>Llandruidion</name>
            <lat>53.324061</lat>
            <lon>-3.827609</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandruidion">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llandruidion, sydd 91.8 milltir (147.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.6 milltir (353.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llandruidion yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llandygwydd">
            <name>Llandygwydd</name>
            <lat>52.064352</lat>
            <lon>-4.566113</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandygwydd">Llandygwydd is a small settlement in Ceredigion, west Wales, between Newcastle Emlyn and the town of Cardigan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llandygwydd">Pentref bychan yng nghymuned Beulah, Ceredigion, Cymru yw Llandygwydd, sydd 71.8 milltir (115.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 193.6 milltir (311.5 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Llandygwydd yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Elin Jones (Plaid Cymru) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Mark Williams (Y Democratiaid Rhyddfrydol).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanfair-nant-gwyn">
            <name>Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn</name>
            <lat>52.005711</lat>
            <lon>-4.677475</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn">Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn is a hamlet and small parish in the community of Eglwyswrw, north Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is a rural parish with few dwellings and was in the ancient Hundred of Cemais.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Crymych, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn, sydd 73.8 milltir (118.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 197.6 milltir (317.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanfair-Nant-Gwyn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanfyrnach">
            <name>Llanfyrnach</name>
            <lat>51.951374</lat>
            <lon>-4.591071</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfyrnach">Llanfyrnach (English: church of St Brynach) is a village and parish in the Hundred of Cemais, Pembrokeshire, Wales. The village is in the community and electoral ward of Crymych, while the village of Crymych and the hamlets of Hermon, Glandwr and Pentre Galar, are in Llanfyrnach parish.
Llanfyrnach village is in a remote upland area on the headwaters of the River T&#xE2;f, about 11 miles (18 km) from Cardigan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanfyrnach">Pentref bychan a phlwyf yn Sir Benfro yw Llanfyrnach. Fe'i lleolir mewn ardal wledig yng ngogledd y sir, i'r dwyrain o fryniau Preseli, tua deg milltir i'r de o Aberteifi.
Enwir y plwyf ar &#xF4;l Sant Brynach.
Ganwyd y bardd Niclas y Glais yno yn 1878.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llangloffan">
            <name>Llangloffan</name>
            <lat>51.949928</lat>
            <lon>-5.049474</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangloffan">Pentref yng nghymuned Pen-caer, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llangloffan, sydd 86.5 milltir (139.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.8 milltir (342.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llangloffan yng Nghynulliad Cenedlaethol Cymru gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llangolman">
            <name>Llangolman</name>
            <lat>51.910154</lat>
            <lon>-4.737173</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangolman">Llangolman (Welsh: Llangolman) is a village and parish on the southern flank of the Preseli Hills in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is part of the community of Mynachlog-ddu.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangolman">Pentref bychan a phlwyf yn Sir Benfro yw Llangolman. Mae'n gorwedd yng ngogledd y sir ar lethrau deheuol mynyddoedd y Preseli. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Mynachlog-ddu.
Enwir y plwyf ar &#xF4;l Sant Colman.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llangwm">
            <name>Llangwm</name>
            <lat>51.747112</lat>
            <lon>-4.91223</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwm">Llangwm could be one of several places in Wales:
Llangwm, Conwy
Llangwm, Monmouthshire
Llangwm, Pembrokeshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangwm">Gall Llangwm gyfeirio at sawl lle yng Nghymru:
Llangwm, pentref a chymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Conwy
Llangwm, pentref a chymuned yn Sir Benfro
Llan-gwm, pentref a chymuned yn Sir Fynwy</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanhowel">
            <name>Llanhowel</name>
            <lat>51.9026086</lat>
            <lon>-5.1718398</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanhowel">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanrhian, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llanhowel, sydd 90.4 milltir (145.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.7 milltir (350.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanhowel yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanion">
            <name>Llanion</name>
            <lat>52.2817522</lat>
            <lon>-4.1771996</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanion">Ardal yng nghymuned Doc Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llanion, sydd 77 milltir (123.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 206.6 milltir (332.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanion yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanon">
            <name>Llanon</name>
            <lat>52.2817522</lat>
            <lon>-4.1771996</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanon">Llanon (also spelt Llan-non) is a village in Ceredigion, Wales. It adjoins the village of Llansantffraid on the coast of Cardigan Bay, 5 mi (8.0 km) north of Aberaeron and 11 miles (18 km) south of Aberystwyth on the A487 road. It is situated on a raised beach. The village is named after the church of Saint Non (llan-Non), the mother of Saint David. By tradition, St David was brought up in Llanon.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanreath">
            <name>Llanreath</name>
            <lat>51.6909025</lat>
            <lon>-4.9607639</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanreath">Ardal yng nghymuned Doc Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llanreath, sydd 78 milltir (125.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.7 milltir (334.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanreath yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanrhian">
            <name>Llanrhian</name>
            <lat>51.937821</lat>
            <lon>-5.17394</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrhian">Llanrhian is a small village and community in Pembrokeshire in west Wales, near the coast, south of Porthgain village. According to the 2001 census it had a population of 897. The community of Llanrhian includes the settlements of Llanhowell (Welsh: Llanhywel), Croesgoch, Portheiddy, and Porthgain.
Llanrhian's church is dedicated to St Rhian and is a grade II* listed building. The village also contains an old school and farm cottage, built in 1769. A farm named Barry Island farm and the hamlet of Ynys Barri lies just to the northwest of the village which are not to be confused with Barry Island in southeast Wales in the Vale of Glamorgan. Llanrhian is also noted for its stone watermill named Melin Llanrhian which is now being run as a holiday cottage. The old machinery used in the mill still remains. The village is in the area of the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park.
Originally part of the Cantref of Pebediog (later Dewisland Hundred) granted in perpetuity to the Bishops of St Davids in 1082, the manors of Llanrhian, Castle Morris and Priskilly were, prior to 1175, granted to Maurice Fitzgerald by his brother, David Fitzgerald, second Norman approved Bishop of St Davids. They then remained with Fitzgerald's descendants, by then settled in Ireland, until 1302 when Sir John Wogan, Chancellor of St Davids and Lord Justiciar of Ireland bought out the remaining Fitzgerald interests in all three manors. Castle Morris and Priskilly were returned to the bishopric. But Llanrhian appears to have remained in the Wogan family until the 17th century when it passed by marriage into the Le Hunte family of Artramont. The Le Hunte's then in turn retained Llanrhian manor until the 1880s when it was sold to Henry Prosser, ancestor of the present owner.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrhian">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Llanrhian. Saif i'r gorllewin-ddwyrain o ddinas Tyddewi, i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A487 i Abergwaun.
Dyddia t&#x175;r yr eglwys, a gysegrwyd i Sant Rhian, o'r 13eg ganrif. Mae t&#xEE;m criced Llanrhian yn adnabyddus, ac wedi cael llwyddiant eithriadol i d&#xEE;m o bentref mor fychan.
Heblaw pentref Llanrhian ei hun, mae'r gymuned yn cynnwys Trefin a Phorth-gain. Ar un adeg roedd y diwydiant llechi yn bwysig yn yr ardal, gyda chwareli yn Abereiddi, Porth-gain a Thrwyn Llwyd. Allforid y llechi o borthladd bychan Porth-gain.
Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 897.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanstadwell">
            <name>Llanstadwell</name>
            <lat>51.705504</lat>
            <lon>-4.970607</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanstadwell">Llanstadwell is a small village, parish and community in south Pembrokeshire, Wales, on the north bank of the River Cleddau between Milford Haven and Neyland.
The community of Llanstadwell includes the settlements of Hazelbeach, Mascle Bridge (or Mastlebridge), Jordanston, Waterston and Little Honeyborough.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanteg">
            <name>Llanteg</name>
            <lat>51.761407</lat>
            <lon>-4.636889</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanteg">Llanteg (also previously known, and still regularly pronounced, as Lanteague) is a small village in Pembrokeshire, Wales, belonging to the Community of Amroth.
It contains a 13th-century church (St Elidyr) and two closed chapels.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanwnda">
            <name>Llanwnda</name>
            <lat>53.101171</lat>
            <lon>-4.276897</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanwnda">Llanwnda may refer to:
Llanwnda, Gwynedd
Llanwnda, Pembrokeshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanwnda">Gall Llanwnda gyfeirio at:
Llanwnda, pentref yng Ngwynedd
Llanwnda, pentref yn Sir Benfro</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanycefn">
            <name>Llanycefn</name>
            <lat>51.877767</lat>
            <lon>-4.758119</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanycefn">Pentref yng nghymuned Maenclochog, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Llanycefn, sydd 73.4 milltir (118.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.1 milltir (322.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Llanycefn yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llanychaer">
            <name>Llanychaer</name>
            <lat>51.980083</lat>
            <lon>-4.93236</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanychaer">Pentref bychan ger Abergwaun yn Sir Benfro ydy Llanychaer (Llannerch-aur yn wreiddiol; ceir y ffurf Llanych&#xE2;r hefyd; Saesneg: Llanychaer Bridge). Roedd 176 o drigolion yn byw yn y pentref yn 1833. Gorwedd ar lan Afon Gwaun.
Mae'r enw Saesneg yn cyfeirio at yr hen bont ar afon Gwaun.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llawhaden">
            <name>Llawhaden</name>
            <lat>51.821392</lat>
            <lon>-4.803403</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llawhaden">Llawhaden (Welsh: Llanhuadain) is a village and community in the Hundred of Dungleddy (Welsh: Daugleddyf), Pembrokeshire, West Wales. The community of Llawhaden includes also the parish of Robeston Wathen, part of Narberth and the hamlet of Gelli, and had a population of 634 in 2001, increasing to 688 at the 2011 Census.
^ "Community population 2011". Retrieved 20 April 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llechryd">
            <name>Llechryd</name>
            <lat>52.062678</lat>
            <lon>-4.601234</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llechryd">Llechryd (Welsh pronunciation: [&#x26C;&#x25B;xr&#x26A;d]) is a village on the A484 road approximately 3 miles (4.8 km) from Cardigan, in Ceredigion, Wales. It is part of the Community of Llangoedmor.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llechryd">Pentref yn Nyffryn Teifi, Ceredigion yw Llechryd, a leolir tua 3 milltir a hanner i'r de-ddwyrain o Aberteifi.
Saif y pentref ar lan ogleddol afon Teifi ar l&#xF4;n yr A484 rhwng Castell Newydd Emlyn ac Aberteifi. Ceir pont ar afon Teifi yn y pentref sy'n dwyn y ffordd i Gilgerran ac Abercuch ar y lan ddeheuol.
Llai na milltir i'r dwyrain o Lechryd ceir safle hen blas Maenordeifi (Manordeifi). Glanarberth yw'r enw ar ran o'r pentref, sy'n dwyn cysylltiad ag Arberth (safle llys Pwyll yng nghainc gyntaf y Mabinogi).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llwyn-y-brain">
            <name>Llwyn-y-brain</name>
            <lat>51.9791792</lat>
            <lon>-3.8408241</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llwyn-y-brain">Gallai Llwyn-y-brain gyfeirio at un o ddau bentref yn Sir Gaerfyrddin:

Llwyn-y-brain, Hendy-gwyn ar Daf, yng ngorllewin y sir
Llwyn-y-brain, Llanymddyfri, yn nwyrain y sir</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llwyn-yr-hwrdd">
            <name>Llwyn-yr-hwrdd</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llwynduris">
            <name>Llwynduris</name>
            <lat>51.5854835</lat>
            <lon>-3.6396835</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llys-y-fran">
            <name>Llys-y-fran</name>
            <lat>51.882923</lat>
            <lon>-4.845334</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#llys-y-fran reservoir">
            <name>Llys-y-fran Reservoir</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#loveston">
            <name>Loveston</name>
            <lat>51.742386</lat>
            <lon>-4.77695</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loveston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Jeffreyston, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Loveston, sydd 71 milltir (114.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 200 milltir (321.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Loveston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lower freystrop">
            <name>Lower Freystrop</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower Freystrop">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Freystrop, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lower Freystrop, sydd 79.2 milltir (127.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 208 milltir (334.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Lower Freystrop yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lower solva">
            <name>Lower Solva</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lower town">
            <name>Lower Town</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower Town">Lower Town (also spelled "Lowertown" (French: la Basse-Ville) is a neighbourhood in Rideau-Vanier Ward in central Ottawa, Ontario, Canada, to the east of downtown. It is the oldest part of the city. It is bounded roughly by Rideau Street to the south, Sussex Drive and Ottawa River to the north, the Rideau Canal to the west, and the Rideau River to the east. It includes the commercial Byward Market area in the south-western part, and is predominantly residential in the north and east.
It was historically French Canadian and Irish (as opposed to English and Scottish Upper Town, a term no longer in use) and is to this day home to many Franco-Ontarian families, businesses and institutions. Its total population according to the Canada 2011 Census is 12,274 (including Porter Island)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower Town">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Abergwaun ac Wdig, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lower Town, sydd 84.4 milltir (135.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.6 milltir (337.4 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Lower Town yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ludchurch">
            <name>Ludchurch</name>
            <lat>51.763649</lat>
            <lon>-4.69569</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludchurch">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanbedr Felfre, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Ludchurch, sydd 68 milltir (109.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.6 milltir (316.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Ludchurch yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#lydstep">
            <name>Lydstep</name>
            <lat>51.6489053</lat>
            <lon>-4.7646097</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lydstep">Pentref yng nghymuned Maenorb&#x177;r, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Lydstep, sydd 69.4 milltir (111.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 199.4 milltir (320.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Lydstep yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#maddox moor">
            <name>Maddox Moor</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maddox Moor">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Freystrop, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Maddox Moor, sydd 78.6 milltir (126.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.5 milltir (333.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Maddox Moor yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#maenclochog">
            <name>Maenclochog</name>
            <lat>51.9105909</lat>
            <lon>-4.788986</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maenclochog">Maenclochog is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales. It is also an electoral ward comprising an area that brings together the villages of Llanycefn, Maenclochog and Rosebush. The electoral ward had a population at the 2011 census of 3,104.
Maenclochog lies south of the Preseli Hills, about one mile southeast of the village of Rosebush on the B4313 Narberth to Fishguard road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maenclochog">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Sir Benfro, de-orllewin Cymru, yw Maenclochog (cyfeiriad grid SN083273). Mae'n gorwedd i'r de o fryniau Preseli, tua milltir i'r de-ddwyrain o bentref Rosebush ac 11 milltir i'r de-ddwyrain o Abergwaun.
Ym 2007 darganfuwyd olion muriau hen gastell, sy'n dyddio i'r 13eg ganrif efallai, wrth gloddio ar safle maes parcio newydd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#maiden wells">
            <name>Maiden Wells</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maiden Wells">Maidenwells is a small village 1.6 miles south of Pembroke in Pembrokeshire. The population is currently around 300.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maiden Wells">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Maiden Wells (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg). Mae'n gorwedd yn ne'r sir 1.5 milltir i'r de o dref Penfro. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Hundleton.
Cofnodir yr enw am y tro cyntaf fel Mayden Welle, a hynny yn 1336. Mae 350 o bobl yn byw yno heddiw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#manorbier">
            <name>Manorbier</name>
            <lat>51.646019</lat>
            <lon>-4.797414</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manorbier">Manorbier (/&#x2CC;m&#xE6;n&#x259;r&#x2C8;b&#x26A;&#x259;r/; Welsh: Maenorb&#x177;r [m&#x251;&#x268;n&#x254;r&#x2C8;b&#x268;&#x2D0;r]) is a village on the south coast of Pembrokeshire, Wales. The name means the 'Manor of P&#x177;r'. The village is served by Manorbier railway station on the West Wales Line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#manorbier newton">
            <name>Manorbier Newton</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#manorowen">
            <name>Manorowen</name>
            <lat>51.9865319</lat>
            <lon>-5.010226</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#marloes">
            <name>Marloes</name>
            <lat>51.7315479</lat>
            <lon>-5.197859</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marloes">Marloes is a village and parish in Pembrokeshire, West Wales, on the Marloes Peninsula 7 miles (11 km) west of the port of Milford Haven and forms the westernmost tip of the southern shore of St Brides Bay. It is within part of the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. The parish has 6 miles (10 km) of mainland coastline accessible throughout by the Pembrokeshire Coast Path and, together with St Brides, constitutes the community of Marloes and St Brides (population 323 in 2001).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marloes">Pentref bychan ar arfordir gorllewinol Sir Benfro ar lan Bae Sain Ffraid yw Marloes. Cyfeirir at y penrhyn y saif arno fel 'Penrhyn Marloes' yn ogystal. Mae'n gymuned wasgaredig tua 8 milltir i'r gorllewin o Aberdaugleddau.
Mae Marloes yn adnabyddus am ei draeth ardderchog a leolir milltir i'r gogledd o'r pentref ar Fae Sain Ffraid. Mae'r clogwynni hen dywodfaen coch yn enwog ym myd daeareg fel enghreifftiau gwych o'r graig honno.

Gyferbyn i ben y penrhyn mae Ynys Skomer a'i bywyd gwyllt. I'r de o Farloes mae pentref Dale a Bae Westdale. Glaniodd Harri Tudur ym Mill Bay yn 1487 ac oddi yno deithiodd drwy Gymru i Faes Bosworth.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#martletwy">
            <name>Martletwy</name>
            <lat>51.761079</lat>
            <lon>-4.847286</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martletwy">Martletwy is a village and community in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martletwy">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Martletwy. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg am y pentref. Saif i'r dwyrain o Afon Cleddau, tua hanner y ffordd rhwng Hwlffordd a Dinbych y Pysgod.
Ail-adeiladwyd yr eglwys, a gysegrwyd i Sant Marchell yn yr Oesoedd Canol, yn 1848-1850.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Landshipping a Lawrenni, ac yn ymestyn at lan Afon Cleddau. Ar un adeg, bu mwyngloddio ac allforio glo carreg yn weddol bwysig yn yr ardal. Ceir canolfan ymwelwyr Oakwood, gyda reidiau ac atyniadau eraill, o fewn y gymuned. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 523 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mascle bridge">
            <name>Mascle Bridge</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mascle Bridge">Ardal yng nghymuned Llanstadwel, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Mascle Bridge, sydd 78.3 milltir (126.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.9 milltir (334.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Mascle Bridge yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mathry">
            <name>Mathry</name>
            <lat>51.945207</lat>
            <lon>-5.087567</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathry">Mathry (Welsh: Mathri) is a village in Pembrokeshire, Wales. Situated some 6 miles west of Fishguard, the village is perched atop a hill.
In 2006 in records office in Haverfordwest records were found, which show a Jemima Nicholas being baptised in the parish of Mathry on 2 March 1755.
Nearby villages include Abercastle, Trefin, Porthgain, Llanrhian, Square and Compass, Penparc and Croesgoch.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mayeston">
            <name>Mayeston</name>
            <lat>51.6982738</lat>
            <lon>-4.8814355</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayeston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cosheston, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Mayeston, sydd 74.7 milltir (120.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 204.3 milltir (328.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Mayeston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#merrion">
            <name>Merrion</name>
            <lat>51.635362</lat>
            <lon>-4.9818809</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merrion">Merrion, Merion, or Meirion may refer to:
Places
United States:
Merion, Pennsylvania
Merion Village, Columbus, Ohio
Wales:
Merrion, Pembrokeshire
Merionethshire
Meirionnydd
Merrion Estate, Dublin, Ireland:
Merrion Gates
Merrion Road
Merrion Square
Merrion Street
Mount Merrion
People
Meirion, father of Caradog ap Meirion, King of Gwynedd (reigned 754? &#x2013; 798)
Mem Fox (Merrion Frances Partridge, b.1946), Australian children's author
Other
SS Merion, 1902 ocean liner
Merrion Centre (disambiguation)
Merion Golf Club, Merion, Pennsylvania
Merion Cricket Club, Merion, Pennsylvania
Merrion Cricket Club, Dublin, Ireland</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merrion">Pentref yng nghymuned Castellmartin a Stackpole, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Merrion, sydd 78.3 milltir (126 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.6 milltir (335.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Merrion yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mesur-y-dorth">
            <name>Mesur-y-dorth</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mesur-y-dorth">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanrhian, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Mesur-y-dorth, sydd 89.9 milltir (144.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.7 milltir (348.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Mesur-y-dorth yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#middle hill">
            <name>Middle Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Freystrop, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Middle Hill, sydd 79.2 milltir (127.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 208 milltir (334.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Middle Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#middle mill">
            <name>Middle Mill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle Mill">Middle Mill (Welsh: Felinganol) is a small settlement on the River Solva in the parish of Whitchurch, Pembrokeshire, Wales, approximately 1 mile upstream from the coastal village of Solva.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#milford haven (aberdaughleddau)">
            <name>Milford Haven (Aberdaughleddau)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#millin cross">
            <name>Millin Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millin Cross">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Uzmaston, Boulston a Slebets, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Millin Cross, sydd 78.7 milltir (126.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.1 milltir (333.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Millin Cross yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#milton">
            <name>Milton</name>
            <lat>51.6923559</lat>
            <lon>-4.835491</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milton">Milton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#minwear">
            <name>Minwear</name>
            <lat>51.7817182</lat>
            <lon>-4.8435295</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minwear">Minwear is a parish in the community council ward of Martletwy, in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales, located 4 1&#x2044;2 miles (7.2 km) southwest of the town of Narberth.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minwear">Pentref yng nghymuned Martletwy, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Minwear, sydd 74.5 milltir (119.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 203 milltir (326.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Minwear yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#monington">
            <name>Monington</name>
            <lat>53.1716983</lat>
            <lon>-3.0583711</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monington">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Nanhyfer, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Monington, sydd 77.5 milltir (124.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.2 milltir (322.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Monington yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#monkstone point">
            <name>Monkstone Point</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#monkton">
            <name>Monkton</name>
            <lat>51.4275405</lat>
            <lon>-3.5408054</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monkton">Monkton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monkton">Gallai Monkton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mount pleasant">
            <name>Mount Pleasant</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount Pleasant">Mount Pleasant may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#moylgrove">
            <name>Moylgrove</name>
            <lat>52.068194</lat>
            <lon>-4.747112</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moylgrove">Moylgrove (Welsh: Trewyddel), also spelled Moylegrove, is a village and parish in north Pembrokeshire, Wales, about 7 kilometres (4.3 mi) from Cardigan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#musselwick">
            <name>Musselwick</name>
            <lat>51.7181428</lat>
            <lon>-5.1481197</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musselwick">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanisan-yn-Rhos, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Musselwick, sydd 86.4 milltir (139.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.1 milltir (347.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Musselwick yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#mynachlog-ddu">
            <name>Mynachlog-ddu</name>
            <lat>51.942386</lat>
            <lon>-4.701729</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynachlog-ddu">Mynachlog-ddu (SN143306) is a village and community in the Preseli Hills, Pembrokeshire, Wales. The community includes the parish of Llangolman.
^ "Community population". Retrieved 20 April 2015.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynachlog-ddu">Pentref, cymuned a phlwyf yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Mynachlog-ddu. Saif ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r briffordd A478, ac i'r de-orllewin o bentref Crymych. I'r gorllewin o'r pentref mae copaon Mynydd Preseli. Credir fod rhai o gerrig C&#xF4;r y Cewri wedi dod o Gaermeini, neu'n fwy cywir Carn Menyn gerllaw.
Cysegrwyd yr eglwys i Sant Dogfael; cyn diddymu'r mynachlogydd roedd y plwyf yn eiddo i Abaty Llandudoch. Roedd Thomas Rees (Twm Carnabwth) (1806 - 1876), un o arweinwyr Merched Beca, yn frodor o Fynachlog-ddu, ac mae wedi ei gladdu yma. Bu'r bardd Waldo Williams yn byw yma o 1911 hyd 1915, pan oedd ei dad yn brifathro ar yr ysgol gynradd, ac yma y dysgodd Gymraeg. Ceir cofeb iddo gerllaw'r pentref.
Bu'r Parch Parry Roberts a oedd yn frodor o Sir F&#xF4;n yn weinidog ar gapel y Bedyddwyr yma am gyfnod hir. Ef oedd un o'r ymgyrchwyr yn erbyn y Weinyddiaeth filwrol gymryd drosodd ffermydd yr ardal i'w gwneud yn ardal ymarfer rhyfel.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#narberth (arberth)">
            <name>Narberth (Arberth)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#narberth bridge">
            <name>Narberth Bridge</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#nevern">
            <name>Nevern</name>
            <lat>52.02347</lat>
            <lon>-4.795869</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nevern">Nevern (Welsh: Nanhyfer) is a small village or hamlet, of just a few houses in Pembrokeshire, West Wales which, together with the adjacent settlements of Felindre Farchog, Monington, Moylgrove and Bayvil, constitutes the community of Nevern. It lies in the valley of the River Nevern close to the Preseli Hills of the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park 2 miles (3 km) east of Newport.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#new hedges">
            <name>New Hedges</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/New Hedges">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanfair Dinbych-y-pysgod, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw New Hedges, sydd 67.4 milltir (108.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.9 milltir (316.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir New Hedges yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#new moat">
            <name>New Moat</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New Moat">New Moat (Welsh: Y Mot) is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It extends from the southern edges of Mynydd Preseli to the Pembrokeshire-Carmarthenshire border.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#newchapel">
            <name>Newchapel</name>
            <lat>52.025143</lat>
            <lon>-4.584443</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newchapel">Newchapel is a hamlet in the Borough of Newcastle-under-Lyme, close to Kidsgrove in Staffordshire, England.
Newchapel was originally named Thursfield. It was mentioned in the Domesday Book in 1086 as Turvoldesfeld. After the Reformation in the 17th century the land reverted to private ownership, the new owner built a stone Chapel and the village was renamed Newchapel.
From 1894 to 1904 Newchapel formed part of Wolstanton Rural District. After re-organisation of boundaries, from 1904 to 1974 it was part of Kidsgrove Urban District; following the Local Government Act 1972, it was absorbed into the Borough of Newcastle-under-Lyme.
Newchapel was served by a railway station (shared with Goldenhill), Newchapel and Goldenhill on the Potteries Loop, which was opened by the North Staffordshire Railway on 1 October 1874 and closed on 2 March 1964.
The canal engineer James Brindley (1716 &#x2013; 27 September 1772) died at his Turnhurst estate in Newchapel, within sight of his unfinished Harecastle Tunnel. On 30 September 1772, just nine days after the completion of his Birmingham Canal, he was buried in the churchyard of Newchapel; the present church, St. James, is dedicated to his memory. The grave is marked by a bronze plaque.
During the excavation work for the first Harecastle Tunnel, large amounts of coal were discovered underground. This led to the development, initially by the Duke of Bridgewater and then by Robert Heath and Sons of a significant mining and coal by-products works known as Birchenwood. Growing from the Birchenwood Colliery Company founded in 1893, this was the largest industrial site that the Newchapel area has ever known and provided employment for several thousand people in its heyday. Newchapel as seen today was born as a result of the success of Birchenwood, and the first houses built were to provide homes for the workers and their families.
^ "St James Church, Newchapel - History Page". Churchonhill.org.uk. 1957-09-06. Retrieved 2011-12-01. 
^ "harriseahead.com". harriseahead.com. Retrieved 2011-12-01. 
^ "birchenwoodhistory". Btinternet.com. 1913-04-23. Archived from the original on 2012-06-30. Retrieved 2011-12-01.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#newgale">
            <name>Newgale</name>
            <lat>51.859305</lat>
            <lon>-5.124496</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#newton cross">
            <name>Newton Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton Cross">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-lai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Newton Cross, sydd 85.6 milltir (137.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.7 milltir (342.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Newton Cross yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#neyland">
            <name>Neyland</name>
            <lat>51.704948</lat>
            <lon>-4.948318</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neyland">Neyland is a town in Pembrokeshire, Wales, lying on the River Cleddau and the upstream end of the Milford Haven estuary. The nearby Cleddau Bridge crosses the river, linking Neyland to Pembroke Dock.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neyland">Tref a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Neyland. Mae yn y rhanbarth Saesneg ei iaith o'r sir, ac nid ymddengys bod enw Cymraeg. Saif ar ochr ogleddol Afon Cleddau, gyferbyn a Doc Penfro, gyda Phont Cleddau yn eu cysylltu. Mae Caerdydd 125.3 km i ffwrdd o Neyland ac mae Llundain yn 335.8 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Abertawe sy'n 68.8 km i ffwrdd.
Pentref pysgota bychan oedd Neyland hyd 1856, pan ddaeth yn orsaf a phorthladd ar ben draw Rheilffordd y Great Western a adeiladwyd gan Isambard Kingdom Brunel. Yn 1899 agorwyd porthladd newydd yn Wdig ger Abergwaun, a lleihaodd y defnydd o Neyland. Caewyd porthladd Neyland yn 1964.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#nine wells">
            <name>Nine Wells</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nine Wells">Pentref bychan yng nghymuned Solfach, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Nine Wells, sydd 91.6 milltir (147.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.4 milltir (353 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Nine Wells yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#nolton">
            <name>Nolton</name>
            <lat>51.821357</lat>
            <lon>-5.097392</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nolton">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Nolton (ni cheir enw Cymraeg). Mae'n gorwedd ger yr arfordir tua miilltir o lan Bae Sain Ffraid yng ngorllewin y sir. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Nolton a'r Garn.
Ceir traeth Nolton (Nolton Haven) i'r gorllewin o Nolton. Mae'r pentref a'r ardal o'i gwmpas yn rhan o Barc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Sir Benfro ac mae Llwybr Arfordir Sir Benfro yn mynd heibio gerllaw.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#nolton haven">
            <name>Nolton Haven</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nolton Haven">Nolton Haven is a hamlet halfway along the coast of St Bride's Bay in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is included within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. Together with the larger inland village of Nolton which is about 1km to the southeast and the village of Roch, Nolton Haven falls within Nolton and Roch community.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nolton Haven">Pentref yng nghymuned Nolton a'r Garn, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Nolton Haven, sydd 86.2 milltir (138.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 214.5 milltir (345.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#nyfer">
            <name>Nyfer</name>
            <lat>52.0214404</lat>
            <lon>-4.829775</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#orlandon">
            <name>Orlandon</name>
            <lat>51.7403995</lat>
            <lon>-5.1717743</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orlandon">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Marloes a Sain Ffr&#xEA;d, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Orlandon, sydd 87.5 milltir (140.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.9 milltir (349.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#parrog">
            <name>Parrog</name>
            <lat>52.020532</lat>
            <lon>-4.843892</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parrog">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Parrog. Mae'n gorwedd ger yr arfordir tua milltir i'r gorllewin o dref fechan Trefdraeth.
Bu cloddio am lechi yma yn y gorffennol a cheir Chwarel Parrog gerllaw.
Mae'r pentref yn gorwedd o fewn ffin Parc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Sir Benfro ac mae Llwybr Arfordir Sir Benfro yn rhedeg trwyddo. Mae'n boblogaidd gan dwristiaid. Ceir clwb golff a meysydd carafanio.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pelcomb">
            <name>Pelcomb</name>
            <lat>51.822572</lat>
            <lon>-5.016065</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelcomb">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pelcomb, sydd 82.3 milltir (132.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.5 milltir (338.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pelcomb yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pelcomb bridge">
            <name>Pelcomb Bridge</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelcomb Bridge">Ardal yng nghymuned Hwlffordd, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pelcomb Bridge, sydd 81.5 milltir (131.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.8 milltir (337.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pelcomb Bridge yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pelcomb cross">
            <name>Pelcomb Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelcomb Cross">Pentref yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pelcomb Cross, sydd 82.5 milltir (132.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.7 milltir (339.1 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pelcomb Cross yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pembroke (penfro)">
            <name>Pembroke (Penfro)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pembroke dock">
            <name>Pembroke Dock</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pembroke Dock">Pembroke Dock (Welsh: Doc Penfro) is a town in Pembrokeshire, South West Wales, lying north of Pembroke on the River Cleddau. Originally a small fishing village known as Paterchurch, the town was greatly expanded from 1814 onwards following the construction of a Royal Naval Dockyard. It is the third largest town in Pembrokeshire after Haverfordwest and Milford Haven.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pembroke ferry">
            <name>Pembroke Ferry</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pembroke Ferry">Ardal yng nghymuned Doc Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pembroke Ferry, sydd 77 milltir (123.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 206.6 milltir (332.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pembroke Ferry yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pen brush">
            <name>Pen Brush</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pen-bedw">
            <name>Pen-bedw</name>
            <lat>51.5616488</lat>
            <lon>-3.4054019</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-bedw">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Boncath, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pen-bedw, sydd 72 milltir (115.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 195 milltir (313.8 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pen-bedw yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pen-lan-mabws">
            <name>Pen-Lan-mabws</name>
            <lat>51.927299</lat>
            <lon>-5.0824864</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen-Lan-mabws">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-lai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pen-Lan-mabws, sydd 87.2 milltir (140.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 214 milltir (344.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pen-Lan-mabws yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pen-y-bryn">
            <name>Pen-y-Bryn</name>
            <lat>52.053908</lat>
            <lon>-4.659392</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penally (penalum)">
            <name>Penally (Penalum)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penalum (penally)">
            <name>Penalum (Penally)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penbwchdy">
            <name>Penbwchdy</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penclegyr">
            <name>Penclegyr</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penffordd">
            <name>Penffordd</name>
            <lat>52.077664</lat>
            <lon>-4.218352</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penfro (pembroke)">
            <name>Penfro (Pembroke)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pennar">
            <name>Pennar</name>
            <lat>51.68492</lat>
            <lon>-4.949309</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennar">Ardal yng nghymuned Doc Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pennar, sydd 77.4 milltir (124.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.3 milltir (333.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pennar yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).

</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pennar park">
            <name>Pennar Park</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennar Park">Ardal yng nghymuned Doc Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pennar Park, sydd 78.4 milltir (126.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.2 milltir (335 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pennar Park yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penparc">
            <name>Penparc</name>
            <lat>52.101573</lat>
            <lon>-4.611118</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penparc">Ceir dau bentref yng Nghymru o'r enw Penparc:
Penparc, Ceredigion
Penparc, Sir Benfro</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penrhyn castle">
            <name>Penrhyn Castle</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrhyn Castle">Penrhyn Castle is a country house in Llandegai, Bangor, Gwynedd, North Wales, in the form of a Norman castle. It was originally a medieval fortified manor house, founded by Ednyfed Fychan. In 1438, Ioan ap Gruffudd was granted a licence to crenellate and he founded the stone castle and added a tower house. Samuel Wyatt reconstructed the property in the 1780s.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pentlepoir">
            <name>Pentlepoir</name>
            <lat>51.721599</lat>
            <lon>-4.726967</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentlepoir">Pentref yng nghymuned Dwyrain Trewiliam, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pentlepoir, sydd 68.6 milltir (110.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 197.8 milltir (318.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pentlepoir yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pentre galar">
            <name>Pentre Galar</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentre Galar">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Pentre Galar.
Fe'i lleolir ar bwys ffordd yr A478 tua 12 milltir i'r de o Aberteifi, tua hanner ffordd rhwng y dref honno ac Arberth i'r de. I'r gorllewin o'r pentref ceir Mynydd Preseli. Y pentref agosaf yw Crymych, tua 2 filltir i'r gogledd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pentrisil">
            <name>Pentrisil</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentrisil">Pentref yng nghymuned Cwm Gwaun, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pentrisil, sydd 78.4 milltir (126.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 203.5 milltir (327.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pentrisil yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penycwm">
            <name>Penycwm</name>
            <lat>51.868072</lat>
            <lon>-5.125027</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penycwm">Penycwm (Welsh for "Head of the valley") is a small settlement on the A487 road near Newgale, Pembrokeshire, Wales. It is part of the parish of Brawdy. At the other end of a valley to the coast is Penycwm beach, also known as Pwll March. 
The community's Independent Chapel, built in 1870, has now been converted into residential accommodation.
Penycwm was also the location for the United Kingdom's first 5-star youth hostel.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penycwm">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Breudeth, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Penycwm, sydd 87.7 milltir (141.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 215.4 milltir (346.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Penycwm yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penyfeidr">
            <name>Penyfeidr</name>
            <lat>51.8526739</lat>
            <lon>-4.749423</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penyfeidr">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Breudeth, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Penyfeidr, sydd 87.3 milltir (140.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 214.5 milltir (345.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Penyfeidr yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penygroes">
            <name>Penygroes</name>
            <lat>53.05459</lat>
            <lon>-4.283645</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygroes">Penygroes or Pen-y-groes may refer to any of several places in Wales:
Penygroes, Gwynedd
Penygroes railway station, a former station in the town

Penygroes, Pembrokeshire
Pen-y-groes, Carmarthenshire</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penygroes">Am y pentref bychan yn Sir Gaerfyrddin, gweler Pen-y-groes, Sir Gaerfyrddin.

Pentref mawr yng Ngwynedd yw Penygroes (hefyd: Pen-y-groes). Fe'i lleolir yn Nyffryn Nantlle, ger pentrefi Llanllyfni, Carmel a Groeslon.
Lleolir Ysgol Dyffryn Nantlle yn y pentref, ynghyd &#xE2; ffatri papur toiled a chlwb peldroed enwog Nantlle Vale. Dyma ganolfan fasnachol ac economaidd y dyffryn, bellach wedi edwino rhyw gymaint ers agor ffordd osgoi heibio pentrefi'r cwm. Yno hefyd mae meddygfeydd, llyfrgell, canolfan dechnoleg, canolfan hamdden Plas Silyn, fferyllydd a stad ddiwydiannol. Cydnabyddir fel un o'r cymunedau Cymreiciaf yn y byd, gyda mwy na 90% yn gallu'r Gymraeg yno.
Mae bysiau sy'n rhedeg i Gaernarfon yn gwasanaethu'r pentref.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#penyraber">
            <name>Penyraber</name>
            <lat>51.872903</lat>
            <lon>-5.1943142</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penyraber">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Abergwaun ac Wdig, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Penyraber, sydd 85.1 milltir (136.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.3 milltir (338.4 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Penyraber yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pill">
            <name>Pill</name>
            <lat>51.480421</lat>
            <lon>-2.68773</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pill">Pill or The Pill may refer to:
Drug-related:
Pill (pharmacy), referring to anything small and round for a specific dose of medicine
"The Pill", a general nickname for the combined oral contraceptive pill
Places:
Pill, Tyrol, a municipality in Austria
Pill, Somerset, a village in the United Kingdom
Pill, a colloquial abbreviation of Pillgwenlly, electoral ward in the city of Newport, South Wales
Entertainment:
"The Pill" (song), a 1975 song by Loretta Lynn
"The Pill", a 1965 song by The Brothers-in-Law on their 1965 album "Oh, Oh, Canada"
The Pill (film), a 2011 film
"The Pill", a 1999 episode of That '70s Show TV series
"Pills", a song by Bo Diddley
People:
Alison Pill (born 1985), Canadian actress
Brett Pill (born 1984), American Major League Baseball player
Cathy Pill, Belgian fashion designer
Malcolm Pill (born 1938), a former Lord Justice of Appeal of the Court of Appeal of England and Wales
Pill (rapper), American rapper
Other uses:
Pill (textile), a small ball of fuzz on cloth, or the creation of such fuzz balls</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pill">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pill, sydd 80.9 milltir (130.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.5 milltir (338.8 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#plain dealings">
            <name>Plain Dealings</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain Dealings">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanhuadain, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Plain Dealings, sydd 74.3 milltir (119.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 202.1 milltir (325.3 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Plain Dealings yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pleasant valley">
            <name>Pleasant Valley</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleasant Valley">Pleasant Valley may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleasant Valley">Pentref yng nghymuned Amroth, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pleasant Valley, sydd 67.1 milltir (108 km) o Gaerdydd a 196.1 milltir (315.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pleasant Valley yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pont-yr-hafod">
            <name>Pont-yr-hafod</name>
            <lat>51.5205165</lat>
            <lon>-3.3226661</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pont-yr-hafod">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-lai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pont-yr-hafod, sydd 85.1 milltir (137 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.3 milltir (341.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pont-yr-hafod yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pontfaen">
            <name>Pontfaen</name>
            <lat>51.9679209</lat>
            <lon>-4.881518</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontfaen">Am y dref ym Mro Morgannwg, gweler Y Bont-faen.

Pentref yn Sir Benfro yw Pontfaen. Saif i'r de-ddwyrain o Abergwaun ac i'r gogledd o'r ffordd B4313. Enwir y pentref ar &#xF4;l y bont sydd yn croesi'r Afon Gwaun sy'n llifo drwy ei ganol.
Mae'r pentref yn enwog am dafarn hynafol a nodedig y Dyffryn Arms neu fel a elwir ar lafar gwlad "Tafarn Bessie" ar &#xF4;l gwraig y dafarn, Mrs Bessie Davies. Yma y gwerthir un math o gwrw'n unig.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pontiago">
            <name>Pontiago</name>
            <lat>52.0099064</lat>
            <lon>-5.0277981</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontiago">Pentref yng nghymuned Pen-caer, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pontiago, sydd 87.3 milltir (140.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.4 milltir (341.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pontiago yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pontyglasier">
            <name>Pontyglasier</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pope hill">
            <name>Pope Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Johnston, Sir Benfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pope Hill, sydd 80.4 milltir (129.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.2 milltir (336.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Pope Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#port lion">
            <name>Port Lion</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port Lion">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Burton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Port Lion, sydd 76.6 milltir (123.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 205.8 milltir (331.2 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Port Lion yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#portfield gate">
            <name>Portfield Gate</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portfield Gate">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Portfield Gate, sydd 82 milltir (131.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.5 milltir (338.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Portfield Gate yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#portheiddy">
            <name>Portheiddy</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#porthgain">
            <name>Porthgain</name>
            <lat>51.947171</lat>
            <lon>-5.180185</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porthgain">Porthgain (Welsh for fair/beautiful port) is a village in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park in Wales, located between St David's and Goodwick, and just north of Llanrhian.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#poyston">
            <name>Poyston</name>
            <lat>51.839995</lat>
            <lon>-4.952707</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poyston">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Rudbaxton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Poyston, sydd 79.9 milltir (128.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.8 milltir (334.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Poyston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#poyston cross">
            <name>Poyston Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poyston Cross">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Rudbaxton, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Poyston Cross, sydd 79.3 milltir (127.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.2 milltir (333.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Poyston Cross yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#prendergast">
            <name>Prendergast</name>
            <lat>51.80935</lat>
            <lon>-4.963356</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prendergast">Prendergast (alt Prendergrast or Pendergrast) (Irish: de Priondarg&#xE1;s) is a Hiberno-Norman name.
It may have its origins in Berwickshire, in the hamlet now called Prenderguest or in the hamlet of Prendergast (Haverfordwest) in Pembrokeshire. The Prendergast name in Ireland derives from the 12th century Norman Knight Maurice de Prendergast, who came to Ireland with Strongbow. His descendants were seated in Tipperary and in south Mayo, counties in which the name has always subsequently been most populous. Some families of Prendergast assumed the name Fitzmaurice at an early date. The Prendergasts who assumed the Fitzmaurice name were also called MacMorris.
Variant spellings of Prendergast include Pender, Pendergast, Pendergrass, Penders, Pendy, Pinder, Pinders, Pindy, Prender, Prendergest, Prindergast, Pendergist.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prendergast">Ardal o fewn i Hwlffordd yng nghymuned Hwlffordd, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Prendergast, sydd 80 milltir (128.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.3 milltir (335.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Prendergast yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#princes gate">
            <name>Princes Gate</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princes Gate">This is a redirect from a modification of the target's title; for example, its words are rearranged, or punctuation in the name is changed. In cases of modification from distinctly longer or shorter names, please use {{R from long name}} or {{R from short name}}, respectively. For more information follow the category link.
Use this rcat instead of {{R from other capitalisation}} and {{R from plural}} in namespaces other than mainspace for those types of modification.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princes Gate">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanbedr Felfre, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Princes Gate, sydd 68.8 milltir (110.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 197.1 milltir (317.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Princes Gate yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#priory">
            <name>Priory</name>
            <lat>51.813108</lat>
            <lon>-2.712988</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priory">A priory is a monastery of men or women under religious vows that is headed by a prior or prioress. Priories may be houses of mendicant friars or religious sisters (as the Dominicans, Augustinians, Franciscans, and Carmelites, for instance), or monasteries of monks or nuns (as the Benedictines). Houses of canons regular and canonesses regular also use this term, the alternative being "canonry".</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priory">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Priory, sydd 81.6 milltir (131.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 211.1 milltir (339.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Priory yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#puncheston">
            <name>Puncheston</name>
            <lat>51.930289</lat>
            <lon>-4.898428</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puncheston">Puncheston (Welsh: Cas-mael) is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, southwest Wales.
It sits below the mountain known as Castlebythe (English: Cow Castle).</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#pwllcrochan">
            <name>Pwllcrochan</name>
            <lat>51.684191</lat>
            <lon>-5.008984</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pwllcrochan">Pentref yng nghymuned Angle, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pwllcrochan, sydd 79.9 milltir (128.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.8 milltir (337.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pwllcrochan yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ramsey island">
            <name>Ramsey Island</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramsey Island">Ramsey Island (Welsh: Ynys Dewi) is an island about 1 km off the coast of the St David's peninsula in Pembrokeshire on the northern side of St Brides Bay, in southwest Wales. It is 640 acres (2.59 square km) in extent.
In Welsh the island is named after Saint David (Dewi Sant), the patron saint of Wales. It was the home of his confessor, Saint Justinian. The nearest town, strictly a city, is St David's.
Ramsey Island is less than 3.2 km (2 mi) long and its highest point is 136 metres (446 ft) above sea level at Carnllundain, and is listed as a HuMP. It is the fourth largest island in Wales, after Anglesey, Holy Island and Skomer.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#red hill">
            <name>Red Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red Hill">Red Hill may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red Hill">Mae Red Hill yn gopa mynydd a geir rhwng y Trallwng a'r Gelli Gandryll; cyfeiriad grid SO156500. Uchder cymharol, neu &#x201D;amlygrwydd&#x201D; y copa, ydy 434 metr: dyma'r uchder mae'r copa'n codi uwchlaw'r mynydd agosaf.
Dosberthir copaon Cymru, a gweddill gwledydd Prydain, yn rhestri arbennig yn &#xF4;l uchder ac yn &#xF4;l amlygrwydd y copa; mae'r copa hwn yn cael ei alw'n Dewey. Mae sawl cymdeithas yn mesur, gwiro a chasglu'r rhestri hyn a d&#xF4;nt yngh&#x177;d ar wefan &#x201C;Database of British and Irish hills&#x201D;. Uchder y copa o lefel y m&#xF4;r ydy 509 metr (1670 tr). Cafodd yr uchder ei fesur a'i gadarnhau ar 10 Mawrth 2007.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#redberth">
            <name>Redberth</name>
            <lat>51.703223</lat>
            <lon>-4.775454</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redberth">Pentref bychan gwledig yn Sir Benfro yw Redberth (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg). Mae'n gorwedd ar y briffordd A477 tua 2.5 milltir i'r dwyrain o bentref Caeriw, yn ne'r sir.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#reynalton">
            <name>Reynalton</name>
            <lat>51.745907</lat>
            <lon>-4.766015</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reynalton">Reynalton is a small village in Pembrokeshire, Wales, near to Tenby and Kilgetty, belonging to the Kilgetty/Begelly community.
Reynalton was one of six broadband "not-spots" in Wales &#x2013; communities without high-speed Internet access. In December 2008, the Welsh Assembly Government in conjunction with BT confirmed that coverage in these areas would soon be upgraded to bring them into line with the rest of the UK.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reynalton">Pentref bychan yn ne Sir Benfro yw Reynalton (ymddengys hi cheir enw Cymraeg am y pentref). Mae'n gorwedd rhwng Cilgeti a Dinbych-y-pysgod.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhos, the">
            <name>Rhos, The</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhoscrowther">
            <name>Rhoscrowther</name>
            <lat>51.679572</lat>
            <lon>-5.033101</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhoscrowther">Rhoscrowther (Welsh: Rhoscrowdder) is a village and former civil parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales, 5.6 miles (9.0 km) west of Pembroke, near the south shore of Milford Haven. It is part of the community of Hundleton.
The placename is Welsh and perhaps means "crwth-player's moor".
The church is a very early Christian site and was dedicated to Saint Decuman, whence the settlement's original name Llandegeman or Llandegman. It was the "bishop-house" of the cantref of Penfro and one of the seven principal churches in Dyfed under medieval Welsh law. The parish was taken during the Norman invasion of Wales and, as a part of Little England beyond Wales, has been essentially English-speaking for 900 years. The church is Grade I listed, and is in the care of Friends of Friendless Churches.
Much of the parish and almost all the medieval village except the church was cleared during the establishment of the BP oil terminal south-west of the village in 1961 and during the construction of the Texaco refinery immediately to the north three years later. A major explosion occurred at the refinery on 2 June 2011, killing four people.
Census populations of the parish: 219 (1801): 201 (1851): 113 (1901): 131 (1951): 176 (1981)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhosfach">
            <name>Rhosfach</name>
            <lat>51.925999</lat>
            <lon>-4.755724</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosfach">Pentref yng nghymuned Mynachlog-ddu, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Rhosfach, sydd 73.6 milltir (118.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 199.6 milltir (321.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rhosfach yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhosson">
            <name>Rhosson</name>
            <lat>51.879492</lat>
            <lon>-5.303139</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosson">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Rhosson, sydd 95.1 milltir (153.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 223 milltir (358.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rhosson yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhosycaerau">
            <name>Rhosycaerau</name>
            <lat>51.999132</lat>
            <lon>-5.031326</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhosygilwen">
            <name>Rhosygilwen</name>
            <lat>52.0355643</lat>
            <lon>-4.6227396</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhosygilwen">Gwesty yng nghymuned Cilgerran, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Rhosygilwen, sydd 72.8 milltir (117.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 195.6 milltir (314.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rhosygilwen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhyd-y-brown">
            <name>Rhyd-y-Brown</name>
            <lat>51.8684082</lat>
            <lon>-4.8036161</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhydowen">
            <name>Rhydowen</name>
            <lat>52.083697</lat>
            <lon>-4.272871</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhydowen">Rhydowen is a small village in Ceredigion in south-west Wales.
It has a population of about 347, of which around 200 are Welsh-speaking.
The village hall, established in 1917, has been recently demolished, despite local protest. The hall, declared derelict in 1973 after falling into disrepair due to lack of use, or indeed maintenance, had undergone several attempts at restoration; but any future efforts were deemed too costly.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhydowen">Gallai Rhydowen gyfeirio at:
Rhydowen, Ceredigion
Rhydowen, Sir Gaerfyrddin</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rhydygele">
            <name>Rhydygele</name>
            <lat>51.585862</lat>
            <lon>-3.304931</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ridgeway">
            <name>Ridgeway</name>
            <lat>51.6173426</lat>
            <lon>-4.0258019</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridgeway">A ridgeway (road) is a road or path that follows a ridge, or the highest part of the landscape.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#robeston back">
            <name>Robeston Back</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robeston Back">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanhuadain, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Robeston Back, sydd 72.9 milltir (117.4 km) o Gaerdydd a 201.1 milltir (323.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Robeston Back yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#robeston wathen">
            <name>Robeston Wathen</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robeston Wathen">Robeston Wathen is a rural village and parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales, 2 miles (3.2 km) west of Narberth, on the former Narberth to Haverfordwest turnpike, now the A40. Robeston Wathen is in the community of Llawhaden.
The village is mediaeval and limestone was quarried there. It was bypassed in 2011.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robeston Wathen">Pentref yng nghymuned Llanhuadain, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Robeston Wathen, sydd 72.4 milltir (116.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.5 milltir (322.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Robeston Wathen yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#robeston west">
            <name>Robeston West</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robeston West">Pentref yng nghymuned Castell Gwalchmai, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Robeston West, sydd 83.2 milltir (133.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 212.5 milltir (341.9 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Robeston West yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#roch">
            <name>Roch</name>
            <lat>51.848714</lat>
            <lon>-5.079682</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#roch gate">
            <name>Roch Gate</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rose valley">
            <name>Rose Valley</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rose Valley">Rose Valley may refer to:
Rose Valley, Bulgaria
Rose Valley, Chi&#x15F;in&#x103;u
Rose Valley, India
Rose Valley, New South Wales (Cooma-Monaro), Australia
Rose Valley, New South Wales (Kiama), Australia
Rose Valley (California), United States of America
Rose Valley, Pennsylvania, United States of America
Rose Valley, Saskatchewan, Canada
Rose Valley, British Columbia, Canada
Rose Valley, Cappadocia, Turkey</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rose Valley">Ardal yng nghymuned Penfro, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Rose Valley, sydd 74.9 milltir (120.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 204.9 milltir (329.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Rose Valley yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rosebush">
            <name>Rosebush</name>
            <lat>51.930501</lat>
            <lon>-4.800306</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosebush">Rosebush may refer to:
The rose plant
Rosebush, Pembrokeshire, Wales
Rosebush, Michigan, United States</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosebush">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Sir Benfro, de-orllewin Cymru, yw Rosebush (ni cheir ffurf Cymraeg ar yr enw). Mae'n gorwedd ar y B4313 i'r de o fryniau'r Preseli, tuag 1 filltir i'r gogledd-orllewin o bentref Maenclochog a 10 milltir i'r de-ddwyrain o Abergwaun.
Ceir hen dafarn yn o'r enw Tafern Sync, ar dir yr hen orsaf reilffordd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rosehill">
            <name>Rosehill</name>
            <lat>53.2726114</lat>
            <lon>-3.2162937</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosehill">Rosehill may refer to:
Rosehill, New South Wales, in Sydney
Rosehill, New Zealand, a suburb of Auckland
Rosehill, Cornwall
Rosehill, London
Rosehill (Gambrills, Maryland), historic home
Rosehill, one of the Darby Houses in Coalbrookdale, Shropshire

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rosemarket">
            <name>Rosemarket</name>
            <lat>51.739073</lat>
            <lon>-4.965194</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosemarket">Rosemarket is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#rudbaxton">
            <name>Rudbaxton</name>
            <lat>51.8469</lat>
            <lon>-4.961987</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudbaxton">Rudbaxton is a parish and a local government community in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales, and is 81 miles (130 km) from Cardiff and 208 miles (330 km) from London. The community includes the village of Crundale and the hamlets of Poyston Cross and Bethlehem.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudbaxton">Pentref, plwyf a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Rudbaxton. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo. Saif ychydig i'r gogledd o dref Hwlffordd ac i'r dwyrain o'r briffordd A40.
Cysegrwyd yr eglwys, sy'n dyddio or 11eg ganrif, i Sant Mihangel. Bu William Laud yn rheithor yma pan oedd yn Esgob Tyddewi.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Crundale a Poyston Cross. Ganed y cadfridog Thomas Picton yn Poyston Hall. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 1,062 yn 2001.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#sageston">
            <name>Sageston</name>
            <lat>51.695438</lat>
            <lon>-4.814019</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sageston">Pentref yng nghymuned Caeriw, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Sageston, sydd 71.9 milltir (115.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 201.5 milltir (324.3 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Sageston yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#sandy haven">
            <name>Sandy Haven</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy Haven">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanisan-yn-Rhos, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Sandy Haven, sydd 84.6 milltir (136.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 214.1 milltir (344.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Sandy Haven yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#sardis">
            <name>Sardis</name>
            <lat>51.740204</lat>
            <lon>-4.941147</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sardis">Sardis (/&#x2C8;s&#x251;rd&#x26A;s/) or Sardes (/&#x2C8;s&#x251;rdi&#x2D0;z/; Lydian: Sfard; Ancient Greek: &#x3A3;&#x3AC;&#x3C1;&#x3B4;&#x3B5;&#x3B9;&#x3C2; Sardeis; Old Persian: &#x103BF;&#x103B1;&#x103BC;&#x103AD; Sparda) was an ancient city at the location of modern Sart (Sartmahmut before 19 October 2005) in Turkey's Manisa Province. Sardis was the capital of the ancient kingdom of Lydia, one of the important cities of the Persian Empire, the seat of a proconsul under the Roman Empire, and the metropolis of the province Lydia in later Roman and Byzantine times. As one of the Seven churches of Asia, it was addressed by the author John of the Book of Revelation in the Holy Bible in terms which seem to imply that its population was notoriously soft and fainthearted. Its importance was due, first to its military strength, secondly to its situation on an important highway leading from the interior to the Aegean coast, and thirdly to its commanding the wide and fertile plain of the Hermus.
^ Rhodes, P.J. A History of the Classical Greek World 478-323 BC. 2nd edition. Chichester: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010, p. 6.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#saundersfoot">
            <name>Saundersfoot</name>
            <lat>51.709379</lat>
            <lon>-4.699726</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saundersfoot">Saundersfoot is a community in Pembrokeshire, west Wales near Tenby; two of the most visited Welsh holiday destinations. Saundersfoot lies in the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park and on the Pembrokeshire Coast Path.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saundersfoot">Pentref glan-m&#xF4;r ym mhlwyf Sant Isel, yn ne-ddwyrain Sir Benfro, yw Saundersfoot. Gyda'i gymydog Dinbych-y-Pysgod, 2 filltir i'r de, mae'n un o'r cyrchfeydd gwyliau mwyaf poblogaidd yng Nghymru. Mae'n enwog am ei draethau braf ar Fae Caerfyrddin.
Adeiladwyd yr harbwr yn 1829 ar gyfer allforio glo carreg (anthracite) o'r pyllau glo niferus yn yr ardal (e.e. yn ardal Stepaside), ond cyn hynny allforid glo o'r traeth ei hun am ganrifoedd. Tyfodd y pentref o gwmpas yr harbwr. Mae cwrs hen dramffordd o bwll Cwrt Bonville yn croesi'r pentref tra fod y yr hen dramffordd o bentref Amroth yn ffurfio'r promenad heddiw. Daeth y diwydiant glo i ben ar ddechrau'r 20fed ganrif.
Manteisiodd y pentref ar y rheilffordd ger llaw i ddenu ymwelwyr o ardaloedd glofaol a dinesig De Cymru a gorllewin Lloegr a thyfodd i fod yn bentref glan-m&#xF4;r poblogaidd. Gorwedd ym Mharc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Penfro ac mae Llwybr Arfordir Penfro yn rhedeg trwyddo.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#scleddau">
            <name>Scleddau</name>
            <lat>51.9676199</lat>
            <lon>-4.993685</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scleddau">Scleddau is a village and a community in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales, and is 2 miles (3.2 km) south of Fishguard on the A40. In 2011 the population of Scleddau was 1,013 with 34.2% able to speak Welsh.
The River Cleddau which lends its name to the village flows under the main road. Castell Hendre-Wen and the Round Barrow on Jordanson Hill are both Scheduled prehistoric Monuments dating back to the early Iron Age. 1 mile (1.6 km) south-east of Scleddau, and within the community, is the Grade II Listed Church of St Justinian, in the village of Trecwn.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scleddau">Pentref a chymuned yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Scleddau Saif i'r de o dref Abergwaun ger y briffordd A40.
Heblaw Scleddau ei hun, mae'r gymuned yn cynnwys pentrefi Trefwrdan (Jordanston yn Saesneg) a Manorowen. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 586.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#shipping">
            <name>Shipping</name>
            <lat>51.739552</lat>
            <lon>-4.728858</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shipping">Pentref yng nghymuned Cilgeti a Begeli, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Shipping, sydd 69 milltir (111 km) o Gaerdydd a 198 milltir (318.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Shipping yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#simpson">
            <name>Simpson</name>
            <lat>51.5326556</lat>
            <lon>-3.6902553</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpson">Simpson may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpson">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Nolton a'r Garn, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Simpson, sydd 84.8 milltir (136.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 213.1 milltir (342.9 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Simpson yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#simpson cross">
            <name>Simpson Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#skerryford">
            <name>Skerryford</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#skokholm island">
            <name>Skokholm Island</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#skomer island">
            <name>Skomer Island</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#skyfog">
            <name>Skyfog</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skyfog">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Skyfog, sydd 91 milltir (146.5 km) o Gaerdydd a 218.4 milltir (351.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Skyfog yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#slade">
            <name>Slade</name>
            <lat>51.552838</lat>
            <lon>-4.183329</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slade">Slade are an English rock band from Wolverhampton/Walsall. They rose to prominence during the glam rock era of the early 1970s with 17 consecutive top 20 hits and six number ones. The British Hit Singles &amp; Albums names them as the most successful British group of the 1970s based on sales of singles. They were the first act to achieve three singles enter at number one; all six of the band's chart-toppers were penned by Noddy Holder and Jim Lea. Total UK sales stand at 6,520,171, and their best selling single, "Merry Xmas Everybody", has sold in excess of one million copies.
Following an unsuccessful move to the United States in 1975, Slade's popularity waned but was unexpectedly revived in 1980 when they were last minute replacements for Ozzy Osbourne at the Reading Rock Festival. The band later acknowledged this to have been one of the highlights of their career. The original line up split in 1992 but the band reformed the following year as Slade II. The band has continued, with a number of line-up changes, to the present day. They have now shortened the group name back to Slade.
A number of diverse artists have cited Slade as an influence, including alternative rock icons Nirvana and the Smashing Pumpkins, punk pioneers the Ramones, Sex Pistols, the Undertones, the Runaways and the Clash, glam metal bands Kiss, M&#xF6;tley Cr&#xFC;e, Twisted Sister, Quiet Riot, Poison and Def Leppard and pop-rock stalwarts the Replacements, Cheap Trick and Oasis.
The Illustrated Encyclopaedia of Music tells of Holder's powerful vocals, guitarist Dave Hill's equally arresting dress sense and the deliberate misspelling of their song titles for which they became well known.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#slebech">
            <name>Slebech</name>
            <lat>51.801475</lat>
            <lon>-4.870597</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slebech">Slebech was a community (prior to 1974, a parish) in Pembrokeshire, West Wales which is now part of the combined community of Uzmaston and Boulston and Slebech. Uzmaston and Boulston and Slebech is a sparsely populated community on the northern shore of the Eastern River Cleddau which shares common land boundaries with the Communities of Wiston and Llawhaden and mainly consists of farmland and woodland. Much of the community is within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park and Picton Castle's stable block loft is an important breeding roost for the rare Greater Horseshoe Bat.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#solva">
            <name>Solva</name>
            <lat>51.8739786</lat>
            <lon>-5.1953135</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solva">Solva (Welsh: Solfach) is a village and community in Pembrokeshire, Wales, UK.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#south hill">
            <name>South Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South Hill">South Hill may refer to:
South Hill, Cornwall
South Hill, New York
South Hill, Toronto
South Hill, Virginia
South Hill, Washington
South Hill, Anguilla
The South Hill neighborhood of Minot, North Dakota
The South Hill area of Spokane, Washington</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/South Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Yr Hafanau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw South Hill, sydd 86.2 milltir (138.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 215.4 milltir (346.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir South Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#spittal">
            <name>Spittal</name>
            <lat>51.869998</lat>
            <lon>-4.940691</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spittal">This is a redirect from an ambiguous page name to a disambiguation page. These redirects are pointed to by links that should always be disambiguated. Therefore, this template should never appear on a page that has "(disambiguation)" in its title. Use {{R to disambiguation page}} instead. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spittal">Penref, plwyf a chymuned yn Sir Benfro yw Spittal. Saif tua hanner y ffordd rhwng Hwlffordd ac Abergwaun.
Cafodd y pentref ei enw o'r hospitium, neu fan i bererinion gael llety, oedd yn eiddo i Eglwys Gadeiriol Tyddewi. Ceir y cyfeiriad cynharaf ato yn 1259. Ail-adeiladwyd Eglwys y Santes Fair yma yn y 19eg ganrif; o'i mewn ceir maen ag arysgrif arni o'r 5ed neu'r 6ed ganrif. Adeiladwyd ysgol gynradd newydd yma yn 2004; ceir hefyd swyddfa'r post, neuadd a thafarn.
Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 501.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#square and compass">
            <name>Square and Compass</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st brides">
            <name>St Brides</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Brides">St Brides (Welsh: Sain Ffraid) is a small coastal village in Pembrokeshire, West Wales. It lies at the south of St Brides Bay, about one and a half miles north of the larger village of Marloes with which it forms the Marloes and St. Brides community council.
The village lies within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park and is on the route of the Pembrokeshire Coast Path.
Buildings include a small Norman parish church and St Bride's Castle, a 19th-century baronial-style country house which later became a sanatorium called Kensington Hospital and has now been converted into holiday accommodation. The castle underwent extensive renovation by current owners the Holiday Property Bond. The latter is a grade II* listed building 
Scouting in Pembrokeshire have a campsite in the village; it is used by Scouting and Girl Guiding groups both locally and nationally.
^ "St Brides Castle, Marloes and St Brides". British Listed Buildings. Retrieved 31 December 2013.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st davids">
            <name>St Davids</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Davids">St Davids or St David's (Welsh: Tyddewi, [t&#x268;&#x2D0; &#x2C8;&#xF0;&#x25B;wi], lit. "David's house") is a city and community (full name St David's and the Cathedral Close) in Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the United Kingdom. Lying on the River Alun on St Davids Peninsula, it is Britain's smallest city in terms of both size and population, the final resting place of Saint David, Wales's patron saint, and the de facto ecclesiastical capital of Wales. St Davids was given city status in the 16th century due to the presence of St David's Cathedral but lost this in 1888. City status was restored in 1994 at the request of Queen Elizabeth II.
^ Office for National Statistics 2011 census &#x2013; St. David's and the Cathedral Close C
^ Parish Headcounts for Pembrokeshire (based on 2001 Census) at Office for National Statistics. Retrieved 2011-08-01
^ As specified in New Oxford Dictionary for Writers and Editors OUP 2005. The name is often spelt without its possessive apostrophe, including by the St Davids City Council</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st florence">
            <name>St Florence</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Florence">St Florence is a village, parish and community situated 4 miles (6 km) to the west of the seaside town of Tenby in Pembrokeshire, Wales. It had a population of 751 in 2001, increasing slightly to 756 at the 2011 Census. The present name of the village is taken from the saint to whom the church is dedicated.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st nicholas">
            <name>St Nicholas</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st petrox">
            <name>St Petrox</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#st twynnells">
            <name>St Twynnells</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/St Twynnells">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Castellmartin a Stackpole, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw St Twynnells, sydd 77.6 milltir (124.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 207.9 milltir (334.5 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir St Twynnells yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#stackpole">
            <name>Stackpole</name>
            <lat>51.629875</lat>
            <lon>-4.914125</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stackpole">This is a redirect from a subtopic of the target article. For more information follow the category link.
This is a redirect from a topic that does not have its own page to a section of a page on the subject. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#stackpole elidor (cheriton)">
            <name>Stackpole Elidor (Cheriton)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#stackpole head">
            <name>Stackpole Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#star">
            <name>Star</name>
            <lat>53.2265159</lat>
            <lon>-4.2281739</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star">A star is a luminous sphere of plasma held together by its own gravity. The nearest star to Earth is the Sun. Other stars, mostly in the Milky Way, are visible from Earth during the night, appearing as a multitude of fixed luminous points in the sky due to their immense distance from Earth. Historically, the most prominent stars were grouped into constellations and asterisms, and the brightest stars gained proper names. Extensive catalogues of stars have been assembled by astronomers, which provide standardized star designations.
For at least a portion of its life, a star shines due to thermonuclear fusion of hydrogen into helium in its core, releasing energy that traverses the star's interior and then radiates into outer space. Once the hydrogen in the core of a star is nearly exhausted, almost all naturally occurring elements heavier than helium are created by stellar nucleosynthesis during the star's lifetime and, for some stars, by supernova nucleosynthesis when it explodes. Near the end of its life, a star can also contain degenerate matter. Astronomers can determine the mass, age, metallicity (chemical composition), and many other properties of a star by observing its motion through space, luminosity, and spectrum respectively. The total mass of a star is the principal determinant of its evolution and eventual fate. Other characteristics of a star, including diameter and temperature, change over its life, while the star's environment affects its rotation and movement. A plot of the temperature of many stars against their luminosities, known as a Hertzsprung&#x2013;Russell diagram (H&#x2013;R diagram), allows the age and evolutionary state of a star to be determined.
A star's life begins with the gravitational collapse of a gaseous nebula of material composed primarily of hydrogen, along with helium and trace amounts of heavier elements. Once the stellar core is sufficiently dense, hydrogen becomes steadily converted into helium through nuclear fusion, releasing energy in the process. The remainder of the star's interior carries energy away from the core through a combination of radiative and convective processes. The star's internal pressure prevents it from collapsing further under its own gravity. Once the hydrogen fuel at the core is exhausted, a star with at least 0.4 times the mass of the Sun expands to become a red giant, in some cases fusing heavier elements at the core or in shells around the core. The star then evolves into a degenerate form, recycling a portion of its matter into the interstellar environment, where it will contribute to the formation of a new generation of stars with a higher proportion of heavy elements. Meanwhile, the core becomes a stellar remnant: a white dwarf, a neutron star, or (if it is sufficiently massive) a black hole.
Binary and multi-star systems consist of two or more stars that are gravitationally bound, and generally move around each other in stable orbits. When two such stars have a relatively close orbit, their gravitational interaction can have a significant impact on their evolution. Stars can form part of a much larger gravitationally bound structure, such as a star cluster or a galaxy.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star">Gallai Star gyfeirio at un o sawl peth:
Pentrefi:
Star, Sir Benfro, Cymru
Star, Ynys M&#xF4;n, Cymru
Star, Gwlad yr Haf, Lloegr
Gweler hefyd:
Seren
Star Trek
Star Wars</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#stepaside">
            <name>Stepaside</name>
            <lat>51.737097</lat>
            <lon>-4.697814</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stepaside">Stepaside or Step Aside may refer to:
Placenames
Stepaside, Cornwall, a hamlet in the UK
Stepaside, Dublin, a suburb in Ireland
Stepaside, Pembrokeshire, a hamlet in Wales
Stepaside, Powys, a hamlet in Wales
Other
"Step Aside", a song by Sleater-Kinney from their 2002 album One Beat
"Step Aside", a song by Efterklang from their 2004 album Tripper</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stepaside">Pentref bychan yn ne-ddwyrain Sir Benfro yw Stepaside. Fe'i lleolir tua 2 filltir i'r gogledd o Saundersfoot, 4 milltir i'r gogledd o Ddinbych-y-Pysgod. Mae ei enw Saesneg yn adlewyrchu'r ffaith ei fod i'r de o'r Landsker.
Ar un adeg bu'r pentref yn gartref i byllau glo a haearn, ond erbyn heddiw mae wedi troi'n bentref tawel sy'n dibynnu ar dwristiaeth. Ceir un dafarn yno. Lleolir Parc Etifeddiaeth Stepaside ar y ffordd o'r pentref i Wisemans Bridge.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#steynton">
            <name>Steynton</name>
            <lat>51.729759</lat>
            <lon>-5.017754</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steynton">Steynton or Stainton is a parish in the county of Pembrokeshire, Wales, formerly in the hundred of Rh&#xF4;s and now an area of Milford Haven. It houses c.3,000 inhabitants. The parish includes the hamlet of Dreenhill, near Haverfordwest.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steynton">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Steynton, sydd 80.9 milltir (130.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.3 milltir (338.4 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Steynton yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#stop-and-call">
            <name>Stop-and-Call</name>
            <lat>52.0044816</lat>
            <lon>-5.0041771</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop-and-Call">This is a redirect from a topic that does not have its own page to a section of a page on the subject. For more information follow the category link.
This is a redirect to a subtopic of the redirect's title. For more information follow the category link.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#strumble head">
            <name>Strumble Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strumble Head">Strumble Head (Welsh: Pen Strwmbl) is a rocky headland in the community of Pencaer in north Pembrokeshire, Wales. It lies within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park the coastline making part of the Pembrokeshire Coast Path, a long-distance trail of 186 miles. Views extend eastwards towards Dinas Head and Cardigan Bay, and westwards to the Irish Sea.
Three islands are off the head: Ynys Meicel (34 metres, 112 feet) and Ynys and Carreg Onnen.
It gives its name to Strumble Head Lighthouse (on the island of Ynys Meicel) and Strumble VOR, a way point in many trans-atlantic flights.
It comprises part of the Strumble Head - Llechdafad Cliffs Site of Special Scientific Interest.
Strumble Head is one of the best sites in Britain to view cetaceans, particularly the porpoise which can be spotted in the tidal races around the headland with modest binoculars. Public cetacean watches are frequently organized by Sea Trust. Seals can often be spotted in the waters beneath the light house. A wartime lookout post was converted for use by the public as a shelter from the wind for wildlife fans and was opened by Bill Oddie.
The headland has been the site of numerous ship wrecks. A French shipwreck, possibly from the last invasion of Britain, was found nearby in 2003. The Bardse of the Pile of Fowdrey was wrecked off Strumble Head on 3 October 1763 laden with a cargo of iron and copper from Wicklow bound for Chepstow under its Master, John Kennel. Another notable wreck was the barque Calburga in 1915, one of Canada's last square rigged sailing ships.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#summerhill">
            <name>Summerhill</name>
            <lat>53.07817</lat>
            <lon>-3.033461</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summerhill">Summerhill or Summer Hill may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summerhill">Gallai Summerhill neu Summer Hill gyfeirio at:
Yr Alban
Summerhill, Aberdeen
Summerhill, Dumfries (maesdref)
Cymru
Brynhyfryd, Wrecsam (Saesneg: Summerhill)
Iwerddon
Summerhill, Swydd Fermanagh, Gogledd Iwerddon
Summerhill, Dulyn, ardal yn ninas Dulyn
Summerhill, Swydd Meath</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#sutton">
            <name>Sutton</name>
            <lat>51.802561</lat>
            <lon>-5.033537</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sutton">Sutton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tafarn-y-bwlch">
            <name>Tafarn-y-bwlch</name>
            <lat>51.9680984</lat>
            <lon>-4.7904451</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#talbenny">
            <name>Talbenny</name>
            <lat>51.764168</lat>
            <lon>-5.134103</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tangiers">
            <name>Tangiers</name>
            <lat>51.8276139</lat>
            <lon>-4.969471</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tegryn">
            <name>Tegryn</name>
            <lat>51.968591</lat>
            <lon>-4.580878</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tegryn">Tegryn is a hilltop linear village in north Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the community and parish of Clydau and is the largest settlement in the community.
It is at the eastern end of the Preseli Mountains, 1 mile (1.6 km) north of Llanfyrnach.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tegryn">Pentref bychan yng ngogledd Sir Benfro yw Tegryn. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Clydau.
Gorwedd y pentref ar groesffordd wledig tua naw milltir i'r de o Aberteifi. Mae lonydd yn ei gysylltu a phentrefi eraill yn y cylch, sef Hermon i'r de-ddwyrain, Star a Chlydau i'r gogledd a Llanfyrnach i'r de. Ychydig i'r gogledd mae copa'r Frenni Fach.
Yn ymyl Tegryn ceir Capel Llwyn-yr-hwrdd, capel Cymraeg sydd a lle pwysig yn hanes yr Annibynwyr.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#templeton">
            <name>Templeton</name>
            <lat>51.772794</lat>
            <lon>-4.736548</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Templeton">Templeton is a Scottish surname, and may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tenby (dinbych-y-pysgod)">
            <name>Tenby (Dinbych-y-pysgod)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#thomas chapel">
            <name>Thomas Chapel</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas Chapel">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cilgeti a Begeli, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Thomas Chapel, sydd 69.7 milltir (112.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 198.6 milltir (319.7 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Thomas Chapel yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#thornton">
            <name>Thornton</name>
            <lat>51.7309542</lat>
            <lon>-5.0386904</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thornton">Thornton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thornton">Gallai Thornton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tiers cross">
            <name>Tiers Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiers Cross">Tiers Cross is a community and an electoral ward containing the community in Pembrokeshire, West Wales. In addition to the main village it also comprises the areas of Thornton and Dreenhill.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiers Cross">Pentref a chymuned yn ne Sir Benfro yw Tiers Cross. Ymddengys nad oes enw Cymraeg arno. Saif ar ffordd gefn rhwng Hwlffordd ac Aberdaugleddau, ychydig i'r gorllewin o'r briffordd A4076. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 471 yn 2001.
Mae'r gymuned hefyd yn cynnwys pentrefi Dreenhill a Thornton. Saif yn y rhan y mae Gwyddoniadur Cymru yn ei ddisgrifio fel y "rhan leiaf diddorol o Sir Benfro". Bu David Lloyd George yn byw yn ffermdy Bulford am ychydig dros flwyddyn pan oedd yn ieuanc.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tower point">
            <name>Tower Point</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#townsend">
            <name>Townsend</name>
            <lat>50.9999078</lat>
            <lon>-2.5854304</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Townsend">Townsend or Townshend may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Townsend">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Dale, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Townsend, sydd 87 milltir (140 km) o Gaerdydd a 216.7 milltir (348.7 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Townsend yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#trecwn">
            <name>Trecwn</name>
            <lat>51.954969</lat>
            <lon>-4.960174</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trecwn">Trecwn is a village in Pembrokeshire, west Wales, 1.6 miles (2.6 km) east of the A40 (Fishguard to Haverfordwest) road in the community of Scleddau.
^ "Welsh Statutory Instruments 2011 No. 683 (W.101) Local Government, Wales The Pembrokeshire (Communities) Order 2011" (PDF). UK Stationery Office. Retrieved 1 January 2014.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#trefasser">
            <name>Trefasser</name>
            <lat>51.999657</lat>
            <lon>-5.066802</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefasser">Trefasser (variations: Tref-Asser, or Tr&#xEA;f Asser, or Asserton; translation: "town" of "Asser") is a hamlet, located to the west of Fishguard and south of Pwll Deri in western Wales. Historically, it is part of the parish of Llanwnda. It lies on the coast of St George's Channel within the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park. A stream named Cledde Goch runs close by.
Trefasser's farms, houses and cottages are the only settled area of Pen Caer. David Tress has painted the place in an abstract painting. The old post office of Trefasser now serves as a bakery and prepared-meal kitchen serving holidaymakers. Some of the farms in the area supplement their income by opening up paintballing and karting facilities to tourists.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#treffgarne">
            <name>Treffgarne</name>
            <lat>51.874428</lat>
            <lon>-4.969698</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treffgarne">Treffgarne is a small village in Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#treffynnon">
            <name>Treffynnon</name>
            <lat>53.276009</lat>
            <lon>-3.225103</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treffynnon">Mae Treffynnon (Saesneg: Holywell) yn dref yn Sir y Fflint. Saif yn agos i lan orllewinol Glannau Dyfrdwy ar yr A5026, tua hanner ffordd rhwng Prestatyn i'r gogledd a'r Wyddgrug i'r de, tua 5 milltir o dref Y Fflint. Mae'r hen dref yn gorwedd ar un o lethrau is Mynydd Helygain. Mae'r dref yn enwog fel lleoliad Ffynnon Gwenffrewi a'i chapel, sy'n ganolfan pererindod i Gatholigion ac eraill ers canrifoedd lawer.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#trefgarn owen">
            <name>Trefgarn Owen</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#trefin">
            <name>Trefin</name>
            <lat>51.94923</lat>
            <lon>-5.144323</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefin">Trefin is a village in the Welsh-speaking area of Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales. It is sometimes given the anglicised spelling Trevine, particularly on older maps, although the official name is now Trefin in both English and Welsh. Trefin has derived its name from the Welsh name 'Trefaen' which translated to English means 'village on the rock outcrop'. The rock outcrop can be seen in many places around Trefin, especially its centre.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefin">Erthygl ar y pentref yn Sir Benfro yw hon. Am y bardd "Trefin", gweler Edgar Phillips.

Pentref ar arfordir gogleddol Sir Benfro yw Trefin. Saif ychydig i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A487, tua hanner y ffordd rhwng Tyddewi ac Abergwaun, ym Mharc Cenedlaethol Arfordir Penfro, ac mae Llwybr Arfordir Sir Benfro gerllaw.
Enwogwyd y pentref gan gerdd adnabyddus Crwys, Melin Trefin, am yr hen felin, sy' ddim yn malu'r gwenith eto, ond sydd yn cael ei "malu" erbyn hyn gan yr amser a'r hin. Mae geiriau'r gerdd yn ffitio'r tiwn i "Dyma Gariad". Defnyddiai yr Archdderwydd Edgar Phillips "Trefin" fel enw barddol.
Yn Nhrefin y bu ymgyrch gyntaf Cymdeithas yr Iaith yn 1964 yn erbyn ffurfiau Seisnigedig o enwau lleoedd; "Trevine" oedd ar yr arwyddion ar y pryd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#treginnis">
            <name>Treginnis</name>
            <lat>51.8750553</lat>
            <lon>-5.2908341</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treginnis">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Treginnis, sydd 95.1 milltir (153.1 km) o Gaerdydd a 223.2 milltir (359.1 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Treginnis yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#treglemais">
            <name>Treglemais</name>
            <lat>51.917906</lat>
            <lon>-5.17497</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treglemais">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Llanrhian, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Treglemais, sydd 90.7 milltir (145.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 217.8 milltir (350.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Treglemais yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tregyddulan">
            <name>Tregyddulan</name>
            <lat>52.2199979</lat>
            <lon>-3.934385</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#treleddyd-fawr">
            <name>Treleddyd-fawr</name>
            <lat>51.903492</lat>
            <lon>-5.267722</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tretio">
            <name>Tretio</name>
            <lat>51.914656</lat>
            <lon>-5.221561</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tretio">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Tretio, sydd 92.6 milltir (149 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.8 milltir (353.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Tretio yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#triffleton">
            <name>Triffleton</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#tufton">
            <name>Tufton</name>
            <lat>51.9173509</lat>
            <lon>-4.851417</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tufton">Tufton may refer to:
Places:
Tufton, Hampshire, a village in the English county of Hampshire
Tufton, Pembrokeshire, a place in the Welsh county of Pembrokeshire
People:
Any of several Earls of Thanet in the United Kingdom, including:

Nicholas Tufton, 1st Earl of Thanet (1578&#x2013;1631)
John Tufton, 2nd Earl of Thanet (1608&#x2013;1664)
Nicholas Tufton, 3rd Earl of Thanet (1631&#x2013;1679)
John Tufton, 4th Earl of Thanet (1638&#x2013;1680)
Richard Tufton, 5th Earl of Thanet (1640&#x2013;1684)
Thomas Tufton, 6th Earl of Thanet (1644&#x2013;1729)
Sackville Tufton, 7th Earl of Thanet (1688&#x2013;1753)
Sackville Tufton, 8th Earl of Thanet (1733&#x2013;1786)
Sackville Tufton, 9th Earl of Thanet (1767&#x2013;1825)
Charles Tufton, 10th Earl of Thanet (1770&#x2013;1832)
Henry Tufton, 11th Earl of Thanet (1775&#x2013;1849)

Satire
Sir Bufton Tufton is one of the Recurring in-jokes in Private Eye</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tufton">Pentref yng nghymuned Cas-mael, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Tufton, sydd 77.8 milltir (125.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 204.1 milltir (328.5 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Tufton yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#underwood">
            <name>Underwood</name>
            <lat>51.5961865</lat>
            <lon>-2.8890049</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Underwood">Underwood is a surname of English topographic origin.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#upper nash">
            <name>Upper Nash</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper Nash">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cosheston, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Upper Nash, sydd 73.9 milltir (118.9 km) o Gaerdydd a 203.6 milltir (327.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Upper Nash yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#upper solva">
            <name>Upper Solva</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#uzmaston">
            <name>Uzmaston</name>
            <lat>51.791333</lat>
            <lon>-4.944397</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzmaston">Uzmaston is a small parish in Pembrokeshire, Wales, about 2 kilometres south-east of Haverfordwest.
The village forms part of the community of Uzmaston, Boulston and Slebech.
Its parish church is dedicated to the 6th-century Breton prince and Welsh saint Isfael.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzmaston">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Uzmaston (ni cheir enw Cymraeg). Fe'i lleolir rhai milltiroedd i'r de-ddwyrain o Hwlffordd ar lan Afon Cleddau Wen. Gyda Boulston, mae'n rhan o gymuned Uzmaston a Boulston.
Credir mai tarddiad yr enw yw Osmund a oedd yn enw personol Eingl-Sgandinafaidd.  Y ffurf wreiddiol oedd Villa Osmundi sy'n mynd yn &#xF4;l i 1176-98. Y ffurf Gymraeg ar yr enw hwn yw Osmwnd neu Osmwnt h.y. Tref Osmwnt.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#vachelich">
            <name>Vachelich</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vachelich">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Vachelich, sydd 92.2 milltir (148.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 219.9 milltir (353.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Vachelich yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#valley, the">
            <name>Valley, The</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#walton east">
            <name>Walton East</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walton East">not to be confused with East Walton.

Walton East (Welsh: Waltwn) is a parish in the hundred of Dungleddy situated in Pembrokeshire, south-west Wales. Walton East is 2 miles (3.2 km) south-west of Llys y Fran and 1 1&#x2044;2 miles (2.4 km) north of Clarbeston Road.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walton East">Pentref yng nghymuned Cas-wis, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Walton East, sydd 77.8 milltir (125.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 205 milltir (329.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Walton East yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#walton west">
            <name>Walton West</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walton West">Pentref yng nghymuned Yr Hafanau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Walton West, sydd 84.9 milltir (136.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 213.9 milltir (344.2 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Walton West yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#warren">
            <name>Warren</name>
            <lat>51.6385919</lat>
            <lon>-4.9898292</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warren">Warren may refer to:
Warren (noun), a given name and a surname, including lists of persons so named
Warren (noun), a densely populated or labyrinthine building or district
Warren (name), a given name and a surname, including lists of persons so named</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warren">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Castellmartin a Stackpole, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Warren, sydd 78.7 milltir (126.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 208.9 milltir (336.2 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Warren yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#waterloo">
            <name>Waterloo</name>
            <lat>51.6940219</lat>
            <lon>-4.929837</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterloo">Waterloo may refer to:
Battle of Waterloo, a battle fought in 1815 near Waterloo, Belgium, in which Napoleon met his final defeat
Waterloo in popular culture, the notion of ultimate or final defeat</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterloo">Gallai Waterloo gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#waterston">
            <name>Waterston</name>
            <lat>51.712564</lat>
            <lon>-4.986853</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterston">Waterston is a village near Milford Haven in Pembrokeshire, Wales, in the community of Llanstadwell.
Part of the village lies between the boundaries of the Dragon LNG terminal. The plant is expected to process between ten and twenty percent of the UK's gas supply requirement.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterston">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Waterston (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg am y pentref). Fe'i lleolir yn ne'r sir ger Aberdaugleddau. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Llanstadwel.
Codwyd purfa olew ar gwr y pentref ond mae wedi cau erbyn hyn.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#waun beddau">
            <name>Waun Beddau</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waun Beddau">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Tyddewi a Chlos y Gadeirlan, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Waun Beddau, sydd 93.1 milltir (149.8 km) o Gaerdydd a 220.2 milltir (354.4 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Waun Beddau yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wdig (goodwick)">
            <name>Wdig (Goodwick)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#welsh hook">
            <name>Welsh Hook</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh Hook">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Cas-blaidd, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Welsh Hook, sydd 83.7 milltir (134.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.5 milltir (338.8 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Welsh Hook yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#west denant">
            <name>West Denant</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#west williamston">
            <name>West Williamston</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#western cleddau">
            <name>Western Cleddau</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#weston">
            <name>Weston</name>
            <lat>52.353118</lat>
            <lon>-2.983587</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weston">Weston may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#whitchurch">
            <name>Whitchurch</name>
            <lat>51.8846529</lat>
            <lon>-5.2004816</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitchurch">Whitchurch can refer to:
Towns in the United Kingdom:
Whitchurch, Shropshire
Whitchurch, Hampshire
Villages in the United Kingdom:
Whitchurch, Bristol
Whitchurch, Buckinghamshire
Whitchurch, Cardiff
Whitchurch, Devon
Whitchurch Canonicorum, Dorset
Whitchurch, Herefordshire
Whitchurch, an alternative name for Little Stanmore in the historic county of Middlesex.
Whitchurch-on-Thames, Oxfordshire
Whitchurch, Pembrokeshire, near St. David's
Whitchurch-by-Cardigan, Pembrokeshire
Whitchurch, Somerset
Whitchurch, Warwickshire
In Canada:
Whitchurch, Ontario, since 1971 part of Whitchurch&#x2013;Stouffville, Ontario</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitchurch">Gallai Whitchurch gyfeirio at:
Yr Eglwys Newydd, un o faesdrefi Caerdydd
Tregroes, pentref yn Sir Benfro
Yr Eglwys Wen, tref yn Swydd Amwythig, Lloegr, heb fod ymhell o'r ff&#xEE;n a Chymru
Yr Eglwys Wen, tref yn Hampshire, Lloegr</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wind hill">
            <name>Wind Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wind Hill">Wind Hill, situated close to Lynmouth in Devon, England, is the location of an Iron Age enclosure or "spur" hill fort. The site is effectively a hillside forming a spur or promontory between the steep valley of the East Lyn River to the south and the cliffs to the north. Wind Hill's summit is at 261 metres (856 ft) above sea level, though the enormous earthworks defending the spur are at a lower level to the east.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wind Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Maenorb&#x177;r, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Wind Hill, sydd 70 milltir (112.7 km) o Gaerdydd a 200.1 milltir (322 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Wind Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wiston">
            <name>Wiston</name>
            <lat>51.825918</lat>
            <lon>-4.872326</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiston">Wiston may refer to:
Wiston, Pembrokeshire, Wales
Wiston Castle

Wiston, South Lanarkshire, Scotland
Wiston, West Sussex, England
Wiston House</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#withybush">
            <name>Withybush</name>
            <lat>51.824325</lat>
            <lon>-4.9598978</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wolfsdale">
            <name>Wolfsdale</name>
            <lat>51.854543</lat>
            <lon>-5.003992</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wolfsdale hill">
            <name>Wolfsdale Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfsdale Hill">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Camrose, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Wolfsdale Hill, sydd 82.2 milltir (132.3 km) o Gaerdydd a 209.8 milltir (337.6 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Wolfsdale Hill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wood">
            <name>Wood</name>
            <lat>41.6051669</lat>
            <lon>-83.5150227</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wood">Wood is a porous and fibrous structural tissue found in the stems and roots of trees and other woody plants.
It has been used for thousands of years for both fuel and as a construction material. It is an organic material, a natural composite of cellulose fibers (which are strong in tension) embedded in a matrix of lignin which resists compression. Wood is sometimes defined as only the secondary xylem in the stems of trees, or it is defined more broadly to include the same type of tissue elsewhere such as in the roots of trees or shrubs. In a living tree it performs a support function, enabling woody plants to grow large or to stand up by themselves. It also conveys water and nutrients between the leaves, other growing tissues, and the roots. Wood may also refer to other plant materials with comparable properties, and to material engineered from wood, or wood chips or fiber.
The Earth contains about one trillion tonnes of wood, which grows at a rate of 10 billion tonnes per year. As an abundant, carbon-neutral renewable resource, woody materials have been of intense interest as a source of renewable energy. In 1991, approximately 3.5 cubic kilometers of wood were harvested. Dominant uses were for furniture and building construction.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wood">Pentrefan yng nghymuned Nolton a'r Garn, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Wood, sydd 87.1 milltir (140.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 215 milltir (346 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Wood yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#wooden">
            <name>Wooden</name>
            <lat>51.6587667</lat>
            <lon>-3.4991098</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wooden">Pentref yng nghymuned Dwyrain Trewiliam, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Wooden, sydd 68.7 milltir (110.6 km) o Gaerdydd a 198 milltir (318.6 km) o Lundain.
Cynrychiolir Wooden yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Angela Burns (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Simon Hart (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#woodsend">
            <name>Woodsend</name>
            <lat>51.6520003</lat>
            <lon>-4.9247073</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodsend">Woodsend is a hamlet in the civil parish of Aldbourne in Wiltshire, England. Its nearest town is Marlborough, which is approximately 4.5 miles (7.2 km) south-west from the hamlet.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#woodstock">
            <name>Woodstock</name>
            <lat>51.897435</lat>
            <lon>-4.865099</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodstock">The Woodstock Music &amp; Art Fair&#x2014;informally, the Woodstock Festival or simply Woodstock&#x2014;was a music festival, billed as "An Aquarian Exposition: 3 Days of Peace &amp; Music". It was held at Max Yasgur's 600-acre (240 ha; 0.94 sq mi) dairy farm in the Catskills near the hamlet of White Lake in the town of Bethel, New York, from August 15 to 18, 1969. Bethel, in Sullivan County, is 43 miles (69 km) southwest of the town of Woodstock, New York, in adjoining Ulster County.
During the sometimes rainy weekend, 32 acts performed outdoors before an audience of 400,000 young people. It is widely regarded as a pivotal moment in popular music history. Rolling Stone listed it as one of the 50 Moments That Changed the History of Rock and Roll.
The festival is also widely considered to be the definitive nexus for the larger counterculture generation.
The event was captured in the 1970 documentary movie Woodstock, an accompanying soundtrack album, and Joni Mitchell's song "Woodstock", which commemorated the event and became a major hit for Crosby, Stills, Nash &amp; Young.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#yerbeston">
            <name>Yerbeston</name>
            <lat>51.7461119</lat>
            <lon>-4.8072039</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yerbeston">Pentref bychan yn Sir Benfro yw Yerbeston (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg). Fe'i lleolir i'r gogledd-orllewin o dref Dinbych-y-pysgod ac i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A477. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Jeffreyston.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="pembrokeshire#ynyns deullyn">
            <name>Ynyns Deullyn</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
    </towns>
</county>
