<?xml version="1.0"?>
<county id="Swansea">
    <postcodes>
        <postcode>SA1</postcode>
        <postcode>SA18</postcode>
        <postcode>SA2</postcode>
        <postcode>SA3</postcode>
        <postcode>SA4</postcode>
        <postcode>SA5</postcode>
        <postcode>SA6</postcode>
        <postcode>SA7</postcode>
    </postcodes>
    <towns>
        <town id="swansea#abertawe (swansea)">
            <name>Abertawe (Swansea)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#bach-y-gwreiddyn">
            <name>Bach-y-gwreiddyn</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#barland common">
            <name>Barland Common</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#berry">
            <name>Berry</name>
            <lat>51.3997529</lat>
            <lon>-3.2825859</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berry">The botanical definition of a berry is a fleshy fruit produced from a single flower and containing one ovary. Grapes and eggplants are two common examples. The berry is the most common type of fleshy fruit in which the entire ovary wall ripens into an edible pericarp. They may have one or more carpels. The seeds are usually embedded in the fleshy interior of the ovary, but there are some non-fleshy exceptions, such as peppers, that have air rather than pulp around their seeds.
A plant that bears berries is said to be bacciferous or baccate (a plant that resembles a berry, whether it actually is a berry or not, can also be called "baccate").
In everyday English, "berry" is a term for any small edible fruit. Berries are usually juicy, round, brightly coloured, sweet or sour, and do not have a stone or pit, although many seeds may be present.
Many berries, such as the tomato, are edible, but others in the same family, such as the fruits of the potato (Solanum tuberosum) and the deadly nightshade (Atropa belladonna) are poisonous to humans.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#birchgrove">
            <name>Birchgrove</name>
            <lat>51.667318</lat>
            <lon>-3.872463</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birchgrove">Birchgrove may refer to :</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birchgrove">Gall yr enw Seisnig Birchgrove gyfeirio at sawl lle:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#bishopston">
            <name>Bishopston</name>
            <lat>51.5756777</lat>
            <lon>-4.0493813</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopston">Bishopston may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#black pill">
            <name>Black Pill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#blackhills">
            <name>Blackhills</name>
            <lat>51.6026187</lat>
            <lon>-4.0460486</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#blue anchor">
            <name>Blue Anchor</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue Anchor">Blue Anchor is a seaside village, in the parish of Old Cleeve, close to Carhampton in the West Somerset district of Somerset, England. The village takes its name from a 17th-century inn.
The village marks one end of the Blue Anchor to Lilstock Coast Site of Special Scientific Interest along which the Triassic cliffs have geological interest for the variety of fossils. The coloured alabaster found in the cliffs gave rise to the name of the colour "Watchet Blue". It is on the West Somerset Coast Path.

Blue Anchor railway station is a station on the West Somerset Railway, a heritage railway in Somerset. It is situated in the village and houses the museum of the West Somerset Steam Railway Trust.
Within the village is the only example of an updraught brick kiln known to have survived in Somerset. It was built around 1830, supplied by small vessels carrying limestone to the small culm landing, and is now used as a garage. The kiln is thought to have been used until the 1870s when the large-scale production of bricks in Bridgwater rendered small brickyards uneconomic.
Marshwood farmhouse dates from the late 15th century and was originally a manor house or grange. It has been designated by English Heritage as a Grade II* listed building.
Coincidentally there is another Blue Anchor Inn directly north across the Bristol Channel in East Aberthaw, The Vale of Glamorgan.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#bon-y-maen">
            <name>Bon-y-maen</name>
            <lat>51.641012</lat>
            <lon>-3.910918</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bon-y-maen">Bon-y-maen, sometimes spelt Bonymaen, (Welsh: B&#xF4;n-y-maen) is a community in Swansea, Wales located about 1.5 miles (2.4 km) north east of Swansea city centre. It falls within the Bonymaen ward. Immediately above Bon-y-maen on the top of Kilvey Hill is the main TV transmitter for Swansea. The local rugby team is Bonymaen RFC. Bonymaen is a Communities First area. B&#xF4;n-y-maen is Welsh for 'Base of the stone' and there are legends that the same stone ends in Penmaen (English: Stone End) on the Gower Peninsula.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#bryn">
            <name>Bryn</name>
            <lat>51.6169859</lat>
            <lon>-3.7123799</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn">Bryn (which is Welsh for hill) is a component ward of the Metropolitan Borough of Wigan, Greater Manchester, England. It is part of the larger town of Ashton-in-Makerfield and is geographically indistinguishable from it. It forms a separate local council ward. Served by Bryn railway station, Bryn is home to the Three Sisters Recreation Area which has been created from three large spoil tips which remain from Bryn's role in Lancashire's coal mining past. The Three Sisters Recreation Area is also the site of the Three Sisters Race Circuit, which provides race driving instruction and plays host to kart racing events and motorcycle road race meetings at clubman level.
The former Bryn (or Brynne) Hall was the seat of the Gerard family beginning in the thirteenth century or earlier. It was a "safe house" for the English Roman Catholic martyr and saint Edmund Arrowsmith and his hand was reportedly preserved there after his execution. The house, dating to the fourteenth century, has now completely collapsed and remaining stones been cleared.
The Unitarian Park Lane Chapel in Wigan Road was built in 1697, though its congregation was founded in 1662. It is the oldest Non-conformist chapel and congregation in the whole district. By the nineteenth century Park Lane was only one of nine non-conformist chapels in the heavily recusant area.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bryn">Allt neu fynydd bychan yw bryn. Yn ogystal &#xE2; bod yn elfen gyffredin iawn mewn enwau lleoedd ceir enghreifftiau ohono ar ben ei hun fel enw lle:
Cymru
Bryn (Bannau Brycheiniog); Cyfeirnod grid OS: SO073227
Bryn, Castell-nedd Port Talbot
Bryn, Llanelli
Bryn-y-Gefeiliau
Bryn-crug
Bryn Euryn
Bryn Iwan
Bryn Celli Ddu
Llanfair-ar-y-bryn
Bryn Gwyn
Brynrefail
Bryniau Clwyd
Lloegr
Bryn, Swydd Amwythig
Bryn, Wigan
Cyffredinol
bryngaer
Enw personol Cymraeg ydy Bryn, hefyd. Mae enghreifftiau o nod yn cynnwys:
Bryn F&#xF4;n
Bryn Terfel</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#brynmill">
            <name>Brynmill</name>
            <lat>51.611497</lat>
            <lon>-3.969249</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynmill">Brynmill is a suburb of the City and County of Swansea, Wales, UK. It lies about two miles (3 km) to the west of Swansea city centre. It is a residential area forming the southern part of the Uplands electoral ward. As it is close to Swansea university, many students choose to rent rooms here during term time. Aside from the student population, this is a fairly middle-class area.
Brynmill is approximately bounded by Swansea Bay to the south; Brynmill Lane to the west; Glanbrydan Avenue to the north; Bryn-y-Mor Road to the north-east; and Guildhall Road to the south-east. Brynmill can be further subdivided between the upland area of Brynmill proper and the lowland area of St. Helen's close the sea.
Brynmill is situated on hilly terrain. Many of the properties are built on slopes. Property subsidence is a problem here. Property prices here are around the national average. Council tax rates here are quite high. The area offers convenient access to the city centre shopping area via the Oystermouth Road to the South, and Sketty Road to the North. However, these roads are rather congested during peak hours.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brynmill">Maestref o ddinas Abertawe yw Brynmill. Fe'i lleolir tua dwy filltir (3.2 km) i'r gorllewin o ganol y ddinas. Ardal breswyl ddosbarth canol yw e'n bennaf, ac gan fod Prifysgol Abertawe yn agos iawn mae nifer o fyfyrwyr yn rhenti tai yno yn ystod y tymor.
Ffinir Brynmill gan Fae Abertawe i'r de, L&#xF4;n Brynmill i'r gorllewin, Rhodfa Glanbrydan i'r gogledd, Heol Bryn-y-Mor i'r gogledd-ddwyrain, a Heol Guildhall i'r de-ddwyrain.
Lleolir Brynmill ar dir serth ac mae nifer o'r adeiladau wedi'u codi ar lethrau. O ganlyniad, gall ymsuddiant fod yn broblem yn yr ardal hon. Mae prisiau tai yn Brynmill o amgylch y cyfartaledd cenedlaethol.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#burry">
            <name>Burry</name>
            <lat>51.590026</lat>
            <lon>-4.228153</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burry">Burry is a surname. Notable people with the surname include:
Andrew George Burry (1873&#x2013;1975), businessman, manufacturer and philanthropist
Burt Burry (born 1909), retired professional ice hockey player
Harold Burry (1912&#x2013;1992), head football coach at Westminster College
Hugh Burry (1930&#x2013;2013), New Zealand rugby union player
Lester Burry (1898&#x2013;1977), United Church minister
Mark Burry (21st century), New Zealand architect
Michael Burry, American investment fund manager</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#burry green">
            <name>Burry Green</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burry Green">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Burry Green (ymddengys i cheir enw Cymraeg) a leolir tua 10 milltir i'r gorllewin o ddinas Abertawe ar ben gorllewinol penrhyn G&#x175;yr a thua 2.5 milltir i'r gorllewin o bentref Llanrhidian.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#burry pill">
            <name>Burry Pill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cadle">
            <name>Cadle</name>
            <lat>51.6539639</lat>
            <lon>-3.9825556</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cadle">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Cadle a leolir ar y briffordd A483 rhai milltiroedd i'r gogledd o ddinas Abertawe. Erbyn hyn mae'r hen bentref yn cael ei amgylchynnu gan yr ardaloedd trefol o gwmpas Fforest-fach.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#carnglas">
            <name>Carnglas</name>
            <lat>51.623393</lat>
            <lon>-3.995124</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#caswell">
            <name>Caswell</name>
            <lat>51.5721922</lat>
            <lon>-4.023925</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caswell">Caswell may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cefn-bychan">
            <name>Cefn-bychan</name>
            <lat>51.665206</lat>
            <lon>-3.144116</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cefn-hengoed">
            <name>Cefn-hengoed</name>
            <lat>51.654335</lat>
            <lon>-3.234659</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cefn-y-garth">
            <name>Cefn-y-Garth</name>
            <lat>52.9872711</lat>
            <lon>-3.1268105</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cheriton">
            <name>Cheriton</name>
            <lat>51.616081</lat>
            <lon>-4.238711</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheriton">Cheriton may refer to</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheriton">Gallai Cheriton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#clase">
            <name>Clase</name>
            <lat>51.6664098</lat>
            <lon>-3.9438924</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clase">Clase is a suburban district of the City and County of Swansea, Wales falling within the Mynydd-Bach ward. Clase approximates to the housing area south of Clasemont Road between Morriston and Llangyfelach.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#clydach">
            <name>Clydach</name>
            <lat>51.694293</lat>
            <lon>-3.898795</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clydach">Clydach may refer to any of various settlements and rivers in South Wales:
Clydach, Monmouthshire (village)
Clydach, Swansea (village)
Clydach Gorge, (Welsh Cwm Clydach) Monmouthshire
River Clydach, Monmouthshire, (Welsh Afon Clydach)
Lower Clydach River, Swansea Valley
Upper Clydach River, Swansea Valley
River Clydach (Neath), tributary of River Neath at Neath
Clydach Vale, (Rhondda Cynon Taff)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clydach">Gweler hefyd Clydach (gwahaniaethu).
Tref fechan yn Sir Abertawe, Cymru, yw Clydach. Saif gerllaw traffordd yr M4. Mae tua chwarter y boblogaeth yn siarad Cymraeg.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cockett">
            <name>Cockett</name>
            <lat>51.632323</lat>
            <lon>-3.98227</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cockett">Cockett (Welsh: Y Cocyd) is a community in Swansea, Wales falling within Cockett ward. It is located about 1.5 miles (2.4 km) north west of Swansea city centre.
Cockett, in common with much of western Swansea, was the result of late Victorian and early twentieth century expansion. More housing estates were developed during the 20th Century and further housing was constructed near the Townhill district in the early 2000s. The area now has a broad mix of housing stock. 83 per cent of the property in the Cockett neighbourhood is owner occupied. The South Wales Police regional headquarters for Swansea was based in Cockett, as is Dylan Thomas Community School. The South Wales Police regional headquarters now resides closer to the city centre however. There are a few shops in central Cockett, but the nearest shopping districts are on Carmarthen Road (A483) to the north and the Swansea West Business Park to the north west.
The main road through Cockett is the A4216 road linking Sketty to the south with Fforestfach to the north. Cockett railway station is a currently disused railway station to the north, by Station Road. The old platforms on the West Wales Lines are still in place and there are proposals by South West Wales Integrated Transport Consortium to reinstate this station in the future, which would provide a 10-minute journey to Swansea railway station in the city centre. Cockett is served by First Cymru buses from Swansea bus station: numbers 15 and 17 to Gowerton; number 43 to Morriston Hospital and numbers 400 and 404 to Llanelli.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#common, the">
            <name>Common, The</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#craig-cefn-parc">
            <name>Craig-cefn-parc</name>
            <lat>51.709251</lat>
            <lon>-3.915678</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#craig-y-duke">
            <name>Craig-y-Duke</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#crofty">
            <name>Crofty</name>
            <lat>51.6362161</lat>
            <lon>-4.1290629</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crofty">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Crofty (ymddengys nad oes enw Cymraeg), a leolir tua 4 milltir i'r gorllewin o dref Gorseinon ar lan ogleddol Penrhyn G&#x175;yr, rhwng Penclawdd a Llanmorlais. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Penclawdd.
Saif chwarter milltir o'r m&#xF4;r ger pentref Llanmorlais a chyferbyn i dref Llanelli dros y bae yn Sir Gaerfyrddin.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cwm dulais">
            <name>Cwm Dulais</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwm Dulais">Cwm yn ne Cymru, ym mwrdeisdref sirol Castell-nedd Port Talbot, yw Cwm Dulais, sy'n cael ei enw o Afon Dulais.
Mae'r cwm yn ymestyn tua'r de-orllewin a'r de o gyffiniau Onllwyn, i'r dwyrain o Ystradgynlais, i Aberdulais, fymryn i'r gogledd-ddwyrain o dref Castell Nedd. Y prif bentrefi eraill yw Blaendulais, Y Creunant a Cil-ffriw. Mae'r briffordd A4109 yn arwain ar hyd y cwm.
Fel mae Afon Dulais yn agosau at Afon Nedd ger Aberdulais, mae'n disgyn i raeadr ysblenydd Rhaeadrau Aberdulais, atyniad twristiaeth poblogaidd a safle hen weithfeydd haearn. Mae'r rhaeadr yn eiddo i'r Ymddiriedolaeth Genedlaethol.
Arferai Cwm Dulais fod yn ardal lofaol bwysig iawn. Roedd glofa Cefn Coed ger y Creunant yn nodedig fel y lofa glo carreg ddyfnaf yn y byd ar un adeg. Mae Amgueddfa Glofa Cefn Coed yn hen adeiladau glofa Blaenant, oedd yn estyniad o lofa Cefn Coed.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cwm gwyn">
            <name>Cwm Gwyn</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cwmcerdinen">
            <name>Cwmcerdinen</name>
            <lat>51.7487464</lat>
            <lon>-3.9816271</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cwmdu">
            <name>Cwmdu</name>
            <lat>51.905508</lat>
            <lon>-3.1924229</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwmdu">Cwmdu may refer to:
Cwmdu, Swansea
Cwmdu, Carmarthenshire
Cwmdu, Powys</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwmdu">Gallai Cwmdu neu Cwm-du gyfeirio at:
Cwmdu, Abertawe
Cwmdu, Powys
Cwm-du, Sir Gaerfyrddin
Gweler hefyd
Llanfihangel Cwm Du gyda Bwlch a Chathedin</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#cwmrhydyceirw">
            <name>Cwmrhydyceirw</name>
            <lat>51.6805251</lat>
            <lon>-3.9275073</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cwmrhydyceirw">Cwmrhydyceirw is a village in the City and County of Swansea, south Wales. The village is located about 1 mile north of Morriston town centre. It is home to the main campus of Morriston Hospital, Morriston Comprehensive School and Cwmrhydyceirw Primary School. The English translation of the name means "the valley of the stags' ford" which gave rise to the name of local pub "The Deer's Leap". However, the name of the village may corrupted from its original, thought to have been "Cwmrhydycwrw" - a reference to the ale-like appearance of the local stream ("cwrw" meaning ale).[1]

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#dunvant">
            <name>Dunvant</name>
            <lat>51.62487</lat>
            <lon>-4.033764</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunvant">Dunvant (Welsh: Dyfnant) (Dyfn - deep; nant - stream or brook) is a suburban district in the City and County of Swansea, Wales, and falls within the Dunvant ward. It is situated in a valley some 4.5 miles west of Swansea city centre.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#faerdre">
            <name>Faerdre</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#fagwyr">
            <name>Fagwyr</name>
            <lat>52.467708</lat>
            <lon>-3.9948174</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#felindre">
            <name>Felindre</name>
            <lat>51.706648</lat>
            <lon>-3.973735</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felindre">Felindre (English: Velindre) is a rural village in south Wales. The village can be found in the far north of Swansea, in the electoral ward of Mawr.
The nearby Lower Lliw Reservoirs are a popular venue for walking and fishing. The water mill in the village was working until the late 1960s, there was also an abbatoir and a post office in the village. It also had three shops, and two mobile shops which used to come around the village twice a week. Again this was in the late 60's and 70's. The school in the village is Welsh speaking. There is also a public house in the village, the Shepherds Inn.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felindre">Ceir sawl pentref yng Nghymru o'r enw Felindre:
Felindre, Ceredigion
Felindre, Powys (2):
Felindre, Maldwyn
Felindre, Brycheiniog

Felindre, Sir Abertawe
Felindre, Sir Gaerfyrddin (4):
Felindre, ger Llangadog
Felindre, ger Llanegwad
Felindre, ger Llansadwrn
Felindre, ger Gastell Newydd Emlyn

Gweler hefyd
Dre-fach Felindre</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#fforest-fach">
            <name>Fforest-fach</name>
            <lat>51.647732</lat>
            <lon>-3.985082</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fforest-fach">Pentref yn Sir Abertawe yw Fforest-fach a leolir ar y briffordd A483 ar gwr gogleddol dinas Abertawe. Erbyn hyn mae'r pentref yn cael ei amgylchynnu gan ardaloedd trefol gogledd-orllewin Abertawe.
Ceir parc adwerthu mawr yn Fforest-fach. Yno hefyd ceir safle un o ffatrioedd Walkers Crisps.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#fox hole">
            <name>Fox Hole</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#frog moor">
            <name>Frog Moor</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#garden village">
            <name>Garden Village</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden Village">Garden Village may refer to:
Garden Village, Ebbw Vale, Wales
The Garden Village, Kingston upon Hull
Garden Village, Leeds, England
Garden Village, Lincolnshire, England
Garden Village, Ontario, Canada
Garden Village, Sheffield, England
Garden Village, Swansea, Wales
Garden Village F.C.

Garden Village, Wrexham, Wales
Garden Village, Kentucky
Garden City, New York, a village

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#garn-swllt">
            <name>Garn-swllt</name>
            <lat>51.762796</lat>
            <lon>-3.993668</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#gendros">
            <name>Gendros</name>
            <lat>51.640224</lat>
            <lon>-3.971329</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gendros">Gendros is a suburban district of the City and County of Swansea, Wales falling within the Cockett ward. Gendros approximates to the settlement northwest of Carmarthen Road (A483 road) between Cwmdu and Penlan. Other areas surrounding Gendros are Blaen-y-Maes, Ravenhill, Cwmbwrla, Cockett, Fforestfach and Mayhill and Townhill. Its post code begins with SA5.
Gendros has two churches, a primary school and a community centre.
It is also the birthplace of the famous British boxer Enzo Maccarinelli, a former World Cruiserweight Champion. It is also home to Chris Holley, the ex-mayor of Swansea.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#gerdinen isaf">
            <name>Gerdinen isaf</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#glais">
            <name>Glais</name>
            <lat>51.689365</lat>
            <lon>-3.878138</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glais">Glais is a small semi-rural village of less than 1,000 people located in Swansea, Wales. The village is separated into two different electoral wards by a stream known as Nant-Y-Pal which runs through the middle of the settlement. To the north of Nant-Y-Pal, Glais comes under the Clydach Electoral Ward while to the south Glais falls under the Llansamlet Electoral Ward.
Unusually for place names, Glais is not named after the stream Nant-Y-Pal but instead its name literally translates to Stream.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#gorseinon">
            <name>Gorseinon</name>
            <lat>51.669543</lat>
            <lon>-4.041545</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorseinon">Gorseinon is a district town in Swansea, Wales, near the Loughor estuary. It was a small village until the late 19th century when it grew around the coal mining and tinplate industries. It is situated in the north west of Swansea City Centre, around 6 miles (9.7 km) north west of the city centre. Gorseinon is also a local Government community with its own elected town council.
The population of the Gorseinon town council area in the 2011 Census is 8,693. However, the ONS defines an area called the Gorseinon Urban Area which comprises all of the continuous built up area in and around Gorseinon. This area includes Gorseinon, Loughor, Garden Village and Penllergaer. and has a population of 20,581.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorseinon">Mae Gorseinon yn dref ger Abertawe yn sir Abertawe. Fe'i lleoli ger aber y Llwchwr, tua 6 milltir i'r gogledd-orllewin o ganol y ddinas. Mae Gorseinon hefyd yn gymuned llywodraeth leol gyda chyngor etholedig yn y dref. Pentref bychan ydoedd tan diwedd y 19eg ganrif pan dyfodd yn sg&#xEE;l y diwydiannau glo a thunplat.

Mae Caerdydd 63.9 km i ffwrdd o Orseinon ac mae Llundain yn 273.5 km. Y ddinas agosaf ydy Abertawe sy'n 7.2 km i ffwrdd.
Yn &#xF4;l Cyfrifiad 2001, mae gan ardal cyngor tref Gorseinon boblogaeth o 7,814. Fodd bynnag, diffinia Swyddfa Ystadegau Cenedlaethol y DU ardal a elwir Ardal Drefol Gorseinon sy'n cynnwys yr ardaloedd mwy poblog yn ac o amgylch Gorseinon. Mae'r ardal hon yn cynnwys Gorseinon, Llwchwr, Pentre'r Ardd a Penllergaer ac mae iddi boblogaeth o 19,273.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#gowerton">
            <name>Gowerton</name>
            <lat>51.6480279</lat>
            <lon>-4.042929</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gowerton">The village of Gowerton (Welsh: Treg&#x175;yr) is situated about 4 miles north west of Swansea city centre, Wales. Gowerton is often known as the gateway to Gower. Gowerton's original name was Ffosfelin. The village falls within the Gowerton electoral ward of Swansea.
In 1980, the Welsh National Eisteddfod was hosted on the 'Elba' area of the village, the Eisteddfod stone (Gorsedd stones) is located on the round-about opposite the garage on the road to Penclawdd.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#graig felen">
            <name>Graig Felen</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#graig trewyddfa">
            <name>Graig Trewyddfa</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#graig-fawr">
            <name>Graig-Fawr</name>
            <lat>51.8225737</lat>
            <lon>-4.1505964</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#grovesend">
            <name>Grovesend</name>
            <lat>51.688828</lat>
            <lon>-4.038314</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grovesend">Grovesend (Welsh: Pengelli) is a village in the community of Grovesend and Waungron (Welsh: Pengelli a Waungron), City and County of Swansea in Wales. The community has a population of 1,181.
Grovesend is a mainly residential community, with the major amenity being the welfare club. Locals must travel to nearby areas such as Gorseinon or Pontarddulais for shopping. Grovesend also has a primary school, with about 100 pupils in, and a nursing home.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#hafod">
            <name>Hafod</name>
            <lat>51.6094859</lat>
            <lon>-3.3813899</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hafod">Hafod is a district of the city of Swansea, in South Wales, U.K., and lies just north of the city centre, within the Landore ward. Hafod is the home to the Hafod Copperworks, founded in 1810 and closed in 1980 which is now being developed into an industrial heritage site.
The word hafod is Welsh for 'summer dwelling' (compare sheiling) or 'farm', and refers to the seasonal cycle of transhumance - the movement of livestock and people from a lowland winter pasture at the main residence (Welsh hendre) to a higher summer pasture from roughly May through October.
The western part of Hafod is a residential suburb. In the late 20th century, this was a mostly run-down area of Swansea, with property prices there being some of the lowest in the city centre area. In the new millennium, many properties in the main Neath Road (B4603) and some of the side streets have benefited from council grants to improve the fa&#xE7;ade of the properties. Beside the River Tawe to the east is a small industrial strip around Morfa Road.
Hafod has a comprehensive school called Pentrehafod School, and a primary school called Hafod Primary school. There used to be junior and senior schools located on the same site but the school was ravaged by fire during the early 1990s. The new primary school was built to replace it and new buildings were constructed within the grounds of Pentrehafod school to cater for the junior and senior pupils. The community sports facility is the Pentrehafod sports hall and pool located in the grounds of the Pentrehafod Comprehensive School. The school is built on what was formerly the waste product dumping ground for the Morris family copper works.
Neath Road is a busy thoroughfare used by buses and cars to travelling between central Swansea and the northern suburbs in and around Morriston and Llansamlet. There is a dedicated express bus route to the east of Neath Road, which is used by buses serving the Landore Park and Ride site and the 'bendy bus' service from Singleton Hospital to Morriston Hospital.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#hendrewen">
            <name>Hendrewen</name>
            <lat>53.2181808</lat>
            <lon>-4.134996</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#heol las">
            <name>Heol Las</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#heol-ddu">
            <name>Heol-ddu</name>
            <lat>51.816049</lat>
            <lon>-4.12201</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#hillend">
            <name>Hillend</name>
            <lat>51.5949385</lat>
            <lon>-4.2860202</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillend">Hillend may refer to:
Hillend, Fife
Hillend, Edinburgh
Hillend, New Zealand</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#horton">
            <name>Horton</name>
            <lat>51.548526</lat>
            <lon>-4.201441</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horton">Horton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ilston">
            <name>Ilston</name>
            <lat>51.594221</lat>
            <lon>-4.084956</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#killay">
            <name>Killay</name>
            <lat>51.617448</lat>
            <lon>-4.019402</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killay">Killay may refer to:
Killay, County Tyrone, a townland and hamlet near Pomeroy in County Tyrone, Northern Ireland
Killay, Swansea, a suburb and local government community in Swansea, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#kittle">
            <name>Kittle</name>
            <lat>51.5840457</lat>
            <lon>-4.0601657</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kittle">Kittle may refer to:
Kittle (surname)
Kittle (Guyana), a kettle drum used in the music of Guyana
Kittle, Swansea, an area of Pennard, Swansea, Wales</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#knab, the">
            <name>Knab, The</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#knelston">
            <name>Knelston</name>
            <lat>51.578038</lat>
            <lon>-4.212099</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#landimore">
            <name>Landimore</name>
            <lat>51.614672</lat>
            <lon>-4.217941</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landimore">Landimore (Welsh: Lland&#xEE;m&#xF4;r) is a hamlet on the north coast of the Gower, in the City and County of Swansea, south Wales. To the north are the extensive saltmarshes of Landimore Marsh, adjoining the Loughor estuary. Landimore Castle which is also known as Bovehill Castle is perched on a hill overlooking the village at OS grid reference SS 464993. Its ruinous remains are on private ground.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#landore">
            <name>Landore</name>
            <lat>51.6412925</lat>
            <lon>-3.9369162</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landore">Landore (Welsh: Gland&#x175;r) is a district of Swansea, Wales, falling in the Landore council ward. A mainly residential area, it is located about 2.5 miles north of Swansea city centre. The north-easterly part of Landore is known as Morfa. There have been a number of new developments in the 21st century, such as the Liberty Stadium and the Morfa Shopping Park, which opened in 2005.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#langland">
            <name>Langland</name>
            <lat>51.568571</lat>
            <lon>-4.0123066</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langland">Langland could refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#leason">
            <name>Leason</name>
            <lat>51.611265</lat>
            <lon>-4.19066</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#little reynoldston">
            <name>Little Reynoldston</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llanddewi">
            <name>Llanddewi</name>
            <lat>52.309483</lat>
            <lon>-3.310747</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanddewi">Gallai'r enw lle Llanddewi gyfeirio at un o sawl lle:
Cymru
Llanddewi, G&#x175;yr
Llanddewi Brefi
Llanddewi Nant Hodni
Llanddewi'r Cwm
Llanddewi Rhydderch
Llanddewi-yn-Heiob
Llanddewi Ysgyryd
Llanddewi Ystradenni
Lloegr
Llanddewi, Swydd Henffordd
Llanddewi Cil Peddeg</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llangennith">
            <name>Llangennith</name>
            <lat>51.600446</lat>
            <lon>-4.271032</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangennith">Llangennith (Welsh: Llangenydd/Llangynydd) is a village in Gower, in the City and County of Swansea, south Wales. It sits at a crossroads in northwest Gower: Moor Lane leads westwards to a caravan park near Rhossili Bay; while Burrows Lane leads northwards to a caravan park overlooking Broughton Bay. The village has a scattering of houses, centred on St Cenydd's church, and one pub - the King's Head. The neighbouring bay is popular with surfers.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llangyfelach">
            <name>Llangyfelach</name>
            <lat>51.671667</lat>
            <lon>-3.960054</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangyfelach">Llangyfelach is a village located in the City and County of Swansea, Wales. Llangyfelach is situated about 4 miles north of the centre of Swansea, just west of Morriston. It falls within the Llangyfelach ward. To the west is open moorland.
Llangyfelach was once the name of a parish that covered much of the former Lordship of Gower. Today's community covers a smaller area including the site of the former Felindre tinplate works, which hosted the National Eisteddfod in 2006.
Bordering the village to the north is the M4 motorway Junction 46. The village has its own primary school, crematorium, a former post office, The 'Plough and Harrow' pub, and a Scout hall.
At the centre of the village is the Parish Church of St David and Cyfelach. The site dates back to the 6th Century: St. David the Patron Saint of Wales founded an early Celtic monastery there. The present church has a 12th Century detached tower and a converted tithe barn as the present church. Contained within the church is the Llangyfelach Cross, a 9th Century Celtic stone.
Llangyfelach was the birthplace of the painter Evan Walters, and is mentioned in a folk song about the practice of 'pressing' men into military service.
Llangyfelach is the birthplace for welsh international bowler Mark Watkins who now resides in Brynhyfryd, Swansea.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llangyfelach">Pentref a chymuned yn ninas a sir Abertawe yw Llangyfelach. Saif tua pedair milltir i'r gogledd o ganol dinas Abertawe, ac i'r gorllewin o Dreforys. Mae traffordd yr M4 ychydig i'r gogledd.
Ceir yno ysgol gynradd, amlosgfa a thafarn. Mae'r eglwys wedi ei chysegru i Dewi Sant a Sant Cyfelach. Credir bod clas Celtaidd wedi bod ar y safle; mae t&#x175;r yr eglwys bresennol, sydd ar wahan i'r eglwys ei hun, yn dyddio o'r 12fed ganrif. Ar un adeg roedd yr eglwys yn un o ganolfannau pwysicaf cantref Eginog. Tu mewn i'r eglwys mae Croes Llangyfelach, Croes Geltaidd yn dyddio o'r 9fed ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llanmadoc">
            <name>Llanmadoc</name>
            <lat>51.618953</lat>
            <lon>-4.255532</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llanmorlais">
            <name>Llanmorlais</name>
            <lat>51.6307685</lat>
            <lon>-4.121865</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanmorlais">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Llanmorlais a leolir tua 4.5 milltir i'r gorllewin o dref Gorseinon ar lan ogleddol Penrhyn G&#x175;yr. Mae'n rhan o blwyf eglwysig Llanrhidian Uchaf.
Saif chwarter milltir o'r m&#xF4;r ger pentref Crofty a chyferbyn i dref Llanelli dros y bae yn Sir Gaerfyrddin, ar y B4295 sy'n ei gysylltu &#xE2; Gorseinon a Llanrhidian.
Ceir cors sylweddol rhwng y pentref a Llanrhidian.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llanrhidian">
            <name>Llanrhidian</name>
            <lat>51.608256</lat>
            <lon>-4.17126</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanrhidian">Mae Llanrhidian yn bentref ar benrhyn G&#x175;yr, yn sir Abertawe, de Cymru. Enwir y llan a'r pentref ar &#xF4;l y sant cynnar Rhidian (5ed-6ed ganrif).
Saif y pentref bron yng nghanol penrhyn G&#x175;yr, ar groesffordd i'r de-orllewin o Benclawdd hanner ffordd rhwng Dynfant a Llangynydd.
Mae'r pentref yn rhoi ei enw i gymunedau Llanrhidian Uchaf a Llanrhidian Isaf.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#llansamlet">
            <name>Llansamlet</name>
            <lat>51.664173</lat>
            <lon>-3.900516</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llansamlet">Llansamlet is a suburban district of Swansea, Wales, falling into the Llansamlet ward. The area is centered on the A48 road (named Samlet Road and Clase Road in the area) and the M4 motorway.
Similar to many other places in Wales where the name begins with Llan, Llansamlet is named after a saint &#x2013; Saint Samlet. There is a Saint Samlet's Church in the area on Church Road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llansamlet">Cymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Abertawe yw Llansamlet. Saif yng ngogledd-ddwyrain dinas Abertawe, o amgylch y briffordd A48 a'r draffordd M4. Roedd y boblogaeth yn 2001 yn 6,196.
Datbygodd diwydiannau glo a chopr pwysig yma yn y 18fed ganrif.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#lon-las">
            <name>Lon-las</name>
            <lat>53.3648075</lat>
            <lon>-4.5175844</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#loughor">
            <name>Loughor</name>
            <lat>51.665095</lat>
            <lon>-4.067286</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loughor">Loughor (/&#x2C8;l&#x28C;x&#x259;r/) (Welsh: Casllwchwr) is a town in the City and County of Swansea, Wales, within the historic county boundaries of Glamorgan, Wales. It lies on the estuary of the River Loughor. The town has a community council called Llwchwr. In 2014, it was rated one of the most attractive postcode areas to live in Wales.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#low neck">
            <name>Low Neck</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#lower sketty">
            <name>Lower Sketty</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#lunnon">
            <name>Lunnon</name>
            <lat>51.588281</lat>
            <lon>-4.10046</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#manselfield">
            <name>Manselfield</name>
            <lat>51.5807461</lat>
            <lon>-4.0360794</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#manselton">
            <name>Manselton</name>
            <lat>51.639634</lat>
            <lon>-3.9523651</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manselton">Manselton is a suburban area of Swansea, Wales falling within the Cwmbwrla ward. Manselton approximates to the area to the west of Llangyfelach Road just north of the railway line from Landore depot to west Wales.
Manselton consists mainly of suburban housing, although there is large, open park area and a few shops. The local primary school is Manselton Primary school.
Grade II listed buildings in the area include:
Mount Calvary Baptist Chapel &amp; Hall on Cecil Street
Manselton School &amp; attached Block on Manor Road
St. Michael &amp; All Angel's Church on Manor Road
Manselton also has a local doctors surgery which is located along the side road by the local Chemist. It also has a local community center which is located behind the chemist.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mayals">
            <name>Mayals</name>
            <lat>51.5933629</lat>
            <lon>-4.010752</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayals">Mayals is a suburb of Swansea, Wales. It is located about 3 miles south west of Swansea city centre. It falls within the Mayals ward and the Mumbles community council area (MCC). The ward of Mayals lies within the constituency of Swansea West, the only MCC ward not in the Gower constituency.
The suburb of Mayals consists mainly of higher value privately owned housing. Located on Clyne Common near the suburb in the area is the Craig-y-Nos School, an independent school for children, whilst the well performing Mayals Primary School lies within the area. Actress Catherine Zeta-Jones once lived in the Mayals, on St Andrews Close and singer Bonnie Tyler maintains a home in Blackpill.
Much of the Mayals area is accounted for by Clyne common, upon which is the prestigious 18-hole Clyne golf club.
The renowned botanical gardens at Clyne also account for a significant amount of Mayals. The gardens include many rare, tropical and notable plans, including Britain&#x2019;s largest Magnolia, and many hybrids. Notable constructions include a Japanese bridge, the Admirals Tower, Gazebo, and the neo-Gothic Victorian Church. There is also a small lake, an unused quarry, family Pet Cemetery, and many hidden and secluded areas with Victorian paving and red-brick steps. However, the most notable building of all is Clyne Castle, built in 1791 by Richard Phillips a wealthy landowner. The castle and grounds were bought by the wealthy Swansea Vivian family in 1860, who made many changes to the castle and grounds. During that time the Castle hosted many notable guests, including Adelina Patti, Neville Chamberlain, Queen Victoria, Winston Churchill, and King Edward VIII and later on Jon and Carys Richards. In 1952 the Castle came under the ownership of Swansea University, becoming student accommodation. In 2003 the Castle was sold to become high value luxury apartments.
There is also a smaller Mayals Park, next to Mayals Primary School which unlike Clyne, has play-facilities for children as well as a small basketball court, footpaths and streams, and an unmaintained wooded area.
In the local council elections in 2008 Mayals (electoral ward) was won by Conservative Candidate Rene Kinzett, who stood for Swansea West in the 2010 national election. In the 2012 local council elections Linda Tyler-Lloyd retained the seat for the Conservative Party after Rene Kinzett decided to stand down.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mayhill">
            <name>Mayhill</name>
            <lat>51.6277904</lat>
            <lon>-3.9542345</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayhill">The district of Mayhill (also known as Mayhill Garden City) is spread over the top of a steep hill of the same name just north west of Swansea city centre, partly separated from Townhill to the west.
Mayhill Garden City started in 1914 as an experimental row of six houses that are still in occupation today as even numbers 2 to 12 Islwyn Road. The majority of homes were built by 1940. Maps from 1874, 1879, and 1921 confirm that prior to the Mayhill Garden City project, Townhill Farm occupied the upper end of Waun Wen Road and a well used by Baptists was located halfway down. At the end of what is now called Long Ridge (previously called Bryon Crescent) there was, and still is, a Jewish burial ground. Waun Wen Road was completed before 1938.
Politically, Mayhill falls within the Townhill ward. The south side of Mayhill overlooks the city centre, docklands and Swansea Bay. A prominent landmark on Mayhill, visible from the city centre and Hafod is Sea View Primary School (previously known as Mayhill Primary).
Mayhill consists mostly of suburban housing, however it does also feature a post office on Townhill Road, two fast food takeaways and a convenience store at the bottom of Waun Wen Road, as well as a small collection of shops at the intersection of Mayhill Road and Townhill Road. There are several churches in Mayhill including Our Lady of Lourdes, a popular Roman Catholic church, and Hill URC Church. Mayhill also features several park and nature reserve areas.
The largest open space recreational area is located around Sea View Primary School and includes parkland, small wooded areas, and heathland. There is also a small picnic park located along Bryn Y Don Road, and woodland between Waun Wen Road and Townhill Road.
The local football team is West End F.C. who play in Pryderi Park Stadium in the area.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#middleton">
            <name>Middleton</name>
            <lat>51.567149</lat>
            <lon>-4.277898</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middleton">It may also be spelled Middelton, Myddleton, and Myddelton.
Middleton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#morriston">
            <name>Morriston</name>
            <lat>51.662244</lat>
            <lon>-3.930297</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morriston">Morriston (Welsh: Treforys) is a community in the City and County of Swansea, Wales and falls within the Morriston ward. Morriston is sometimes referred to as a distinct town (e.g. the local football club is named Morriston Town A.F.C.), however Morriston never had a town charter, and is now part of the continuous urban area around Swansea, the centre of which lies three miles to the south-west. Morriston is the most populous of Swansea's electoral divisions. Morriston's Orpheus Choir has been described as one of the leading Welsh choirs.
Morriston is close to other communities, these areas include Parc Gwernfadog, Cwmrhydyceirw, Clase, Ynystawe, Ynysforgan. This is due to the gradual centralisation of Morriston as an Electoral ward over the years which has gained intensity in the last decade due to the fast amount of services, organisations and commercial outlets available in the main area of Morriston.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mumbles head">
            <name>Mumbles Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mumbles hill">
            <name>Mumbles Hill</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumbles Hill">Mumbles Hill is a hill near the south eastern tip of the Gower Peninsula, Wales. Parts of the hill form a designated Local Nature Reserve, declared in 1991.
Defensive gunnery positions were built on the hill in World War II. Remnants of the 623rd Anti-Aircraft Battery gun emplacements and control bunker are still visible on the hill.
Coastal Defence Battery 299 had a site on a hill with 6 inch gun and underground magazines, though none of this remains on the hill. However there are information boards marking the spot.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mumbles, the">
            <name>Mumbles, The</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#murton">
            <name>Murton</name>
            <lat>51.5821143</lat>
            <lon>-4.0432592</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murton">Murton could refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mynydd-bach">
            <name>Mynydd-Bach</name>
            <lat>51.646062</lat>
            <lon>-2.748088</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mynydd-Bach">Mynydd-Bach or Mynydd-bach is a suburban district of the City and County of Swansea, Wales and falls within the Mynydd-Bach ward. The name Mynydd-Bach ("little mountain") refers to a small plateau, centred about 2.5 miles (4 km) north of Swansea city centre. The most important local employer is the DVLA, which moved here in 1974.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#mynydd-bach-y-glo">
            <name>Mynydd-bach-y-glo</name>
            <lat>51.6429858</lat>
            <lon>-4.0068397</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#newton">
            <name>Newton</name>
            <lat>51.5726783</lat>
            <lon>-4.0161386</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton">Newton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton">Gallai Newton gyfeirio at:</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#nicholaston">
            <name>Nicholaston</name>
            <lat>51.574946</lat>
            <lon>-4.135357</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholaston">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Nicholaston (ymddengys ni cheir enw Cymraeg). a leolir tua 8 milltir i'r gorllewin o ddinas Abertawe. Mae'n gorwedd ar lan Bae Oxwich ar Benrhyn G&#x175;yr. Mae tywynod Nicholaston yn Warchodfa Natur Cenedlaethol. Rhed y briffordd A4118 trwy'r pentref.
&#x2191; Enwau Cymru</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#northway">
            <name>Northway</name>
            <lat>51.5853603</lat>
            <lon>-4.0413315</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northway">Northway may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#norton">
            <name>Norton</name>
            <lat>52.298095</lat>
            <lon>-3.021757</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norton">Norton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#oldwalls">
            <name>Oldwalls</name>
            <lat>51.6058189</lat>
            <lon>-4.186653</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#oldway">
            <name>Oldway</name>
            <lat>51.5801043</lat>
            <lon>-4.0441095</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#overton">
            <name>Overton</name>
            <lat>52.97233</lat>
            <lon>-2.934909</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overton">Overton may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#oxwich">
            <name>Oxwich</name>
            <lat>51.559028</lat>
            <lon>-4.170341</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxwich">Oxwich is a village on the Gower Peninsula, in the city and county of Swansea in south Wales. Oxwich is part of the small community of Penrice which extends from the village of Horton to Oxwich Bay, and as of 2001 recorded a population of 454 inhabitants.
Oxwich's main site of historical interest is the castle which is thought by many academics to be the most historic castle on the Gower Peninsula. The earliest evidence of it being inhabited is in 1459, where Philip Mansel was recorded as holding it. The Mansel family were a minor gentry in South Wales, who grew in power and prestige under the Tudor monarchs. The parish church of St. Illtyd's overlooks Oxwich Bay. A place of worship has stood on this site since the 6th century, but the main tower of today was built in the 14th century. The chancel of this church is thought to be a 6th-century cell. The church bell in the tower also dates back to the 14th century, but was recast in 1892. In the churchyard there is a well, which locals believe is haunted by a ghost. Legend has it that a ghost was seen in the churchyard before vanishing into a well.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxwich">Pentref ar arfordir deheuol Penrhyn G&#x175;yr ym mwrdeisdref siol Abertawe yw Oxwich (Cyf. OS SS498864). Saif yng nghymuned Pen-rhys. Nid ymddengys fod enw Cymraeg iddo.
Cysegrwyd yr eglwys, sy'n dyddio o'r 13eg a'r 14eg ganrif, i Sant Illtud. Gerllaw'r pentref mae traeth Bae Oxwich, Castell Oxwich, sy'n dyddio o gyfnod y Tuduriaid, a Chastell Pen-rhys. Yma hefyd mae gwarchodfa Natur Genedlaethol Oxwich. Mae Oxwich yn gyrchfan boblogaidd iawn i ymwelwyr, a cheir nifer o westai yma yn ogystal a maes carafannau.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#oxwich green">
            <name>Oxwich Green</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#oystermouth">
            <name>Oystermouth</name>
            <lat>51.575218</lat>
            <lon>-4.006723</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oystermouth">Oystermouth (a corruption of the Welsh name Ystum Llwynarth or Ystumllwynarth) is an electoral ward and a village in the Mumbles community and also the City and County of Swansea, Wales.
The electoral ward consists of some or all of the following areas: Oystermouth, the Mumbles, Thistleboon, Limeslade, in the parliamentary constituency of Gower. The ward is bounded by Newton to the west, West Cross to the north and Swansea Bay to the south and east. As of 2010 it had a population of around 4,100.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pantyffynnon">
            <name>Pantyffynnon</name>
            <lat>51.779145</lat>
            <lon>-3.985494</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pantyffynnon">Pantyffynnon is a small village in Carmarthenshire, Wales, half a mile south-west of Ammanford, and a mile east of Tycroes. It lies between the rivers Loughor and Amman at the foot of Mynydd y Betws.
The village is served by Pantyffynnon railway station on the Heart of Wales Line.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pantyffynnon">Pentref bychan yn ne Sir Gaerfyrddin yw Pantyffynnon. Mae'n rhan o gymuned Rhydaman.
Mae'n gorwedd tua milltir i'r de-orllewin o dref Rhydaman yn rhan isaf Dyffryn Aman. Fe'i lleolir rhwng afonydd Llwchwr ac Aman ac wrth droed Mynydd y Betws. Mae Gorsaf reilffordd Pantyffynnon ar llinell Rheilffordd Calon Cymru.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#parc-hendy">
            <name>Parc-hendy</name>
            <lat>53.1658234</lat>
            <lon>-3.1556807</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#parkmill">
            <name>Parkmill</name>
            <lat>51.582248</lat>
            <lon>-4.091894</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkmill">The village of Parkmill (Welsh: Melin y Parc) is a small rural settlement in the Gower Peninsula (Welsh: G&#x175;yr), South Wales (Welsh: De Cymru), midway between the villages of Penmaen and Ilston (Welsh: Llanilltud Gwyr), about eight miles (13 km) west of Swansea (Welsh: Abertawe), and about one mile (1.5 km) from the north coast of the Bristol Channel (Welsh: M&#xF4;r Hafren). The village lies to the north of the A4118, the main South Gower road between Swansea and Port Eynon, in a wooded area, at the bottom of a valley.
The building at the centre of the village is a former school that is now home to the West Glamorgan Girl Guides Activity Centre. Pennard golf course lies immediately to the south of the village. Parkmill is in the Gower ward of the City and County of Swansea (Welsh: Cyngor Dinas a Sir Abertawe).
Parkmill's only religious building is the Mount Pisgah United Reformed Church, a Congregational chapel, erected in 1822 and rebuilt in 1890.
The area is little changed from the mid 19th century, when Samuel Lewis said in his 'A Topographical Dictionary of Wales' (1849):

The hamlet of Park-Mill, forming the most populous part of the parish, [Ilston] is yet extremely rural; and the surrounding scenery, which is characterized by features of tranquillity and seclusion, is enlivened by the small rivulet called Pennarth Pill, winding along a beautiful dell, in which are the ruins of an ancient chapel. On this stream a cloth manufactory was established early in the present century, but it has been discontinued.

The 'cloth manufactory', a 12th-century water powered corn and saw mill, at Parkmill has since been renovated and a rural crafts centre sited in it, called the Gower Heritage Centre.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pen-caer-fenny">
            <name>Pen-caer-fenny</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pen-clawdd">
            <name>Pen-clawdd</name>
            <lat>51.6419</lat>
            <lon>-4.100126</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pen-lan">
            <name>Pen-lan</name>
            <lat>51.6476356</lat>
            <lon>-3.9633356</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#penllergaer">
            <name>Penllergaer</name>
            <lat>51.670418</lat>
            <lon>-4.007427</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penllergaer">Penllergaer (Welsh: Penlle'r-gaer) is a village in the City and County of Swansea, Wales, falling within the electoral ward of the same name. It is situated about 4.5 miles north west of Swansea city centre, near junction 47 of the M4 motorway.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#penmaen">
            <name>Penmaen</name>
            <lat>51.6748594</lat>
            <lon>-3.1757295</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmaen">Penmaen may refer to one of several places in Wales:
Penmaen, Caerphilly
Penmaen, Swansea
See also:
Penmaenmawr, Conwy County Borough</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penmaen">Mae Penmaen wedi'i ddynodi'n Safle o Ddiddordeb Gwyddonol Arbennig yng Nghymru (SoDdGA neu SSSI) ers 01 Ionawr 1981 fel ymgais gadwraethol i amddiffyn a gwarchod y safle. Mae ei arwynebedd yn 0.26 hectar. Cyfoeth Naturiol Cymru yw'r corff sy'n gyfrifol am y safle.
&#x2191; Gwefan Cyngor Cefn Gwlad Cymru (bellach 'Cyfoeth Naturiol Cymru'); adalwyd 25 Rhagfyr 2013</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pennard">
            <name>Pennard</name>
            <lat>51.5758023</lat>
            <lon>-4.0882899</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennard">Pentref a chymuned ar benrhyn G&#x175;yr, yn sir Abertawe, yw Pennard. Saif tua 7 milltir i'r de-orllewin o ganol dinas Abertawe. Y canolfannau mwyaf poblog yn y gymuned yw Southgate a Kittle; pentref bychan yw Pennard ei hun. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 2,648.
Mae Castell Pennard, sydd gerllaw Three Cliffs Bay, yn dyddio o tua 1300, ond wedi ei adeiladu ar safle castell cynharach o tua 1150. Ceir gweddillion hen eglwys Pennard gerllaw. Claddwyd hon gan y twyni tywod yn y 14eg ganrif, a defnyddiwyd rhan o'i deunydd i adeiladu yr eglwys newydd rhyw 2 km i'r dwyrain. Claddwyd y bardd Harri Webb yma.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#penrice">
            <name>Penrice</name>
            <lat>51.570474</lat>
            <lon>-4.17669</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penrice">Penrice may refer to:
Penrice, South Australia, a small town in the Barossa Valley in Australia
Penrice, Swansea, a community in Wales
Penrice Castle, near Penrice, Swansea.
Penrice Community College, a comprehensive school in St Austell, Cornwall
Penrice Soda Products a company listed on the Australian Stock Exchange named after its quarry near the town in South Australia
English surname:
Major John Penrice author of a glossary of the Quran (1873)</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pentre-chwyth">
            <name>Pentre-chwyth</name>
            <lat>51.637604</lat>
            <lon>-3.926397</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pentre-dwr">
            <name>Pentre-dwr</name>
            <lat>51.650752</lat>
            <lon>-3.891723</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pentrebach">
            <name>Pentrebach</name>
            <lat>51.721203</lat>
            <lon>-3.355544</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentrebach">Pentrebach (sometimes written Pentre-Bach) (translation: small village) is a village in Merthyr Tydfil County Borough, Wales. It lies on the east side of the River Taff opposite Abercanaid, South of Merthyr and North of Troedyrhiw. To the east of the village lies the Mynydd Cilfach-yr-Encil which rises up to 445 m. Pentrebach can be translated as "Little Village"
Pentrebach is part of the Plymouth electoral ward which covers Pentrebach, Abercanaid and Troedyrhiw. The village was founded at the time that John Guest built the Plymouth Ironworks in 1763. The name Guest became part of the Guest, Keen and Nettelfold company (GKN). In 1818 Anthony Hill took over ownership of the business. His House was later used as an old people's home, and today has been converted into a Brewers Fayre Restaurant with a Premier Inn attached.

The original Merthyr Tramroad, built in 1802, ran alongside the site of the modern day village, on it way from Pennydarren to Abercynon, though very little of the village had been built at that time. A tunnel still exists, which can be visited on the Merthyr Road. Locomotives had to tip their chimneys while going though this tunnel due to the tunnel clearance.
Pentrebach has its own railway station. This opened in 1886 on the standard gauge Taff Vale Railway which runs from Cardiff to Merthyr alongside the River Taff. The original purpose of the railway was to carry iron ore to Cardiff Docks.
In 1862, on the south side of the Village, The South Duffryn Colliery was opened with two shafts which were 250 m deep. At the height of the production there were some 1300 men employed there. An opencast mine was also located on the mountainside above the village.
The Plymouth Ironworks closed in 1882 and the South Duffryn Colliery ceased production in 1940.

After the war, new industries were attracted to the village. In 1945, the Kayser Bondor Factory opened making underwear, followed in 1948 by the establishment of the Hoover factory manufacturing washing machines. The factory later went on the produce the Sinclair C5 battery-powered three-wheeler car. On Friday, 6 March 2009, Hoover confirmed that it was to cease production of washing machines and other laundry products at the factory. Linde has set up a factory in the village on a site where the South Duffryn Colliery was located.
Pentrebach has two clubs: The Hills Plymouth Cricket Club, and the Pentrebach Working men's club. Pentrebach also has a chapel, Jerusalem Chapel, Greenfield School and an Integrated Children's Centre.
The mountain above Pentrebach has become popular with hang glider pilots in recent years.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentrebach">Pentref ym mwrdeisdref sirol Merthyr Tudful yw Pentrebach, weithiau Pentre-bach.
Saif i'r de o ganol tref Merthyr Tudful, yr ochr arall o Afon Taf i bentref Abercannaid ac i'r gogledd o bentref Troed-y-rhiw. I'r dwyrain o'r pentref mae Mynydd Cilfach-yr-Encil (445 m.).
Tyfodd y pentref wedi i John Guest sefydlu Gwaith Haearn Plymouth yn 1763. Roedd rheilffordd wreiddiol Trevethick, a adeiladwyd yn 1804, yn arwain trwy'r pentref ar ei ffordd rhwng Penydarren ac Abercynon. Mae twnel yn yn dal i'w weld yma. Agorwyd Glofa South Duffryn yn 1862.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#penydre">
            <name>Penydre</name>
            <lat>51.6656053</lat>
            <lon>-3.7989143</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#penyrheol">
            <name>Penyrheol</name>
            <lat>51.5857521</lat>
            <lon>-3.2414775</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penyrheol">Penyrheol may refer to:
Penyrheol, Caerphilly
Penyrheol, Pontypool
Penyrheol, Swansea</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penyrheol">Gallai Penyrheol gyfeirio at:
Penyrheol, Caerffili
Penyrheol, Abertawe</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pill">
            <name>Pill</name>
            <lat>51.480421</lat>
            <lon>-2.68773</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pill">Pill or The Pill may refer to:
Drug-related:
Pill (pharmacy), referring to anything small and round for a specific dose of medicine
"The Pill", a general nickname for the combined oral contraceptive pill
Places:
Pill, Tyrol, a municipality in Austria
Pill, Somerset, a village in the United Kingdom
Pill, a colloquial abbreviation of Pillgwenlly, electoral ward in the city of Newport, South Wales
Entertainment:
"The Pill" (song), a 1975 song by Loretta Lynn
"The Pill", a 1965 song by The Brothers-in-Law on their 1965 album "Oh, Oh, Canada"
The Pill (film), a 2011 film
"The Pill", a 1999 episode of That '70s Show TV series
"Pills", a song by Bo Diddley
People:
Alison Pill (born 1985), Canadian actress
Brett Pill (born 1984), American Major League Baseball player
Cathy Pill, Belgian fashion designer
Malcolm Pill (born 1938), a former Lord Justice of Appeal of the Court of Appeal of England and Wales
Pill (rapper), American rapper
Other uses:
Pill (textile), a small ball of fuzz on cloth, or the creation of such fuzz balls</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pill">Ardal o fewn i gymuned Aberdaugleddau, Sir Benfro, Cymru yw Pill, sydd 80.9 milltir (130.2 km) o Gaerdydd a 210.5 milltir (338.8 km) o Lundain.

Cynrychiolir Pill yn y Cynulliad Cenedlaethol gan Paul Davies (Ceidwadwyr) a'r Aelod Seneddol yw Stephen Crabb (Ceidwadwyr).
&#x2191; Gwefan y Cynulliad; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014
&#x2191; Gwefan parliament.uk; adalwyd 24 Chwefror 2014</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pilton green">
            <name>Pilton Green</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pitton">
            <name>Pitton</name>
            <lat>51.566471</lat>
            <lon>-4.271145</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pitton">Pitton is also the name of a small village in the Gower Peninsula, Wales.
Pitton is a village in Wiltshire, England, about 7 miles (11 km) east of Salisbury, just off the A30 London Road.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pontardulais">
            <name>Pontardulais</name>
            <lat>51.712266</lat>
            <lon>-4.037071</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pontlliw">
            <name>Pontlliw</name>
            <lat>51.69301</lat>
            <lon>-4.011885</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontlliw">Pontlliw (Welsh spelling: Pont-lliw) is a village in the community of Pontlliw and Tircoed, part of the City and County of Swansea in Wales. The community has an elected community council, and has a population of 2,075. The village is located near Pontarddulais, off Junction 47 of the M4 motorway.
The name of the village comes from the Welsh word for bridge (pont) and the name of the River Lliw which runs through the village.
Pontlliw has a primary school, as well as a number of small businesses such as a newsagent, Post Office, a hair salon and two public houses - The Buck and The Castle, colloquially known as 'The Shed' - as well as Indian restaurant Rasoi 
The village also is home to Pontarddulais Golf Club - which lies within the boundaries of Pontlliw despite its name featuring neighbouring village Pontarddulais. The 9 hole course opened in the 1990s under the name Allt y Graban.
Pontlliw Village Hall is regularly used to stage theatrical performances and concerts as well as classes run by local groups  including Mark Jermin Stage School 
Passing motorists have to take care through the village though, as there are three sets of speed cameras in the village.
Pontlliw is located between the neighbouring villages Penllergaer and Pontarddulais.
Pontlliw is also the birthplace of Gareth Roberts, the former Wales rugby union player. Other notable residents with a rugby connection include Mervyn 'the Swerve' Davies, who lived in Vernon Close and Paul Thorburn, who lived in Heol Y Waun during the early 1990s.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#port mead">
            <name>Port Mead</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#port tennant">
            <name>Port Tennant</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port Tennant">Port Tennant is a suburban district of Swansea, Wales, falling within the St. Thomas ward. Port Tennant lies at the southern foot of Kilvey Hill just east of St. Thomas and is bounded by the Fabian Way to the south. It is a mostly residential area. An up and coming place to live, located next to the exciting SA1 development.
The area takes its name from the Tennant family who developed the Tennant Canal and were responsible for developing the area. The Tennant Canal terminates at the Vale of Neath Inn (now closed) in the south east of Port Tennant.
Local amenities include the Danygraig Primary School, a few playing fields to the east, a lovely little park for relaxing ; a doctors surgery, some clubs and public houses. Also a grave yard, churches and some handy shops with take away food shops ( Indian, Chinese etc ) on Port Tennant Road. There is a 550-car space Park and Ride site just south of the district, off Fabian Way with dedicated buses to Swansea city centre. There is a new bridge over fabian way linking Port Tennant to the docks and SA1 area. The Killvey woodland is a great place to walk a see the panoramic views of Swansea bay and beyond. There are horses stables on the side of the mountain and hotels car dealerships, petrol stations, post offices all within Port Tennant. The Tir John landfill site and adjacent Civic amenity site is located east of the residential area.
The neighbouring areas are Crymlyn Burrows, Crymlyn Bog, Kilvey Community Woodland, Swansea Docks and St. Thomas.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#port-eynon">
            <name>Port-Eynon</name>
            <lat>51.547634</lat>
            <lon>-4.215976</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#port-eynon point">
            <name>Port-Eynon Point</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#poundffald">
            <name>Poundffald</name>
            <lat>51.6297672</lat>
            <lon>-4.0714912</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#pyle">
            <name>Pyle</name>
            <lat>51.528762</lat>
            <lon>-3.69316</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyle">Pyle (Welsh: Y P&#xEE;l ) is a village and community in Bridgend county borough, Wales. This large village is served by the A48 road, and lies less than one mile from Junction 37 of the M4 motorway, and is therefore only a half-hour journey from the capital city of Wales, Cardiff; in fact it lies approximately equidistant between the capital (Cardiff) and the second city (Swansea). The nearest town is the seaside resort of Porthcawl. Within the Community, to the northeast of Pyle, is the adjoining settlement of Kenfig Hill.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#rallt">
            <name>Rallt</name>
            <lat>53.1182351</lat>
            <lon>-4.1294653</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#reynoldston">
            <name>Reynoldston</name>
            <lat>51.587465</lat>
            <lon>-4.195722</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reynoldston">Pentref a chymuned ar benrhyn G&#x175;yr, yn sir Abertawe, yw Reynoldston. Roedd poblogaeth y gymuned yn 2001 yn 430.
Saif Reynoldston yng nghanol Penrhyn G&#x175;yr, ychydig i'r gogledd o'r briffordd A4118, yn yr hyn oedd yn hanesyddol yn rhan Seisnig G&#x175;yr. Ceir colofn garreg o'r 9fed ganrif yn Eglwys Sant Si&#xF4;r.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#rhossili">
            <name>Rhossili</name>
            <lat>51.5690465</lat>
            <lon>-4.2868132</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhossili">Rhossili (Welsh: Rhosili) is a small village and community on the southwestern tip of the Gower Peninsula in Swansea. It is within an area designated as the first Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty in the United Kingdom. The village has a community council and is part of the Gower parliamentary constituency, and the Gower electoral ward.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#rhyd-y-gwin">
            <name>Rhyd-y-gwin</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#sandylane">
            <name>Sandylane</name>
            <lat>52.956445</lat>
            <lon>-2.893017</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#scurlage">
            <name>Scurlage</name>
            <lat>51.566746</lat>
            <lon>-4.216944</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#sketty">
            <name>Sketty</name>
            <lat>51.618165</lat>
            <lon>-3.986448</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sketty">The suburban district of Sketty (Welsh: Sgeti) is located about 2 miles (3.2 km) to the west of the Swansea city centre on Gower Road. Sketty falls within the Sketty council ward of Swansea.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#southgate">
            <name>Southgate</name>
            <lat>51.5724655</lat>
            <lon>-4.0917658</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southgate">Southgate, South Gate or SouthGate may refer to:</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southgate">Gallai Southgate gyfeirio at un o sawl lle neu beth:
Cymru
Southgate, Abertawe
Southgate, Ceredigion
Southgate, Llundain</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#st thomas">
            <name>St Thomas</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#stembridge">
            <name>Stembridge</name>
            <lat>51.649966</lat>
            <lon>-3.9756109</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#swansea">
            <name>Swansea</name>
            <lat>51.62144</lat>
            <lon>-3.943646</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swansea">Swansea (/&#x2C8;sw&#x252;nzi/ SWON-zee; Welsh: Abertawe [ab&#x25B;r&#x2C8;tau&#x25B;], "mouth of the Tawe"), officially known as the City and County of Swansea, is a coastal city and county in Wales. It is Wales's second largest city and the UK's twenty-sixth largest city. Swansea lies within the historic county boundaries of Glamorgan. Situated on the sandy South West Wales coast, the county area includes the Gower Peninsula and the Lliw uplands. The City and County of Swansea had a population of 239,000 in 2011, making it the second most populous local authority area in Wales after Cardiff. During its 19th-century industrial heyday, Swansea was a key centre of the copper industry, earning the nickname 'Copperopolis'.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swansea">Swansea yw'r enw Saesneg am ddinas a sir Abertawe, Cymru.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#swansea (abertawe)">
            <name>Swansea (Abertawe)</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#three crosses">
            <name>Three Crosses</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three Crosses">Three Crosses (Lithuanian: Trys kry&#x17E;iai) is a prominent monument in Vilnius, Lithuania, on the Hill of Three Crosses, originally known as the Bleak Hill (Lithuanian: Plikasis kalnas), in Kalnai Park. According to a legend, seven Franciscan friars were beheaded on top of this hill. Wooden crosses were built in the location since the early 17th century. It soon became a symbol of the city and an integral part of the city's skyline. As wood rots, the crosses needed to be periodically replaced. In 1916, a concrete monument was designed by Polish&#x2013;Lithuanian architect and sculptor Antoni Wiwulski. It was torn down in 1950 by order of the Soviet authorities. A new monument designed by Henrikas &#x160;ilgalis was erected in its place in 1989. The monument was depicted on 50 litas banknote. A spectacular panorama of the Vilnius Old Town can be observed from a small observation deck at the base of the crosses.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#tircanol">
            <name>Tircanol</name>
            <lat>51.6730928</lat>
            <lon>-3.9226903</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#tirdeunaw">
            <name>Tirdeunaw</name>
            <lat>51.654841</lat>
            <lon>-3.951863</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tirdeunaw">Ardal ar gyrion gogleddol dinas Abertawe, heb fod ymhell o Dreforys yw Tirdeunaw. Mae gan yr ardal gysylltiadau da gyda'r M4 i'r gogledd a Phenrhyn G&#x175;yr i'r gorllewin.
Bellach mae Tirdeunaw yn ymestyn o groes Capel Caersalem ar hyd Heol Llangyfelach hyd ben y bryn uwchben Llangyfelach. Arferai ymestyn i ben uchaf Treboeth ac roedd ganddo swyddfa bost ac ysgol gynradd.
Mae dros 400 o blant yn mynychu'r ysgol, sef Ysgol Gynradd Gymraeg Tirdeunaw, y drws nesaf at Ysgol Gymunedol Daniel James. Ceir yno hefyd ganolfan hamdden, un siop trin gwallt a deintydd. Bellach, mae yna gae p&#xEA;l-droed newydd o'r enw 'Play Football' hefyd.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#townhill">
            <name>Townhill</name>
            <lat>51.627415</lat>
            <lon>-3.970862</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Townhill">Townhill can refer to:
An area in the town of Hamilton, South Lanarkshire, Scotland
Townhill, Fife, a village in Scotland
Townhill, Swansea, an electoral ward and community and hill in Wales
Townhill Park, a suburb of Southampton surrounding Townhill Park House
Townhill, County Fermanagh, a townland in County Fermanagh, Northern Ireland</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Townhill">Cymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Abertawe yw Townhill. Adeiladwyd y rhan fwyaf o'r tai yma yn ystod yr 20fed ganrif. Roedd y boblogaeth yn 2001 yn 8,443.
Mae Townhill yn adral fryniog, ac mae rhai o'i strydoedd yn serth iawn. Ffurfir yr ardal gan fryn o garreg dywod ychydig i'r gogledd o ganol y ddinas, a'i gopa tua 175m uwch lefel y m&#xF4;r. Ceir ystad dai Townhill o amgylch y copa a'r gogledd-orllewin, ac ardal Mayhill ar y llechweddau i'r gogledd-ddwyrain.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#trallwn">
            <name>Trallwn</name>
            <lat>51.6086478</lat>
            <lon>-3.3315699</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trallwn">Trallwn is a common place name in Wales. Places include:
Trallwn in Pontypridd
Trallwn near Swansea.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#tre-boeth">
            <name>Tre-boeth</name>
            <lat>51.648468</lat>
            <lon>-3.948173</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ty-coch">
            <name>Ty-coch</name>
            <lat>51.6370656</lat>
            <lon>-3.0255813</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ty-draw">
            <name>Ty-draw</name>
            <lat>51.4491674</lat>
            <lon>-3.5252476</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#tyn-y-cwm">
            <name>Tyn-y-cwm</name>
            <lat>52.4213123</lat>
            <lon>-3.6712361</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#uplands">
            <name>Uplands</name>
            <lat>51.61789</lat>
            <lon>-3.972711</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uplands">Cymuned ym mwrdeisdref sirol Abertawe yw Uplands. Saif tua milltir i'r gorllewin o ganol dinas Abertawe ac ar lan y m&#xF4;r, o gwmpas y briffordd A4118, sy'n cysylltu canol Abertawe a Sgeti. Roedd y boblogaeth yn 2001 yn 13,355.
Magwyd Dylan Thomas yma, yn rhif 5, Cwmdonkin Drive. Un arall a fagwyd yma oedd y gwleidydd Michael Heseltine.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#upper killay">
            <name>Upper Killay</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#waunarlwydd">
            <name>Waunarlwydd</name>
            <lat>51.639227</lat>
            <lon>-4.014005</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waunarlwydd">Waunarlwydd (English: The Lord's Meadow &#x2013; arlwydd is a local variant of arglwydd) is a village in Swansea, Wales, falling within the Cockett ward.
A mostly residential area, despite its expanding size the village has the feeling of a small community.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#waungron">
            <name>Waungron</name>
            <lat>51.7499619</lat>
            <lon>-3.6129114</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#wern">
            <name>Wern</name>
            <lat>52.716432</lat>
            <lon>-3.106802</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wern">Wern is a river of Bavaria, Germany.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#wern-olau">
            <name>Wern-olau</name>
            <lat>51.6910548</lat>
            <lon>-3.7810059</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#wernffrwd">
            <name>Wernffrwd</name>
            <lat>51.6242234</lat>
            <lon>-4.1433837</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wernffrwd">Wernffrwd (Gwernffrwd) is a village in the south of Wales. It is located approximately 8.5 miles (13.7 km) from Swansea, and is within the Community of Llanrhidian Higher.
The village is situated in the north of the Gower Peninsula, overlooking the Loughor Estuary and consists of lower and upper Wernffrwd. The majority of the houses can be found in the lower part of the village, as does the church of Saint David's which can be found on the marsh road which skirts the village.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#west cross">
            <name>West Cross</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West Cross">West Cross is a suburban area of Swansea, Wales, located to the south of Swansea city centre, near Mumbles falling within the West Cross ward.
A high majority of the homes are Council built, but many have been sold to the occupiers in the Council's right to buy policy scheme during the 1970s and 1980s. Along with homes being bought, the Council had to upgrade a number of the houses during the 1980s, as they were of the BISF (British Iron and Steel Federation) prefabricated design and had to be brought up to current safety standards by removing asbestos insulation and replacing the structure rods. Along with the Council designed/built homes, private homes were built (by home development companies) from the 1950s and 1960s onwards. The area also includes: two parks, three schools, two pubs and various small (convenience) stores.
Ysgol Gynradd Gymraeg Llwynderw, a Welsh-medium primary school, relocated from its temporary premises in Singleton Park to West Cross Lane in West Cross in September 2008. The school serves the Swansea West area and is now housed in modern purpose built premises at West Cross.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#whiteford point">
            <name>Whiteford Point</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#winsh-wen">
            <name>Winsh-wen</name>
            <lat>51.650408</lat>
            <lon>-3.899885</lon>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#worms head">
            <name>Worms Head</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ynus-tawelog">
            <name>Ynus-tawelog</name>
            <lat/>
            <lon/>
            <wikipedia/>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ynysforgan">
            <name>Ynysforgan</name>
            <lat>51.6809847</lat>
            <lon>-3.9174577</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ynysforgan">Ynysforgan is a village in Swansea, Glamorgan, Wales. It lies just off Junction 45 of the M4 motorway, geographically between Morriston and Ynystawe. The origins of its name are not known for certain but ynys is Welsh for a river-meadow (i.e., an "island" &#x2013; the main meaning of ynys &#x2013; in otherwise marshier ground beside a river) and Forgan is a mutation of the name Morgan; a reasonable translation of the name would therefore be Morgan's Meadow. The River Tawe flows past Ynysforgan so it is not unreasonable to speculate that it is the river in question. Several other nearby locations also use the term Ynys in their names including Ynystawe (the neighbouring village to Ynysforgan), Ynystanglws Farm (near Ynystawe), and Ynysmeudwy (near Pontardawe).
However, as historically insignificant as Ynysforgan may seem it holds a hidden gem unknown to most locals and has its name embedded in the annals of Welsh time. In the latter part of the Middle Ages (circa 1330 - 1403) Ynysforgan was the home of Hopcyn ap Tomas ab Einion. This clearly indicates the name Ynysforgan extends back further than the 15th century and given the 'modernisation' of language it's conceivable its name is derived from old Welsh. Historians have speculated that ab Einion was responsible for a manuscript titled the Red Book of Hergest which is one of the most important medieval Welsh language manuscripts. Furthermore, in 1403 ab Einion was summoned to Carmarthen by none other than Owain Glynd&#x175;r, the last true Prince of Wales to shed light on his fate by bringing his knowledge and expertise to bare by interpreting old bardic prophecies.[1] Click this link to view a commemorative stone dedicated to ab Einion located in Ynystawe Park.
Before 1963 Ynysforgan essentially comprised the main Swansea to Brecon road (now Clydach Road) with houses on either side. It is interesting to note the 1911 census shows the address as 'Clydack Road'. The 'newer' houses behind Clydach Road were built in late 1960 starting with Garth View, followed by Elizabeth Close, Ian's Walk and Orpheus Road. The builders name was Emrys Davies of Neath who was a sole trader employing skilled tradesmen. It is believed that the road names Elizabeth Close, Ian's Walk and Andrews Crescent are attributable to Mr Davies' relatives. Garth View takes its name from its aspect facing the hill opposite, known colloquially as 'The Garth'. Orpheus Road is probably in recognition of the famous Morriston Orpheus Choir.
The old Swansea Tram system extended up the Swansea valley as far as Llanllienwen Road where there was a halt. With the building of the M4 motorway in 1973 the geography of Ynysforgan changed dramatically. The motorway essentially cut the village in two resulting in the demolition of the old Sunday School which stood (roughly) in the vicinity of the M4 exit slip road straight on from Clydach Road and a new Sunday school was built at the top of Garth View and Christopher Road.
Up until the mid-1970s there stood a grand house - Glyncollen - in its own grounds at the top of Garth View. Glyncollen was originally accessed by a long drive that joined the lower end of Llanllienwen Road, but this access was blocked when the motorway divided the village. In the 1930s Glyncollen House was the residence of the late Captain Sidney Davies, Managing Director of the Forest and Worcester Tinplate Works at Morriston - a brother of the late Alderman D. J. Davies of "Firgrove", Llanllienwen Road, a former Mayor of Swansea. He was followed as owner-occupier by the late Doctor and Mrs. N. E. Edwards-Jones, in the 1940s. The house was abandoned in the early 1970s and fell into ruin, only to be demolished later that decade. The grounds were taken over by the council and became a local amenity.
Ynysforgan used to lie on both the main Brecon to Swansea Canal which was navigable until the late 1950s and a Swansea Valley railway line. The canal was filled in and covered over in the 1960s and the route of the railway line has now been used as the Swansea valley by-pass road. There were several relics of World War II such as pillboxes and manholes along the canal: these were demolished when the canal was filled in.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ynysforgan">Pentref bychan yn Sir Abertawe yw Ynysforgan. Fe'i lleolir i'r gogledd o ddinas Abertawe fymryn i'r de o Glydach. Rhed yr M4 heibio i'r de o'r pentref.
Gyferbyn ag Ynysforgan ceir Ynysdawe. Roedd gan y ddau le ran amlwg ym mywyd diwylliannol Morgannwg yn yr Oesoedd Canol am fod dau gartref y Tomasiaid yn gorwedd yno, un yn Ynysforgan a'r llall yn Ynysdawe. Yr enwocaf o'r teulu oedd Hopcyn ap Tomas (tua 1350 - 1400au), casglwr llawysgrifau, brudiwr a noddwr beirdd. Yn &#xF4;l traddodiad galwodd Owain Glynd&#x175;r am ei gyngor fel brudiwr yn 1403 ac roedd Llyfr Coch Hergest a nifer o lawysgrifau eraill yn ei feddiant.</wikipedia>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ynystawe">
            <name>Ynystawe</name>
            <lat>51.690074</lat>
            <lon>-3.905167</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ynystawe">Ynystawe (also Ynysdawe in Welsh; Welsh pronunciation: [&#x268;&#x31E;n&#x268;&#x31E;s.ta&#x28A;.&#x25B;]) is a small village in the City and County of Swansea in Wales, in the electoral ward of Morriston. It is centred half a mile (1 km) north of Junction 45 of the M4 motorway, between Ynysforgan and Clydach in the lower Swansea Valley. The Welsh name Ynystawe or Ynysdawe derives from ynys, meaning "island" or "river-meadow", and Tawe, the name of the river running immediately to the east and which gives the Welsh name of Swansea, Abertawe.

</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia/>
        </town>
        <town id="swansea#ystradgynlais">
            <name>Ystradgynlais</name>
            <lat>51.779621</lat>
            <lon>-3.753603</lon>
            <wikipedia lang="en" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ystradgynlais">Ystradgynlais (Welsh: [&#x2CC;&#x259;sdrad&#x2C8;&#x261;&#x259;nlais], English /&#x2CC;&#x28C;str&#x259;d&#x2C8;&#x261;&#x28C;nla&#x26A;s/) is a town on the River Tawe in southwest Powys. The town, which is the largest in the historic county of Brecknockshire and the second largest in the administrative area of Powys, grew around the ironmaking, coal mining and watchmaking industries.</wikipedia>
            <wikipedia lang="cy" href="https://cy.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ystradgynlais">Tref yn ne-orllewin Powys, yng Nghwm Tawe Uchaf, yw Ystradgynlais.</wikipedia>
        </town>
    </towns>
</county>
